2 Ancient Origins

Modern theories of panpsychism have their roots in the mythology and spiritualism of the pre-classical world. For the Greeks, this worldview was embodied in the writings of Homer and Hesiod. Their work, combined with elements of Egyptian theology and Eastern philosophy, formed a potent context for the emergence of distinctively Western approaches to mind and reality. These precursors all contained aspects of animistic thinking, and thus Greek philosophy emerged from within a panpsychist milieu. We are not surprised, then, to find relatively blunt statements of panpsychism in the earliest Greek philosophers, and more subtle and sophisticated approaches in the later thinkers. Panpsychism remained strong into the Hellenistic era, and even found its way, indirectly, into early Christian theology.

2.1 Ancient Greece and the “Hylozoist” Tradition—the Pre-Socratics

The pre-Socratic era covered a range of roughly 200 years, from the emergence of Thales’ philosophy circa 600 BC to the death of Democritus in 370 BC. There were a dozen or so major Greek philosophers in this time frame, and at least twice as many lesser ones; collectively they established basic framework of philosophical thinking that would be fleshed out by Socrates, Plato, and Aristotle. The panpsychist milieu into which these individuals were born shows itself in their clear and unambiguous statements. Some form of panpsychism seems to have been taken for granted by nearly all major pre-Socratics. Hence they provide not arguments for it but rather their own interpretations of it, using their uniquely personal terminology and concepts.

The very first philosophers were the Milesians: Thales (625–545 BC), Anaximander (610–540 BC), and Anaximenes (585–525 BC). They concerned themselves not with mythology and theology but rather with fundamental metaphysical questions: What are things ultimately made of? Where did things come from? What are the guiding principles of the cosmos? How can we account for such things as life, motion, and the psyche? Before these men, such questions were evidently never addressed in a systematic way.

At its most fundamental level, the world of the Milesians was composed of things that move. Hence among their most basic questions were “What is the essence of a thing?” and “What causes motion?” They seemed to have developed an intuitive view that the apparent plurality of things belied an underlying commonality or unity. This was a rational conclusion, given the fact that we live in a unitary cosmos and that things seem to be connected and even convertible into other things—as when wood burns and becomes fire, or when soil transforms into plant life, or when animals ingest and incorporate various foods and drinks. Also undeniable was the fact that certain things had the power of self-motion: humans, animals, some plants, stars, the moon, and various other astronomical objects. Finally, the cosmos seemed, upon reflection, to be much less arbitrary than portrayed by Homer and Hesiod. Events occurred not by divine mandate, but rather in a systematic and orderly manner. There were patterns of action in the universe, and these patterns indicated a kind of logic to things—to use their word, a logos. The flow of events in the world, furthermore, seemed to work in a specific direction, toward some undefined goal (telos). The apparently vast, diverse, and chaotic cosmos, then, was in reality a single moving substance in a diversity of forms, self-driven in some sense, guided by a higher logos, and moving toward a given end.

The Milesian worldview, therefore, possessed three fundamental qualities: (1) It reflected a rational order, governed by a logos, and thus formed a coherent and comprehensible system. (2) It was evolutionary, in the sense that things moved through the world and developed or changed over time, toward a telos or end. (3) It was inherently animated.^1 The rationality of their metaphysics was manifest as a materialist monism—they each sought to reduce the plurality of things to a single underlying substance or entity. This entity had certain definite characteristics, foremost of which was its capability of producing the movement, life, and soul that were apparent in the everyday world. If everything is ultimately one, and if that one yields spontaneity and life, then a reasonable conclusion is that everything possesses these qualities to some degree. For the Milesians, this was the most compelling and intuitive option. If one were to disagree, one would assume the burden of proof to show, at least, (a) why some things have life and other do not and (b) how such a phenomenon as life might plausibly emerge over the course of time from a lifeless substrate. Apparently no one in ancient Greece argued for such a position. For the Milesians, matter (hyle) possessed life (zoe) as an essential quality. Something like hylozoism was simply accepted as a brute condition of reality. As Guthrie (1962–1981, volume 1: 145) explains, “the union of matter and spirit in a material substance … is [for the Milesians] an assumption that raises no doubts and calls for no argument or defense.”

Consider Thales, who was widely known for his panpsychist views. That he was also the first true Western philosopher demonstrates something of the significance of panpsychism in the early Greek worldview. Thales was famous for predicting a solar eclipse in 585 and for his theory that water was the cosmic arche, the fundamental principle underlying all material things. But of the few remaining fragments by him, two demonstrate his commitment to panpsychism. Both are found in Aristotle’s De anima. First, we have the passage on the lodestone (magnet):

Thales, according to what is related of him, seems to have regarded the soul as something endowed with the power of motion, if indeed he said that the lodestone has a soul because it moves iron. (405a19)

Here we have two distinct ideas: that the soul (psyche) is defined as that which moves or produces motion, and that the lodestone itself has a soul because it can attract iron. Consider first the concept of psyche. In addition to its common interpretation as soul, it has other important meanings and associations, including spirit, life, breath, and mind. The psyche was connected with the life energy of living things, with the divine animating spirit that produced motion in physical objects, and with the activity of the mind. At this early stage in philosophy there was not yet the distinction between having a soul, being alive, and possessing a mind; all these were treated more or less as equivalent.^2 To the pre-Socratics, psyche was as much mind-like as it was soul-like. In the first book of De anima Aristotle takes pains to note that most everyone before him, including Plato, did not clearly distinguish between soul and mind (nous). For example, we find the following passage on the views of Democritus: “Soul and mind are, he says, one and the same thing.” (405a10) And Anaxagoras “[only] seems to distinguish between soul and mind, but in practice he treats them as a single substance” (405a13). Psyche, then, is the energy that animates and produces movement in all things, including the movement of thoughts and ideas.

Humans and animals clearly possess psyche, and in a monist universe anything else that demonstrates the qualities of life—that is, to be self-moving or to cause motion—possesses it too. The lodestone clearly shows the power to move small bits of iron, a fact that must have been rather miraculous to the ancients. And yet the lodestone is obviously in many ways a rock like any other. That some rocks exhibit greater powers of psyche than others is comparable to the notion that humans are just animals of a certain type, and that they exhibit distinctive noetic powers. Apparently Thales concluded from this that all things possessed psyche, to a greater or lesser degree. We see this clearly in the second major fragment:

Certain thinkers say that soul is intermingled in the whole universe, and it is perhaps for that reason that Thales came to the opinion that all things are full of gods. (De anima, 411a7)

Aristotle, presumably following Thales, uses the word theon, which is translated as “gods.” The power of psyche was seen as a god-like, divine power, or perhaps as the power of the gods themselves. But why say “full of gods” (panta plere theon) and not “full of soul’? We can only speculate. Perhaps it was a nod to the mythological language of Homer. Or perhaps it was a strictly linguistic issue; perhaps it was awkward and inappropriate to claim that things were full of soul. In any case, souls are divine, the gods themselves are spirits and souls, and thus, for Thales, the two concepts are deeply interconnected.

Or perhaps Thales was being more exact than we give him credit for. It would seem that an essential quality of a god is that it is a single being, a unitary presence, with a singular sense of identity and personality. Psyche, on the other hand, seems like a relatively amorphous, diffused power—especially conceived as a power to move something, rather than a power to think. It may be that Thales was pointing to singular sense of identity in all things, a mental being and personality, which could simultaneously act, perceive, and move.

If we attempt to construct a rational argument for panpsychism from these two fragments, it would go something like this: Material objects—humans, animals, wind, sea, magnets, heavenly bodies—have the power of motion; they move either themselves or surrounding things. The material object we know most intimately—our own body—possesses an energy, called psyche, that accounts for our power. Under the assumption that the world is rational and that humans are not ontologically unique, a reasonable conclusion is that all things with a motive power also possess psyche. And in light of the fact that we live in a connected, unitary cosmos, it is difficult to explain why only certain material objects are ensouled and not others. Therefore, a reasonable conclusion is that all things possess psyche, to a greater or lesser degree. I will call this the Indwelling Powers argument for panpsychism. It is the first of several that we find throughout history.

Like Thales, Anaximenes argued for a monist worldview, but with an underlying principle of air (pneuma). The word pneuma has an interesting array of meanings, some of which are strikingly similar to those of psyche. Besides “air,” pneuma can also mean “breath,” “soul,” “spirit,” or “mind.” Whereas the primary meaning of psyche is “mind” or “soul,” the primary meaning of pneuma seems to be “breath,” as in “breath of life.” For Anaximenes, the breath of life was the living, animating principle of all things. This again was a logical conclusion. In every animal, breath equals life: no air, no life; no life, no breath. And air seems to be everywhere, as does motion, and so it is not unreasonable to argue that pneuma is the underlying principle or arche of the cosmos.

Anaximenes, though, seems to offer a different kind of argument for panpsychism than Thales. He saw in air a principle of continuity throughout all things. If this substance can be argued to account for our soul/mind, and given that air is omnipresent, then a similar manifestation is likely to be present everywhere. I will call this the Argument by Continuity. Panpsychism is a natural and logical position to hold in a monistic worldview. In fact, to be a monist and dispute the Continuity argument demands either an explanation of the unique emergence of mind—no small matter—or a denial of mind altogether. That the Continuity argument differs from the Indwelling Powers argument of Thales is clear: Thales makes no connection between panpsychism and his arche of water, nor does water account for the existence of soul. Anaximenes, by contrast, fundamentally links his arche of air to mind/psyche. Both arguments, however, appeal to an analogy with basic human experiences of our own minds and selves.^3

As it happens, Anaximenes also makes a kind of appeal to the concept of indwelling power. Air, in the form of soul, has a cohesive power in the world. It holds things together, animates them, and maintains their existence as discrete objects enduring over time. “As our soul … being air, holds us together and controls us, so does [breath] and air enclose the whole world.”^4 But this is supplemental to, and independent of, his primary argument from continuity.

The concept of pneuma, inaugurated by Anaximenes, was seminal. It was taken up by Aristotle in his own quasi-panpsychist theory, and later, to a greater degree, by the Stoics. They gave it a precise elemental structure, and assigned it a specific animating role in the universe. Later still, it seems to have been the inspiration for the Holy Spirit of the Bible; as I will explain, in the original Greek of the New Testament, the term for “spirit” was pneuma.

Chronologically, the next major philosopher after the Milesians was the enigmatic Pythagoras (570–495 BC), who exerted much influence within Greek society generally. Unfortunately, little is known of him with certainty. He apparently lectured on mathematics, ethics, health, and metaphysics. Yet, like Socrates, he wrote nothing. His closest followers formed a secretive cult, and thus we have few direct accounts of him. Most of what is known is indirect and anecdotal. Circa 50 BC, Cicero recounted that Pythagoras “held that mind was present and active throughout the whole universe, and that our minds were a part of it” (On the Nature of the Gods, I, 26–28). This “divine mind” or “pure spirit” was seen as “infused and imprisoned in the world.” We also know that Pythagoras associated numbers with the cosmic arche. This is significant because, as Aetius informs us, Pythagoras “takes number as an equivalent for intelligence” (Placita iv.2).^5 Other reports attribute to Pythagoras the view that everything is intelligent, but this is difficult to confirm with much certainty. It seems clear that he held to a mystic, pan-spiritual view of the universe, and thus that he probably endorsed some variation of a panpsychist philosophy.

Parmenides (545–460 BC) developed ingenious arguments for the view that only Being is possible and therefore that only Being exists. This entails that Becoming, conceived as a change from non-being to being (or vice versa), doesn’t exist—because non-being is not possible. The existence of change in the world is an illusion, he said; therefore motion, and even time itself, are also illusory. This was a radical view, as it directly contracted the centrality of the concept of motion within natural philosophy.

Also, since thinking was acknowledged by Parmenides to be an undeniable aspect of reality, it followed that thought, or mind, must be an essential aspect of Being. The otherwise homogeneous and unchanging Being has this unique, positive property, which apparently has a special ontological standing—perhaps due to its self-evident and undeniable nature. Parmenides concludes, then, not merely that Being “has” thought, but that Being is thought. There are two central fragments that explicitly make this claim, and both are subject to an unusually wide range of interpretations and translations. The first is fragment 3, transliterated from the Greek as To gar auto noein estin te kai einai. Among many translations, one finds the following:

For it is the same thing to think and to be. (Freeman 1948: 42)

What is … is identical with the thought that recognizes it. (Lloyd 1959: 327)

For the same things can be thought of and can be. (Barnes 1987: 132)

Thinking and being are the same. (Reeve and Miller 2006: 13)

Parmenides is making an identity between thought and being, but it is a difficult matter to understand in what sense the two things are “the same.” There are at least two interpretations. First is a sort of metaphysical idealism: that all being is of the nature of a thought, or a mental activity. In this sense it provides an interesting anticipation of the much later work of Berkeley. But there is a second, panpsychist interpretation: that all things can be said to think. But even this is problematic because, for Parmenides, it is not clear that there truly are distinct things in the world; rather, there seems to be only the one monistic Being. If all things, as a whole, think, then such a view would constitute a kind of pan-noetic ontology—something like a panentheism or world-soul, but without personality, just pure thought. This is arguably not panpsychism, which, as defined in chapter 1, requires things individually to possess mind. Parmenides’ intentions on this point are vague.

Support for the second interpretation comes from Coxon (1986: 181), who remarks, regarding this fragment, that “the neoplatonic belief that Parmenides identified Being with Mind was well-founded.” Additional supporting evidence comes from Xenophanes’ assessment of God as a kind of cosmic mind; “[this] may also be regarded as suggesting that Parmenides envisaged Being as Intelligence.” Xenophanes, incidentally, was a “panzoist,” according to Cleve (1969: 21).

Long also argues for a strong “identity” reading of this fragment, one in which “being itself is or has a mind” (1996: 133). The non-identity reading, advanced by some, is untenable because it virtually eliminates mind from the cosmos. Confirming the near-universal stance on panpsychism at the time, Long adds that “no Greek philosopher prior to and immediately posterior to Parmenides treated reality as lifeless and mindless” (140).

The second fragment continues the same line of thinking, though with equally ambiguous results: Tauton d’ esti noein te kai ounechen esti noema (fragment 8, line 34). Here we find no direct mention of einai (“being”), but rather a focus on noein (“thinking”) and noema (“thought” or “consciousness”). The identification is made between thinking and the object of thought:

Therefore thinking, and that by reason of which thought exists, are one and the same thing. (Smith 1934: 16–17)

To think is the same as the thought that It Is. (Freeman 1948: 44)

Thinking and the object of thought are the same. (Cleve 1969: 537)

The same thing are thinking and a thought that it is. (Barnes 1987: 135)

Thinking and the thought that it is are the same. (Reeve and Miller 2006: 14)

Long says that this fragment, because it equates the object of thought (i.e., being) with thinking, “does give explicit testimony for the mind/being identity reading” (1996: 136).

Cleve is sensitive to the panpsychist implications in these two fragments. He observes that being, though technically unextended and incorporeal, is yet permeated by thought: “being itself … is inextensive incorporeal thinking that is present whole and undivided in each and every part of seeming space” (1969: 536). He adds that “the only being is consciousness, noema, that, however, must not be split into act of thinking and content of thinking” (537). Thus it seems clear that thought permeates Being, and that anything that exists must also be said to be identical with thought. Since the metaphysical status of distinct things is unclear, we cannot determine the degree to which Parmenides’ stance is true panpsychism. Yet in view of the “hylozoist” milieu into which he was born, it seems to be the most likely interpretation.

Parmenides’ notion that thought is identical to being anticipates the discussion in Sophist in which Plato puts forth a similar view: that the Form of Being possesses the qualities of “understanding, intelligence, life, and soul” (249a). As we know, Plato held Parmenides in high regard, and thus it isn’t surprising to find him incorporating elements of his predecessor’s ontology.

In opposition to Parmenides’ static world of pure Being, Heraclitus (505–450 BC) conceived a worldview in which change and motion were the essential reality. In a fitting manner, fire became his arche. To the ancient Greeks, fire was a form of pure energy, and it is interesting that Heraclitus developed a distinctively energeticist worldview some 2,300 years before it became fashionable in physics.

Fire, like the pneuma of Anaximenes, was associated with life-energy and hence spirit and soul. Significantly, Heraclitus referred to this fire not merely as pyr but as pyr aeizoon—ever-living fire. Consequently, this spiritual life-energy was seen as responsible for creating and sustaining everything. Diogenes Laertius reports in his Lives of the Philosophers that Heraclitus held to the view that “all things are full of souls and spirits” (IX: 5–12). Again, ensoulment is universal and associated with motion and change.

More specifically, the pyr aeizoon possesses a kind of intelligence or cognitive ability. In the only directly relevant fragment, Heraclitus says that “thinking is common to all” (fragment 113; Barnes 1987: 109). He evidently followed the logic of his predecessors in believing that, in a monist cosmos, intelligent spirit or life must exist in all things, if they exist anywhere. This is clearly Long’s interpretation: “Heraclitus takes thinking … to be implicit in the things that are (the processes of nature)” (1996: 131). In sum, we have here a combination of the Indwelling Powers argument—in the energy of the pyr aeizoon—and the Continuity argument, in which pyr constitutes all things.

Heraclitus and Parmenides lived at about the same time, and their two opposing philosophies must have created something of a crisis in Greek intellectual circles. Each seemed independently plausible, yet they were profoundly incompatible. In response, Empedocles and Anaxagoras each sought, in different ways, to resolve this conflict. They concluded that the problem lay in the assumption of monism. Thus, each articulated a pluralist worldview with more than one fundamental substance. For Empedocles, it was the four elements, Earth, Water, Air, and Fire. For Anaxagoras, it was an infinity of substances. But both men were united in their panpsychist outlooks. As Long states, “Anaxagoras most forcefully and Empedocles more obliquely treat intelligent life as basic to reality” (131).

Anaxagoras, however, was evidently not content with postulating infinitely many substances of the world, and so he concluded that a single overarching principle was needed to provide unity to the whole system. This principle was nous, or mind. This introduction of the term nous into philosophy is evidence of a deepening distinction among the various meanings associated with psyche and pneuma. Nous is more related to the concept of mind in the sense of the human mind or reason, while remaining distinct from logos, which is also sometimes translated as “reason.” Nous represents, furthermore, a kind of unity of thought—a unified entity, a mind, that is the subject of thinking.

Mind, for Anaxagoras, is ubiquitous, omnipresent, and even god-like:

Mind is something infinite and self-controlling … . For it is the finest of all things and the purest, and it possesses all knowledge about everything, and it has the greatest strength. … And mind arranged everything—what was to be, and what was, and what now is, and what will be … . (in Barnes 1987: 227–228)

The action of mind is analogous to a rotation or a turning: “And mind controlled the whole revolution, so that it revolved in the first place.” Thus we see that mind causes motion, as it had for the earlier thinkers. But this motion is of a specific kind, namely circular. It furthermore is a creative force, bringing concrete things into existence.

Anaxagoras determined that mind, as a universal quality, existed in varying degrees: “All mind, both great and small, is alike.” Here we see a form of pluralism that is tempered by a fundamental unity of the nature of the diverse minds. Mind is present in greater and lesser forms, yet they all share some common basis in nous. The lesser minds are not ontologically different than the greater. It is a question of degree.

Finally we have one further relevant citation, from Aristotle. In Metaphysics we find the following view attributed to Anaxagoras: “just as in animals, so in nature, mind is present and responsible for the world” (984b15). The mind that is ubiquitous is not just some amorphous, abstract mind; it is essentially like that of animals, i.e., an animated soul or spirit. Mind is present both in the whole of the cosmos and in the specific objects. This implies a multi-level system of mind, occurring distinctly in different levels of structured matter.

Cleve (1969) addresses this issue of individual minds in detail. Whereas some commentators see Anaxagoras’ nous as existing only in a cosmic sense, Cleve sees it surrounding and penetrating all matter. On his view, the plural elements (moiras) never exist without some conjoining nous: “Anaxagoras, too, is a panzoist, i.e. one to whom body and consciousness are still a unity … . The notion of a ‘matter without consciousness’ … [does] not exist for [him].” (321) He adds that “every molecule is surrounded by Nous on all sides” (207). As to the question of distinct individual minds, he suggests that “a piece of Nous [could] be in a molecule—in the same sense as a fellow locked in a prison ‘is in’” (269). In this interpretation, then, Nous surrounds all matter, and individual nous resides in at least some molecular elements. This is clearly a panpsychist metaphysic.

The pluralism of Empedocles (495–435 BC) was more modest. He argued that a small set of elements sufficed to explain the material nature of the world. Probably borrowing from his predecessors, he took water, air, and fire, added a fourth element, earth, and composed a four-part elemental scheme that held for nearly 2,000 years. As for Anaxagoras, Empedocles believed that the elements required an overarching principle of organization. In his case it was not nous but rather a system of dual forces, designated Philotes (“Love”) and Neikos (“Strife”). Love was the power of attraction and cohesion, and Strife it’s opposite, namely, of repulsion and separation. It was clear to Empedocles that both were needed; if there were only attraction in the universe, all matter would be drawn together into a formless mass, something like a black hole. And if there were only repulsion, the four elements would be driven apart, never to unite into structured objects. He reasoned that there must be a balance of the two, in a kind of harmonic tension.

From the perspective of modern physics, Empedocles’ view is astonishingly accurate. His system was composed of matter and force or energy, just as we believe today. Love has an obvious counterpart in gravity, and physics has its own repulsive forces, namely, similar magnetic poles and similar electric charges (Coulomb’s Law). Even more surprising, physicists have recently discovered a cosmic repulsive force generated by a mysterious substance called “dark energy.” This substance has only one salient feature: a kind of anti-gravity force that serves to accelerate the expansion of the universe. It seems that Empedocles was more correct than he could have known.

Yet he was clearly no mechanistic materialist. Perhaps more than any other pre-Socratic, he made panpsychism central to his worldview.^6 Guthrie states that “it was in fact fundamental to Empedocles’ whole system that there is no distinction between animate and inanimate, and everything has some degree of awareness and power of discrimination” (1962–1981, volume 2: 233). The mere fact that Empedocles chose Love and Strife as his two central forces is clearly suggestive of his belief that animate powers were at work in the cosmos.

Explicit evidence of his panpsychism is found primarily in three fragments. In fragment 103 we read “tede men oun ioteti tyches pephroneken apanta”—“Thus by the will of chance, all things think.” (Barnes 1987: 178) This is an advance in philosophical reasoning. Earlier philosophers’ references to gods, souls, or spirit are absent, to be replaced by autonomous cosmic powers of attraction and repulsion, as we would have it today. The ability of all things to think is granted by tyches, interpreted either as the god Tyche or, more likely, as simply the process of chance or luck. Empedocles is saying, in effect, “By good fortune, all things are able to think.”

The second important passage comes from Aristotle: “Empedocles [says that the soul] is composed of all the elements and that each of them actually is a soul.” (De anima 404b11) The two relevant ideas here are (1) that souls (psychein) are material and composite, and (2) that each element, in itself, is ensouled. Clearly, if each element is a soul, and if these elements constitute the whole world, then all things are souls or soul-like. Empedocles thus seems view psyche in terms of mental activity and thinking rather than as a power of motion. Movement comes from the two central forces which, although animate, are apparently not psychein.

Third, we have a striking fragment recorded in Hippolytus’ Refutation of All Heresies (ca. 210 AD):

If thou shouldst plant these things in thy firm understanding and contemplate them with good will and unclouded attention, they will stand by thee for ever every one, and thou shalt gain many other things from them; … for know that all things have wisdom and a portion of thought. (fragment 110; Guthrie, volume 2: 230)

The final key phrase—panta gar isthi phronesin echein kai nomatos aisan—is, as usual, subject to varying translations. Barnes, for example, renders it as “for know that they all have thought and a share of mind” (163). Cleve offers this: “Do not forget, all things have mind and a share in cognition.” (369) By contrast, Freeman translates phronesin as “intelligence” (1948: 64). In any case, we find here a poetic passage that is at once beautiful and insightful. Empedocles is indicating that a particular method of thinking, a way of approaching the world in a sympathetic fashion (“with good will”), will yield abundant fruit. He is clearly advocating a way of thinking about things with clarity and compassion, centered on the idea that, like ourselves, “all things have wisdom.” Panpsychism is seen as the path to truth and lasting insight.

Empedocles thus relies on two variations of earlier arguments for panpsychism. First he employs the Indwelling Powers argument by claiming that everything has the power of thought. Mind is clearly an inherent part of his cosmic system, and as such it constitutes a kind of metaphysical first principle. The elements think, period. Thinking is a brute characteristic of matter and a power intrinsic to material reality. Second, he uses the Continuity argument in a pluralistic fashion, appealing to an inherent soul-nature of the four elements that constitute all things.

Finally, consider the atomist theory of Leucippus and Democritus. On their view, all things in the world consist of imperceptibly small, indivisible atoms (a-tomos, “uncuttables”) that move through otherwise empty space and interact via mechanical means to create large-scale material objects. Democritus claimed that not all atoms are alike, but that there are many different sizes and shapes, and that these differences account for the different physical properties of things.

It is sometimes believed that there is no place for mind or soul in the atomist universe. And in fact these philosophers did take the first steps away from a hylozoist interpretation. Cleve takes note of this point:

For the very first time, we have here the notion of “matter without consciousness.” Democritus (or Leucippus) forms the notion of atomoi apatheis, of “unfeeling atoms,” being the first to drop [in part] the idea of panzoism. (1969: 421)

However, these philosophers did not eliminate soul from the cosmos. Even though most kinds of atoms were completely unfeeling, one type—namely, that of spherical shape—was unique in that it possessed psyche and sensitivity. Aristotle explains that “those [atoms] which are spherical [Democritus] calls fire and soul” (De anima 404a2). The implied connection between soul and fire was evidently quite common in ancient Greece; both were seen as the most rarefied of substances, and often soul was considered to be made from elemental fire. The Democritean psyche was thus atomistic and material, like all things.^7

The crucial question is this: Which objects, in addition to humans, contain the spherical soul atoms? Aristotle continues:

Spherical atoms are identified with soul because atoms of that shape are most adapted to permeate everywhere, and to set all the other [atoms] moving by being themselves in movement. (404a5)

If soul atoms are everywhere—and not just everywhere in the human or animal body—the apparent conclusion is that all things have souls (argument by Continuity). Consistent with earlier theories of soul, there are clear implications here that soul-atoms are omnipresent and are the ultimate cause of motion. Perhaps they are not always everywhere, and perhaps they are not the only source of motion—this we cannot tell. Consequently, it is difficult to clearly determine the extent of panpsychism in atomism. But the concept of a soul-atom had a great deal of influence, both on ancient atomists, including Epicurus and Lucretius, and on panpsychist philosophers generally, even through the late 1800s. Circa 1870, William Clifford and others put forth panpsychist theories of “mind-stuff” that recall the ideas of Democritus.

It bears noting that the “hylozoism” of the pre-Socratics was of a subtle and implicit form. Apart from Heraclitus, who explicitly referred to life (zoe), the others spoke in terms of psyche, spirit, gods, and motion. These terms were broadly and implicitly associated with the phenomenon of life, and thus, in a loose sense, the pre-Socratics were hylozoists. ‘Hylopsychism’ would be a more appropriate term for their view, or perhaps even ‘hylotheism’. ‘Hylozoism’ carries a negative connotation in modern literature and is frequently used as a vague disparagement of aspects of Greek philosophy. But the term is misleading, and it is one more indication of the low regard—and poor understanding—of panpsychist philosophy. Surprisingly, the one ancient philosopher perhaps most deserving of the label ‘hylozoist’ is Plato, as I will now explain.

2.2 Plato

Socrates, Plato, and Aristotle collectively set philosophy forward on a new path of rationalism and logic. The consensus view that Plato was not a “primitive hylozoist” is typified by the following passage: “The hylozoism of the Milesians was no longer possible for Plato. Life (soul) and matter were not the same, and he sees soul as the self-moving principle which imparts its own motion to otherwise inert body, thus making it animate.” (Guthrie 1962–1981, volume 4: 420) But this statement is misleading, and the implication is arguably incorrect. There is very strong evidence that Plato was in fact a panpsychist or even hylozoist of sorts—or at least that this is the most rational interpretation of his metaphysical scheme.

Certainly Plato broke new ground, but in some ways there was less divergence than is generally acknowledged or understood. Given the panpsychist views of Plato’s esteemed predecessors, we should not be surprised to see elements of panpsychism in Plato himself. In fact he makes a number of statements that point toward such a view, even if he falls short of an outright endorsement. In the end, panpsychism seems to be the most plausible interpretation of his various beliefs.

First, though, I need to elaborate a bit on the status of the world-soul thesis. This concept, clearly and unambiguously held by Plato, is that the cosmos as a whole possesses a soul. This cosmic soul was constructed and set in place by the Demiurge, the creator god of the universe.^8 It is clear that a world-soul thesis doesn’t entail hylozoism, panpsychism, or anything like this. Panpsychism demands that individual objects, in themselves, be ensouled; a cosmic soul has an uncertain relation to any lesser souls. But a world-soul hypothesis is obviously compatible with such views. Of course Plato, like all ancient philosophers, took it for granted that humans possessed souls, and therefore that at least one sort of lesser being was also ensouled. A cosmos with both human souls and a world-soul is immediately in a strange situation: Two highly disparate entities are ensouled. This would seem to be a dubious and arbitrary metaphysical scheme. One would expect that other entities, perhaps many such, would also be ensouled. And in fact this is what we find in Plato.

I also note that my analysis is centered on Plato’s late works as representative of his mature thinking. He seems to have modified his perspective on ensoulment somewhere between his middle and late periods. It is significant that he moved from an ambiguous stance to a more consistent and more universal view of ensoulment in his later years.

As an example of Plato’s middle-period views, consider Phaedrus. In this dialogue he makes a distinction between things animate and inanimate. He notes, for example, that “every bodily object that is moved from outside has no soul” (245e), and that “all soul looks after all that lacks a soul” (246b). There would thus seem to be two distinct categories of things—those ensouled, and those without.

And yet at the same time Plato seems sympathetic to the view that something soul-like is present in, or associated with, apparently inanimate things. Socrates lectures in an unusual setting—outside of town in the shade of a large plane tree—and this inspires him to reflect on nature. Near the end of the dialogue he makes the rather surprising claim that nature was the original source of philosophy, and that the rocks and trees might themselves “speak the truth”:

[T]he priests of the temple of Zeus at Dodona say that the first prophecies were the words of an oak. Everyone who lived at that time, not being as wise as you young ones are today, found it rewarding enough in their simplicity to listen to an oak or even a stone, so long as it was telling the truth … . (275b)

On the one hand this can be read as a breaking away from the “simplicity” of the earlier, hylozoistic view. And yet there is a gentle chiding of the purported wisdom of the young philosophers; one senses a certain sympathy with the ancient ways of knowing nature.

Plato’s more explicit references to panpsychism are found in his later writings. The four primary sources—Sophist, Philebus, Timaeus, and Laws—are generally regarded as among his last works. In these we find three distinct arguments pointing toward a panpsychic universe. The fact that these come in the later works implies that they represent Plato’s final thinking on the matter and thus have a relatively strong degree of significance in his overall system of metaphysics.

I emphasize that these are not explicit arguments. Plato doesn’t explicitly draw a panpsychist conclusion in any of these works. And yet his arguments are individually and collectively consistent with such a worldview. More than this, they logically entail panpsychism. Significantly, nowhere in his late works does Plato deny this implication, and he avoids making fundamental distinctions between obviously animate and obviously inanimate things.^9 All this is indicative of, if not an outright endorsement, at least a strong sympathy with panpsychism.

For Plato, as for the pre-Socratics, the concept of soul was closely related to that of the mind. Psyche and nous are important concepts for him, and the difference in meaning between them is relatively small. Often they are used interchangeably, as if they were evident synonyms. A number of points support this view. Writing on Plato’s treatment in Phaedo—which is a primary text on the theory of the soul—Guthrie (1962–1981, volume 4: 421) states plainly that “in its pure state it [soul] was identical with nous.” Aristotle (De anima, 407a5) observes that “it is evident that Plato means the soul of the whole to be like the sort of soul which is called mind.” This is consistent with Aristotle’s overall discussion in book I of De anima, in which he argues that his predecessors have generally not distinguished between mind and soul. Plato himself, in Philebus, identifies soul as the necessary, though not sufficient, condition for mind: “no wisdom and reason without soul” (30d). In Timaeus we learn that “it is impossible for anything to come to possess intelligence apart from soul” (30b). All this is consistent with his famous tri-partition of the soul: rationality, spiritedness, and desire. The rational faculty is an intrinsic aspect of the soul, and thus we cannot speak of one without the other.

Now let us turn to the four primary texts. In Sophist, Plato investigates the nature and meaning of “being” in its entirety: “that which wholly is.” At the start of a somewhat complicated passage near the middle of the dialogue, the Visitor relates being to dynamis (“power” or “capacity”): “My notion would be, that anything which possesses any sort of power to affect another, or to be affected by another … has real existence; and I hold that the definition of being is simply power.” (247e)^10 Some lines later, the Visitor elaborates that being is “an active or passive energy, arising out of a certain power” (248b). This identification of being with power, or a “potent capacity,” recalls the pyr aeizoon, the ever-living fire, of Heraclitus; both refer to the energy inherent in all extant things. The Visitor then contrasts being (essence) with becoming (generation). The initial thought is that being is something static and fixed, whereas becoming is motion and change. Ultimately (249d), however, it is decided that this is misleading, and that one must “include both the moveable and the immoveable in his definition of being.” The moveable aspect of being reflects both its ability to act upon other things and to be known—a process that demands some change in the thing known. Consequently, “being” here must include both the realm of the changeless Forms and the dynamic phenomenal world as well; it refers to the sum total of reality.

This power of being—the movability and capability for active, dynamic change—draws on Plato’s notion that such power of self-originating motion is indicative of the presence of psyche. This idea recurs later in Laws (below), where Plato equates life and soul/mind with self-motion. But the important conclusion is this: If being has the power of self-generating motion, then such complete or perfect being (to pantelos on) must have not only an inherent psyche but also life and mind:

O heavens, can we ever be made to believe that motion [kinesi] and life [zoe] and soul [psyche] and mind [phronesi] are not present with perfect being? Can we imagine that, being is devoid of life and mind, and exists in awful unmeaningness an everlasting fixture? —That would be a dreadful thing to admit. (249a)

Plato insists, very explicitly, that all three things—life, mind, and soul—inhere in being. As if to reinforce the point, he then immediately emphasizes the issue again. He considers three different possibilities, dismissing all of them as “irrational”: that “[being] has mind and not life,” that “both [mind and life] inhere in perfect being, but that it has no soul,” and that “being has mind and life and soul, but although endowed with soul remains absolutely unmoved.” Reality itself—“that which wholly is”—thus necessarily possesses life, mind, and soul. This constitutes a first argument for the concept of ubiquitous soul, arising from metaphysical first principles.

This conclusion is not without difficulties. If everything possesses life, mind, and soul, then it would seem that all things possess such abilities as the power of self-motion and the power of thought. Plato doesn’t openly acknowledge these aspects of being. Yet it is certainly possible to expand the concepts of self-motion and thought so that they might encompass all material things. As we know, many of Plato’s predecessors did precisely this. All things respond dynamically and change in the face of external stimuli. They perceive; they sense; they are aware of what is going on around them. Even the very process of becoming can itself be seen as a kind of self-motion. Thus the argument is stated, and the implicit conclusion remains. Since neither the panpsychist conclusion nor its denial is addressed, we are left with an open question, at least in this dialogue. But in the absence of a clear denial, and especially in light of the other passages below, the panpsychist conclusion seems the more compelling.

In Philebus, Plato returns to the structure of his earlier Socratic dialogues. In the passages of interest—29a through 31b—Socrates and his two interlocutors are debating the relative standing of knowledge and pleasure as they relate to the good. In the process, they seek to place each of these two qualities into the proper metaphysical category.^11 The relevant passage comes with their discussion of knowledge, which is also referred to as intelligence, wisdom, and reason; we can infer that these qualities are closely related to the concept of psyche in general.

Socrates asks whether the structure of the universe was created by chance or by “order of a wonderful intelligence.” The answer comes that “reason arranges it all” (28d). He then explains that our human bodies are composed of the four elements—fire, air, water, and earth—as are all things in the cosmos, as is the cosmos as a whole. Therefore we may speak of the ordered universe as a whole as constituting a “body.” Our human body possesses a soul (psyche); therefore the “body of the universe” must also possess a soul. In Socrates’ words, “the body of the universe which has the same properties as our [body], but more beautiful in all respects … possesses a soul” (30a). As an argument for the world-soul, the passage is clear enough. The cosmos is argued to possess a soul on the basis of its intelligent ordering of the elements, its regularity, and its beauty. But again, the concept of the world-soul, in itself, doesn’t qualify as panpsychism. It can be seen simply as a form of theism, or of panentheism. Neither of these implies panpsychism. Panpsychism requires that each individual thing, in itself, possess a soul- or mind-like quality.^12 That the combination of all things collectively has a mind is a different proposition.

On the other hand, the concept of a universal mind or a world-soul is likely to be a part of any panpsychist cosmos. Virtually any system that sees mind in all individual things will see it in the whole. Panpsychism implies a world-soul, but not vice versa. Thus we need further elaboration from Plato to determine if his view is only that of a world-soul or whether it is something more, perhaps true panpsychism.

In fact, we find in this part of Philebus the second of three arguments for a panpsychist cosmos. This is a variation of the Continuity argument, and it is quite similar to that used by Empedocles. Plato relies heavily on analogy: A non-human object is argued to be similar in content to the human body, and thus is claimed to possess at least one essential characteristic of humans, namely a psyche. In simplified form, Plato’s Continuity argument is as follows:

(1) All physical objects, from the human body to the cosmos as a whole, are entirely composed of the four elements.
(2) The human body possesses a psyche.
(3) The human psyche is entailed by the body’s composition of the four elements.

Therefore,

(4) the cosmos possesses a psyche (world-soul).

Then, with the further implication that

(5) psyche is a general quality of objects composed of the four elements,

one may conclude that

(6) every object possesses a psyche.

The weakest link in this argument is the third point: that somehow psyche is logically entailed by the fact that our human bodies consist of the four elements. Plato makes no argument here for that claim, but importantly, he does so later on in Laws; at 895c he refers to the elements “alone” and, given their capacity for self-generating motion, they must be counted alive. If the elements individually are alive, it is plausible to conclude that anything composed of them—i.e., everything—is likewise alive. But again, the argument is only implicit here.

Plato’s third argument, also put forth in Philebus, is a version of the well-known Argument by Design. This argument has of course been traditionally used by theologians and philosophers to argue for God’s existence on the basis of the vast and supreme ordering that we see in the world. Plato argues not for God, but for universal mind, the world-soul. In the process, he also makes the argument for panpsychism.

In Philebus one of the metaphysical categories under discussion is “cause,” meaning, ultimate cause—the cause of all things and events in the universe. Socrates notes that “this cause is recognized as all-encompassing wisdom” and, more important, that “cause [is] present in everything” (30b). At issue is the meaning of the latter phrase.

Elaborating on the first point, Socrates says that “cause” is that which “orders and coordinates the years, seasons, and months, and which has every right to the title of wisdom and reason [i.e. mind]” (30c). Two lines later we find Plato’s close correlation of mind and soul: “no wisdom and reason without a soul.” Then, from Socrates, “reason belongs to that kind which is the cause of everything” (30e). Thus mind, in the form of reason, wisdom, or intelligence, belongs to the metaphysical category of “cause of all things.” This cause—mind, and the underlying psyche—is “present in everything.” Clearly this can be read in two ways. It can mean that evidence of the world-soul is present in the overall ordering of the cosmos, or it can mean that wisdom and reason themselves, and the underlying psyche, somehow reside in things. Viewing this passage in isolation, one might presume the former. Viewing it in conjunction with the other late-dialogue passages, however, we can see reason to support the latter interpretation.

Granting these arguments in Sophist and Philebus, we are still left wanting evidence of explicit attribution of soul to things other than humans or the cosmos. Some such evidence is necessary to confirm the panpsychist conjecture. And in fact this evidence appears in the other two late works, Timaeus and Laws.

In Timaeus Plato offers more an exposition of rhetoric than a traditional philosophical dialogue. Socrates is again present, along with a number of other men, including the title character and Critias. The central character, Timaeus, gives an extended description of the creation of the world. He is seen as a philosopher of considerable importance; Socrates says that “he has, in my judgment, mastered the entire field of philosophy” (20a). Thus, nominally at least, Timaeus’ views are to be held in high regard. Also, the dialogue was considered to be the central Platonic text throughout the Middle Ages and into the Renaissance. There was significant interest in Plato’s view of creation and in his idea of the Demiurge, the god-like being who created the universe and used the Forms to give it order. Also of interest was Plato’s depiction of the universe as alive, intelligent, and ensouled.

After some introductory words, Timaeus explains why the Demiurge created the world: He wanted “everything to become as much like himself as possible” (29e)—that is, brought from “a state of disorder to one of order.”^13 The intelligent, ensouled, and “ordered” Demiurge sought to reproduce himself in the cosmos. Timaeus tells us that the Demiurge “concluded that it is impossible for anything to come to possess intelligence apart from soul,” and that “guided by this reasoning, he put intelligence in soul, and soul in body, and so he constructed the universe” (30b). Again we see the implied connection of body—meaning any physical object—with soul/mind. Timaeus sums up his point by saying that the “divine providence brought our world into being as a truly living thing, endowed with soul and intelligence” (30c).

Timaeus then informs us that “the universe resembles more closely than anything else that Living Thing of which all other living things are parts, both individually and by kinds” (30c). The emphasis here is on both the individual things and the whole, which are said to share qualities of life and intelligence. Soul seems to exist in layers—in the “parts,” in the “kinds” of parts, and in the cosmos as a whole. The Demiurge “made [the cosmos] a single visible living thing, which contains within itself all the living things whose nature it is to share its kind” (31a).

Continuing in his account of the creation, Timaeus describes the formation of the stars and others heavenly bodies. The stars are “divine living things” (40b). The Earth itself is a “god,” “foremost [in the universe], the one with greatest seniority” (40c). As the Demiurge was preparing to create the stars, “he turned again to the mixing bowl, … the one in which he had blended and mixed the soul of the universe.” He concocted another “soul mixture,” and then “divided the mixture into a number of souls, equal to the number of the stars and assigned each soul to a star” (41e). Here is clear evidence that Plato saw individual, nonhuman objects—apart from the cosmos—as endowed with psyche.^14

Later in the dialogue (69c–70e), Plato elaborates on his tripartite theory of soul. He examines the three components: reason, spirit, and appetite or desire. These are discussed, significantly, in the context of zoa—animals, or living things. Zoa have, by definition, one or more of these soul-types. Humans have all three, each located in a different part of the body. Celestial objects such as the Earth and the stars have only the highest soul-type: reason.

Some lines later he addresses the potentially problematic issue of plants. Plants are clearly alive, and yet they are different than animals; they have very limited means of self-motion, they have no obvious sense organs, and they function in the world in a very different manner. But they do seek out water and sunlight, and grow in such as way as to fulfill their biological potential. Plants do not seem to reason or to possess any spiritedness per se, but they do evidently have wants and desires, at least. And they are sensitive to their environmental conditions, and thus would appear to have positive and negative sensations about the world—something like pleasure and pain. Plato thus has good reason for ascribing them soul:

We may call these plants “living things” on the ground that anything that partakes of life has an incontestable right to be called “a living thing.” And in fact, what we are talking about now partakes of the third type of soul. … This type is totally devoid of opinion, reasoning, or understanding, though it does share in sensation [aisthêsis], pleasant and painful, and desire. (77b)

Plants thus possess the appetitive soul, which apparently includes both the intentional characteristic of desire and the qualitative ability to sense pleasure and pain.

Left unstated, however, is the possible existence and nature of other soul-types, which may apply to lower-order objects such as rocks. Clearly it would not do to attribute appetite to a rock. And yet some rocks—lodestones, in particular—have an undeniable ability to move things. How does Plato assess the nature of the lodestone? Unfortunately he gives it only passing treatment in Timaeus, treating with disdain the idea that a lodestone exerts a true force of attraction (80c). But in the one substantial reference to the subject, in the early dialogue Ion, he likens the stone’s magnetic power to that of the gods (533d–536a). Poets act as conduits of a “divine power”; thus, they are like the lodestone, which, through a chain of iron rings, passes along its attractive force. One is left with the implication that the power of the lodestone is itself divine, driven by a god or spirit, and thus, in a way, a marker of ensoulment.

In any event, the stock of ensouled entities has grown: humans and other animals,^15 individual elements, the cosmos, stars, the Earth, plants. Again, these are consistent with the arguments in Sophist and Philebus. Such arguments provide something of an ontological theory establishing why all things may be considered as ensouled. If one were to disagree with this conclusion, then one might reasonably expect to find something in Plato’s ontology that would explain why the above set of objects is unique, why they alone are ensouled, and everything else is not. Such an explanation is lacking in his later writings, and thus panpsychism is the more reasonable conclusion.

Plato’s longest and last work, Laws, is primarily known for its description of the structure of the ideal, constitutionally based state. In the process, the issue of punishment arises as an important concern. The theory of punishment depends on the existence of gods, and book X provides an extended argument proving their existence. The argument revolves around the concept of “self-generating motion,” which is seen as primordial and as “the source of all motions.” Any object exhibiting such motion has the further quality of being alive. The character Clinias offers this observation: “When an object moves itself, [we are] to say that it is ‘alive.’ [And furthermore] when we see that a thing has a soul, the situation is exactly the same. … We have to admit that it is alive.” (895c) Furthermore, we have the identification of self-movement with soul. The Athenian asks “What’s the definition of the thing we call soul?” and answers “Motion capable of moving itself.” (896a) Clinias reiterates the point: “The entity which we all call ‘soul’ is precisely that which is defined by the expression “self-generating motion.” Thus, we end up with a three-way identification between life, soul, and self-movement.

Plato then makes a series of statements arguing that soul is primordial in the cosmos, is older than matter, and in fact is the mover of matter: “Soul, being the source of motion, is the most ancient thing there is. … Soul is the master, and matter its natural subject.” (896b–c) Next comes a restatement of the position, brought out in Philebus, that soul is the cause of all things (896d) and “controls the heavens as well” (896e).

The Athenian then addresses whether there is only a single world-soul or multiple souls. The initial answer is clear enough (“more than one”), but he is not confident as to the exact number. Some lines later, he asks, “If, in principle, soul drives round the sun, moon, and the other heavenly bodies, does it not impel each individually? Of course.” (898d) The Athenian then supports this contention by referring to the sun:

Everyone can see [the sun’s] body, but no one can see its soul—not that you could see the soul of any other creature, living or dying. Nevertheless, there are good grounds for believing that we are in fact held in the embrace of some such thing though it is totally below the level of our bodily senses, and is perceptible by reason alone. (898d)

In this remarkable statement, Plato not only adds the sun to the list of ensouled objects—significant insofar as the sun wasn’t recognized as just another star—but also makes clear that the soul of a nonhuman object is not empirically knowable. Rather, it is to be grasped solely by means of the intellect.

Then we have a final passage, arguably definitive, that indicates Plato’s view of the possibility that all things, individually, possess psyche. After acknowledging once again that “soul manages the universe” (899a), he writes:

Now consider all the stars and the moon and the years and the months and all the seasons: what can we do except repeat the same story? A soul or souls … have been shown to be the cause of all these phenomena, and whether it is by their living presence in matter … or by some other means, we shall insist that these souls are gods. Can anybody admit all this and still put up with people who deny that “everything is full of gods”? (899b)

The last phrase, of course, is a nod to Thales and his famous declaration of panpsychism, examined earlier. Souls exist throughout the cosmos, driving and coordinating all movement and change. They are likely to be manifest as a “living presence in matter.” And they are knowable not empirically but through reason alone.

One may object to the phrase “a soul or souls.” It is almost as if Plato is unsure or ambivalent about whether the world-soul acts alone in the cosmos or in conjunction with the manifold individual souls. Yet all other passages suggest multiple souls, acting independently of and contemporaneously with the world-soul. An alternate rendering of this phrase might be “a world-soul, and the multiplicity of other souls, have been shown to be the cause …”

The case for panpsychism in Plato is strong but indirect. The list of ensouled entities is impressively long and diverse. And there are others not mentioned above. For example, in Timaeus we read that our bones are ensouled: “next [the god] implanted in the marrow the various types of soul” (73c); “all those bones that had more soul than others” (74e). This is significant because it implies layers of soul within the human being—paralleling, perhaps, the structure of the cosmos.

Then in Republic we find an account of the polis that suggests that it too possesses a soul. The polis is shown to have a three-part structure, one that parallels the tripartition of the human soul. The structures are the same, and the moral virtues are the same in each. The polis is “courageous” (429b), “has good judgment and is really wise” (428d), is “just” (435a); generally, “everything else that has to do with virtue [is] the same in both” (441c). Indeed, the parts of the polis come from the people themselves; “where else would they come from?” (435e) Similar structure and similar effects imply a similar embodiment of soul, in human and polis alike.

One final piece of supporting evidence comes from Plotinus, circa 250 AD. In the only known explicit reference to panpsychism in Plato, Plotinus writes the following: “Plato says there is soul in everything of this [earthly] sphere” (Ennead VI, 7, 11). That Plotinus is referring not merely to Plato’s world-soul but to a soul or intelligence in all things individually is clear from the context.

Perhaps the final question to ask is this: What consistent metaphysics of the soul could include all the above-mentioned entities and yet not include everything? Can we imagine Plato constructing a vastly complex and seemingly arbitrary theory of the soul that includes humans, plants, stars, bones, elements, Being itself … and nothing else? Surely this is unlikely. No conceivable theory would pick out just those objects for ensoulment. The list is too broad and too diverse not to include every individual object in the cosmos. And this view finds independent support from the arguments listed above. Considering all the evidence, one has a hard time comprehending Guthrie’s bold claim that “hylozoism … was no longer possible for Plato.”

Thus Plato makes subtle use of three distinct arguments for panpsychism. They occur in four of his last major works, and therefore likely represent his mature thinking on the matter. This panpsychist vision is consistent across these works, each mutually supporting the other. And it is in line with the generally panpsychist milieu. By any reasonable assessment, Plato was a panpsychist.

There are several reasons why a panpsychist interpretation of Plato’s metaphysics is neither well known nor examined. First, some commentators simply assume that he is speaking poetically or metaphorically in these passages. This is difficult to prove either way, but in any case it is a problematic feature of much of his writing. To argue this way on the issue of panpsychism is a convenient and simplistic denial. By this tactic, we could dismiss much of substance in Plato’s philosophy. The panpsychist statements are too explicit and too wide ranging to all be argued away as metaphor.

Second, panpsychism seems to be refuted by passages in the early and middle works. Such passages, however, are rare and ambiguous. They do not rule out a broader panpsychist scheme, even if they emphasize the human soul. Nothing in the earlier writings explicitly denies panpsychism. It is more likely that Plato shifted his focus from the human soul to soul generally as he matured. And of course there is the possibility that he himself changed his opinion, from one of uncertainty or unconcern to something approaching a more affirmative stance.

Third, panpsychism doesn’t figure prominently in the overall corpus of Plato’s thinking—at least, not explicitly. This, however, is true not only of him but also of many other major panpsychists. And, of course, this is no basis for denying its existence. The relevant passages must be judged as a whole and in light of any potentially conflicting passages elsewhere. There appear to be no passages anywhere in his writings that explicitly deny the panpsychist conclusion. And there are no implications that would demand a larger role for it.

Fourth, on this issue Plato tends to make relatively flat statements of fact, without supplying much rationale. Elaborate and extended logical arguments are lacking. The arguments that do exist are indirect and implicit. This might suggest that the matter of panpsychism was more of an intuitive view for Plato, grounded perhaps in the so-called hylozoism of his predecessors. Or that argumentation was unnecessary on this point, perhaps because it could not lead to a decisive conclusion. Without detailed and intricate arguments, it is easy for present-day analytical commentators to overlook the matter entirely.

Fifth, for at least two centuries philosophy has been dominated by mechanist interpretations of nature, and writers have been reticent about acknowledging aspects of panpsychism in any major historical philosopher, let alone Plato. We see the same phenomenon with respect to Aristotle and several other prominent thinkers. This is especially true in the last hundred years or so, as hostility to panpsychism became mainstream within analytic philosophy.

This is not to say that no one has addressed the topic. One notable case in point is Ian Crombie. The chapter on Plato’s philosophy of mind in Crombie 1962 addresses his “animism.” The use of that term suggests a hostile treatment, and that is precisely what we find. Focusing on the later dialogues, Crombie writes:

For here we find Plato apparently maintaining, in all the dignity of metaphysical language, something almost indistinguishable from the animism of primitive savages. … So odd is it to find such a doctrine in such an author that one is forced to wonder whether, in ascribing souls to self-moving objects, Plato is really maintaining an animistic doctrine, or whether the better account may not be simply that he is evacuating the word ‘soul’ of all content except ‘self-activation.’ (325)

Concluding a lengthy analysis of the soul-theory in Phaedrus, Crombie writes: “The lesson then of the Phaedrus myth is that all apparent self-activation in physical things is to be ascribed to the presence in the living body of a genuinely self-activating thing, or in other words of a soul.” (328–329) Even if true, of course, this is something less than panpsychism; not every object in the universe is a self-mover. He then gives a brief and unfocused account of the souls of celestial objects, plants, animals, and parts of the human body.

Crombie’s rambling analysis concludes by asking “How are we to interpret the animism of the Phaedrus, Timaeus, and Laws?” (337) After stating that “this is not a simple question to answer,” he proceeds to consider both “figurative” and “literal” interpretations. On the former view, celestial souls are not really minds or spirits but rather a shorthand notation for the fact that “they conform to the requirements of [abstract and non-personal] reason.” ‘Soul’ merely reflects the evident fact that the cosmos is well ordered and follows consistent and rational patterns. Of the latter, literal view, “we need not waste many words.” Crombie does his best to defend the case for the figurative view but is forced to concede, in the end, that “this interpretation is really untenable” (339). In other words, we are stuck with the literal view: true animism or panpsychism. Precisely what this means, Crombie concludes, “is a question I should not like to answer” (341). Apparently he cannot bear to contemplate the possibility that Plato might actually have been a panpsychist.

There are many unanswered questions here. For example, what is the relationship between the myriad individual souls and the world-soul? Are the individual souls truly distinct entities, or are they merely aspects of the one Soul? If they are distinct, they must still stand in some relation to the larger world-soul, which would seem to have a special status among all the souls of the cosmos. One could speculate on answers to these questions, but there is little in Plato’s writings to justify any particular conclusion. He seems to have simply left such matters open. And in any event such questions are not unique to the panpsychist interpretation, nor do they undermine it in any way. Indeed, one might ask if it really matters whether there are many souls or only one Soul with many manifestations. I take it as self-evident that it does matter. It would seem that one’s self-conception, and one’s vision of the self in the world, must be vastly different in each case. It’s hard to imagine that Plato was unconcerned with this distinction. But it’s not hard to imagine him struggling with issues of personhood and the relationship between soul and Soul, ultimately reaching a consistent view of soul as pervading the universe.

2.3 Aristotle

Aristotle is perhaps the last ancient philosopher who would be expected to put forth panpsychist views. His notion of mankind as alone, among living beings, in possessing a rational, separable, and immortal soul is in line with the traditional Cartesian view. His emphasis on analytics, logic, and classification aligns him with present-day materialist science. And his denial of the Platonic Forms makes him more of a conventional realist. Thus, it is in his case that we find perhaps the most surprising evidence of panpsychist thinking. Much of the groundwork along this line was done by A. L. Peck and by John Rist. Rist’s insightful analysis in his 1989 book The Mind of Aristotle is a standout among recent writings on Aristotle’s conception of mind and soul.

By way of background, we know that Aristotle viewed the psyche or soul as “the form of living things.” Like Plato, he posited three degrees of soul: nutritive, sensitive, and rational. These incorporate five “psychic powers”: in ascending order, nutritive/generative, appetitive, sensory, locomotive, and rational. Each level encompasses and contains those below it.

Like Plato, Aristotle accepts that plants are ensouled. A typical statement is found in De anima: “It seems that the principle found in plants is also a kind of soul; for this is the only principle which is common to both animals and plants.” (411b27) Plants, as the lowest order of living things, possess only a nutritive capacity. All animals have, at least, nutritive and sensitive powers; higher animals have additional powers; and man alone possesses all five psychic powers.^16

At issue, then, are the non-living things. According to Aristotle they have no soul—hence, technically, he is no panpsychist. But the question remains whether non-living things have something soul-like in them. From early on, Aristotle seems to have been open to such a view:

Nature proceeds little by little from things lifeless to animal life in such a way that it is impossible to determine the exact line of demarcation, nor on which side thereof an intermediate form should lie. (History of Animals 588b4–6)

And again in the late work Parts of Animals:

For nature passes from lifeless objects to animals in such an unbroken sequence, interposing between them beings which live and yet are not animals, that scarcely any difference seems to exist between two neighboring groups owing to their close proximity. (PA 681a11–15)

Indeed, this continuity is an almost god-like quality of the world: “All things have by nature something divine in them.” (Nicomachean Ethics 1153b33) The lack of a firm ontological distinction between living and lifeless things suggests, or at least leaves open the possibility, that there may be some common soul-like quality shared among all things.

As a part of his broader inquiry into the natural world, Aristotle sought to explain the puzzling phenomenon of the generation of living, ensouled beings. As he saw it, there are two ways in which this can occur: sexual reproduction and spontaneous generation. The former is challenging enough to understand, and he spends considerable effort explaining the nature and action of male and female reproductive organs. On his final view, sexual reproduction occurs because the male supplies the (rational) soul in his semen, which shapes and forms the raw material—the “menstrual blood”—in the female’s uterus. Thus he offers something of a scientific account. Spontaneous generation, on the other hand, is very problematic. Plant and animal life appear out of inanimate matter. How is that possible?

First, we note that there is the clear presence of an evolutionary and teleological imperative in Aristotle’s thinking. That is uncontroversial. He envisions all of nature as continually striving toward a final goal or end (telos), namely “the good,” “the better,” or “the best”:

Nature creates nothing without a purpose, but always the best possible in each kind of living creature. (Progression of Animals 704b15)

There is something divine, good, and desirable … [that matter] desire[s] and yearn[s] for … . (Physics 192a18)

For in all things … nature always strives after the better. (On Generation and Corruption 336b28)

All existing things … seek [their] own special good … . (Eudemian Ethics 1218a30)

All the operations of nature … are for a final cause and for the sake of what is best in each case. (Generation of Animals 789b3)

By ‘better’ or ‘best’ Aristotle has in mind certain specific qualities; he comments that being is better than non-being, life better than non-life, and soul better than matter. Thus, as Rist points out (1989: 123), there is a meaningful sense in which “the whole of the cosmos is permeated by some kind of upward desire and aspiration”—upward in the sense of toward form, life, and soul.

Spontaneous generation is therefore explained in part by the upward striving of matter that Aristotle articulated throughout his writings. Given that striving or desire is typically seen as an intentional mental property, this in itself displays a tendency toward a kind of panpsychism. But Aristotle went further, describing the actual means by which such a tendency or striving became manifest as soul.

At the beginning of book 2 of Physics, he distinguishes things that come about “by nature” from those created “by cause”:

Of things that exist, some exist by nature, some from other causes. By nature the animals and their parts exist, and the plants and the simple bodies (earth, fire, air, water)—for we say that these and the like exist by nature.

All the things mentioned plainly differ from things which are not constituted by nature [e.g. artifacts]. For each of them [i.e. the natural things] has within itself a principle of motion and of stationariness … . (192b9–15)

Animals, plants, and even the four elements are here seen as possessing an inherent “principle of motion” that is related to the essential nature of all natural objects. Aristotle then begins the final book of Physics with a question regarding this universal motion: Has such motion always existed in the cosmos, or was there a time when all was still? After some brief consideration of the alternatives, he concludes that absence of motion is impossible. Thus he provides an affirmative answer to the question “Is [motion] in fact an immortal never-failing property of things that are, a sort of life as it were to all naturally constituted things?” (250b12) This “sort of life” that all things have is consistent with the view of universal striving that we see in the earlier portions of the same work, and in the related passages quoted above.

The “sort of life” in matter was no idle concept; it was directly connected to the process of spontaneous generation. Aristotle put it as follows in one of the last-written books of Metaphysics: “Those natural objects which are produced … spontaneously, are those whose matter can also initiate for itself that motion which [in sexual reproduction] the seed initiates.” (1034b5) The life in matter initiates the generative process, thus bringing biological life, and soul, into being.

Remaining to be explained are (1) the exact nature of this life or striving that all natural things possess and (2) precisely how this life or striving activates a process such as spontaneous generation. Clearly this life-property is not equivalent to psyche, as Aristotle consistently confines soul, in its three forms, to plants, animals, and humans. Rist argues that in the early Aristotle this quality is as much mind-like as soul-like. As evidence he cites a passage from Cicero’s On the Nature of the Gods: “In one place [Aristotle] attributes divinity to mind only; in another he says that the universe itself is God.” (book I, 30–33) The reference is to Aristotle’s lost early work On Philosophy. Rist reads into this a three-way identification among the cosmos, mind, and God—the concept of the world-mind.

The identification of these three entities is supported by the ideas that all things have “a sort of life” and that “matter desires form.” It is also supported, indirectly, by passages in the roughly concurrent work De caelo, at the beginning of which Aristotle reiterates that the four elements, or simple bodies, “possess a principle of movement in their own nature” (268b28). That is, the natural movement of fire and air is upward, whereas that of earth and water is downward. The heavens, however, contain the “primary body,” or ether, which is fundamentally different from the four elements and whose natural movement is circular. Ether moves endlessly in a circle, accounting for the perceived circular motion of the stars and planets. Importantly, the ether exhibits self-movement, and thus is ensouled: “If it moves itself, it must be animate.” (275b25) The self-moving ether is both “immortal” and “divine” (284a4). It contains all limited, finite, earthly motions within it. It is, in essence, the medium and the means by which all other movement occurs in the universe.

Book II of De caelo opens with a discussion of symmetry in the heavens, and again repeats the conclusion: “we have already determined … that the heaven is animate and possesses a principle of movement” (285a28). The self-moving ether drives the motion of the celestial bodies, thus endowing them with a kind of life: “We think of the stars as mere bodies, and as units with a serial order indeed but entirely inanimate; but we should rather conceive them as enjoying life and action.” (292a19–21) Hence, “we must, then, think of the action of the stars as similar to that of animals and plants” (292a32). The motions of all things, from stars to elements, exhibit a degree of rationality, and rationality is a hallmark of mind. Mind is in all things to the extent that its action is manifest in them via a cosmic source of rational movement.

Aristotle evidently came to see the world-mind as insufficient, and so, shortly thereafter, he introduced the concept of the Unmoved Mover, which stood alone and apart from the natural world and, on Rist’s view, operated in conjunction with the world-mind (1989: 129). Mind was immanent, and the Mover was transcendent. Aristotle also began to more clearly distinguish things with souls from those without. Plants, animals, and the ether fell into the former category; all other things, including the four elements, were relegated to inanimate status.

Yet even after the introduction of the Unmoved Mover and the separation between the animate and inanimate, Aristotle still had to account for both spontaneous generation and the natural tendency (dynamis) of the elements to move toward their natural resting places—fire upward, earth downward, and so on. Furthermore, there was the open status of the fifth element, the ether. Rist argues that Aristotle ultimately attached the notion of mind to the Unmoved Mover, removing it from immanence in the cosmos. But some agent of the Mover would have to remain in the natural world.

Aristotle then supplemented the notion of the ether with a new concept: that of the pneuma. Perhaps borrowing from Anaximenes, he installed the pneuma in a preeminent role in nature. It appears prominently in the last three of his biological works (Parts of Animals, Motion of Animals, and Generation of Animals). And it neatly ties together the issues of psyche, generation, and celestial and earthly motion—and panpsychism.

Just as the ether is the heavenly bearer of mind and motion generated by the Prime Mover, the pneuma is the earthly bearer; it is the “vehicle of Soul” and its “immediate instrument” (Peck 1943: lix), the “bearer of soul” (Rist 1989: 131). Pneuma is not mind; that was reserved for the transcendent Mover. Nor is it soul, as soul resides only in those animate beings. It is, rather, “soul-like.” As Aristotle writes in one of his last works, Generation of Animals, it is the “faculty of all kinds of soul,” the “vital heat” (thermoteta psychiken), the “principle of soul” (736b29ff). As such, pneuma shares much in common with ether; they are, as he says, “analogous.” Both are intermediaries to the Prime Mover, and both convey its rationality and soul. Neither is explicitly mind or soul; each is only the carrier of such. Furthermore, both share a vital power or a generative capacity. Both bring soul to natural objects, and thus in a sense account for the life in them. This brings us back us to the problem of spontaneous generation versus sexual reproduction. In sexual reproduction it is the soul-heat of the pneuma in the semen that conveys life to the embryo. In the case of spontaneous reproduction—which works best in decomposing matter sitting out in the hot sun—it is the heat of the solar ether, manifest on Earth as the pneuma, that conveys life. Regarding this vital heat, Aristotle writes:

This is not fire nor any such force, but it is the pneuma included in the semen and the foam-like, and the natural principle in the pneuma, being analogous to the element of the stars [i.e. ether]. (GA 736b35)

The soul-like pneuma is ubiquitous in the natural world, penetrating and informing all things. Not only does it bring soul to the embryo and to the spontaneously generated creatures; it also accounts for the general property of matter, its desire for form and for the good. Aristotle is explicit and unambiguous that all things are inspirited by the pneuma:

Animals and plants come into being in earth and in liquid because there is water in earth, and pneuma in water, and in all pneuma is vital heat, so that in a sense all things are full of soul. (762a18–20; emphasis added)

The final striking phrase of this passage from Generation of Animals is unique in Aristotle’s corpus. The text is emphatic: hoste tropon tina panta psyches einai plere. Echoing panpsychist thinking from Thales to Plato, Aristotle apparently came to the conclusion that something soul-like, of varying degrees, inhered in all objects of the natural world. Peck (1943: 585) referred to this passage as Aristotle’s “startling admission,” arguing that such a conclusion is justified in part by the fact that animated beings arise out of nature (phusis), and that “as we know, phusis never acts idly but always with a telos [end] in view.” “Regarded in this way,” Peck continues, “‘matter’ … might be looked upon as considerably more than mere lifeless, inert material; and in Generation of Animals Aristotle does in fact ascribe even the possession of psyche to it.” Peck seems taken aback by this “startling admission,” and appears unwilling or unable to place it in the larger context of Aristotle’s conception of life and mind. It is in the latter step—the elaboration of the larger role of pneuma in Aristotle’s theory of mind—that Rist makes a significant contribution.

Pneuma is thus the universal link among all things, and it provides a common ontological dimension. It makes the distinction between animate and inanimate relatively superficial. Through the pneuma, Aristotle avoids an unacceptable and unexplainable dualism between things that are ensouled and those that are utterly soulless. Granted, he still has the problem of explaining just how pneuma becomes manifest as full-blown soul in certain objects, such as plants, animals, and humans. But this is more a difference of degree than of kind, and thus it is less difficult metaphysically. It is unfortunate that, as far as we know, Aristotle never addressed it fully.

As might be expected, panpsychist readings of Aristotle are as rare as of Plato. Thomas Aquinas cited this possibility in his Summa (part 1a, question 18; see discussion below). Apart from Peck and Rist, very few recent writers have commented on it. De Quincey (2002: 118–119) suggests that it is inherent in Aristotle’s theory of hylomorphism. Several years earlier, Charles Hartshorne argued obliquely for a similar view:

Aristotle’s statements that the soul … is all things, that all things are moved by God as the lover by what he loves (implying that all things love, and thus are sentient … ), that a soul is the form of any organized, self-moving body (implying that if … nature consists entirely of more or less organized, self-moving bodies … then nature consists entirely of besouled constituents). (1950: 443)

Hartshorne was on the right track, but the details are sorely lacking. Apart from these few cases, recent literature on Aristotle is utterly vacant on this matter. Gill and Lennox (1994), for example, include eight chapters on Aristotle’s theory of self-motion, and yet the pneuma concept appears not once. Freudenthal (1995) has an extensive discussion of vital heat and the pneuma but completely overlooks the panpsychist implication. As to why recent scholars fail to address the pneuma theory, a knowledgeable colleague remarked that “they simply don’t know what to do with it.”

As elaborated above, we can see a clear picture of a quasi-panpsychist cosmos in Aristotle—a cosmos in which everything has either soul or, at least, a soul-like presence, the pneuma, which confers an evolutionary, life-like impulse upon all things.

2.4 Epicurus and the Atomic Swerve

Epicurus was the founder of one of the three great Hellenistic philosophical systems—Stoicism and Skepticism being the others. Epicurean physical theory relied heavily on the atomism of Democritus and followed his central thesis of material reality as composed of atoms moving through the void. On this view, atoms possess only the primary qualities of size, shape, and mass or inertia; they interact and combine to form the large-scale objects of the world around us. It was a thoroughly materialistic and modern approach to physical theory.

As a theory, atomism had a unique problem: how to account for the soul in a materialistic and atomistic universe. As we saw, Democritus’ solution was to posit a special class of atoms—small, round, smooth—that were the bearers of soul. Light, fluid, and self-moving, the soul-atoms penetrated everywhere and set the other atoms into motion. Because they were omnipresent, the action of the psyche was presumably also found everywhere.

The atomists also believed that atoms had a natural “downward” motion through the void, something like that of falling raindrops. For Democritus and Leucippus, the motion of these atoms, soul-atoms included, was of a deterministic nature: “Nothing happens in vain, but everything for a reason and by necessity.” (in Barnes 1987: 243) Aristotle confirms this view: “Democritus, however, neglecting the final cause, reduces to necessity all the operations of nature.” (GA 789b3) If everything, including the action of the soul, occurs deterministically, then there is no room for anything like free will in a Democritean universe.

That was problematic for Epicurus, whose ethical system required free will. He therefore kept the Democritean atoms but discarded the determinism. He argued instead that the motion of atoms resulted from three sources: weight, mechanical collisions, and a new third factor that he called “swerve”—in Greek, parenklisis, meaning a deflection or turning aside. In effect, the atoms occasionally “chose” to deflect from their normal downward flow. This was effectively seen as a small amount of free will exhibited by the atoms. The swerve was a crucial process in nature because it caused collisions and combinations with other atoms, leading to a cascading of action that resulted in the formation of large objects. Without swerve, atoms would fall smoothly through the void, unfettered by atomic collisions and interactions, and thus no complex structures would ever develop. And it also provided the root source of human will.

Very few of Epicurus’ original writings have survived, so we rely primarily on later doxographers—primarily Cicero, Lucretius, and Diogenes Laertius. Lucretius’ De rerum natura (On the Nature of Things), written around 50 BC, contains the best sympathetic account of the atomic swerve. The basic statement of the view is found near the beginning of book II:

Though atoms fall straight downward through the void by their own weight, yet at uncertain times and at uncertain points, they swerve a bit. … And if they did not swerve … no clashes would occur, no blows befall the atoms; nature would never have made a thing. (II: 215–225)

The willful swerving of the atoms is the basis for our own free will: Out of the swerve “rises … that will torn free from fate, through which we follow wherever pleasure leads, and likewise swerve aside at times and places” (II: 255–260). Human free will cannot arise ex nihilo (“since nothing, we see, could be produced from nothing”; 287) and hence must be present in the atoms themselves. “Thus to the atoms we must allow … one more cause of movement [namely, that of free will]—the one whence comes this power we own.” (284–286)

Cicero, in On Fate, adds a similar but more critical account:

Epicurus thinks that the necessity of fate can be avoided by the swerve of an atom … . [He] introduced this line of reasoning because he was afraid that if an atom always moved by its natural and necessary heaviness, we would have no freedom, since our mind would be moved in such a way that it would be compelled by the motion of atoms. (in Inwood and Gerson 1997: 47–48)^17

Thus the swerve serves two important purposes: It accounts for the complex physical structure of objects and, independently, it provides the basis for human freedom of will. Epicurus used the swerve to simultaneously solve two potentially serious problems for his atomic worldview.

The second purpose, in fact, also provides a new approach in arguing for panpsychism. Epicurus’ argument can be reconstructed as follows: Humans clearly exhibit will. Will is a fundamental quality of existence and cannot plausibly emerge from non-will. Therefore will is present in the elemental particles of the cosmos, and hence, potentially, in all things. This is an Argument by Non-Emergence. If certain psychic qualities are not emergent, then they are necessarily present in at least some of the ultimate or most fundamental particles.^18 This particular argument has proved to be one of the more enduring and more important arguments for panpsychism, and it is still employed today. I examine this argument in detail in the chapters to follow.

Given that atoms have a will, this does not imply, according to Lucretius—and presumably Epicurus—that they possess sensitivity or other mental powers. Lucretius allows for certain qualities to emerge from nothing, including life and sentience. The ability to sense is evidently viewed as an emergent phenomenon, unlike the power of will. Thus, atoms are said to possess will but not sentience: “Now all that we know [of] is composed of insensate atoms … in every case.” (864–846) And it is permissible to “rightly conclude that sense comes from non-sense” (930). The atomic swerve has no connection to human sensate qualities such as joy, happiness, or pain; atoms “must not, then, be endowed with sense” (972). This is a plausible claim. A non-emergentist need not hold that nothing emerges; that would be a ludicrous and indefensible position. Even today, the physical realm is held to consist of certain fundamental, non-emergent entities which then combine into more complex structures. The same could well be true for the mental realm.

In concluding this section, I must mention recent scientific developments that seem, surprisingly, to confirm the existence of an atomic will. The mathematicians John Conway and Simon Kochen argue in two papers (2006, 2009) that “if indeed we humans have free will, then elementary particles already have their own small share of this valuable commodity.” Sounding rather like modern-day Epicureans, they explain: “Our [Free Will Theorem] asserts that if experimenters have a certain freedom, then particles have exactly the same kind of freedom. Indeed, it is natural to suppose that this latter freedom is the ultimate explanation of our own.” (2009: 230) The technical details of their theorem are beyond the scope of this book, but Conway and Kochen note that the phrase “the particles make a free decision” is more accurately stated as “the Universe makes this free decision in the neighborhood of the particles” (2006: 1456). Quantum theory decisively refutes a deterministic universe, they say. The strangeness of quantum experiments can best be explained by atomic choices that we cannot predict.^19 Once again, ancient metaphysical ideas find confirmation in modern science.

By attributing will to atoms, Epicurus made explicit the implicit panpsychism of Democritus. Neither Cicero nor Lucretius expanded on the panpsychic implications, nor did they discuss freedom of will in ordinary inanimate objects—which seems to be a logical consequence.

2.5 Stoicism and the Pneuma

Zeno of Citium, a contemporary of Epicurus, founded his own school of philosophy in Athens around 325 BC. Because Zeno spent much time in the stoa (covered portico) of the agora, his school came to be known as Stoicism. Zeno, along with successors Cleanthes and Chrysippus, pieced together the various lines of Stoic thought and constructed a comprehensive philosophical system. Stoic philosophy was highly influential in the ancient world, even more so than the views of Plato and Aristotle. It vied with and largely surpassed Skepticism and Epicureanism for influence, and it maintained a dominant position for nearly 500 years. Panaetius and Posidonius carried on the tradition through the pre-Christian era, and the Roman Stoics—Seneca, Epictetus, and Marcus Aurelius—continued it until nearly 200 AD.

Stoicism can be divided into the three traditional parts of philosophy: physics, logic, and ethics. These were not three isolated branches of thought; they all addressed the presence of reason in the cosmos. As Tony Long says (1974: 119), “the subject matter of logic, physics, and ethics is one thing, the rational universe.” Reason (logos) is embodied alike in mankind and in the cosmos. “Cosmic events and human actions are … not happenings of two quite different orders; in the last analysis they are both alike consequences of one thing—logos.” (108) Thus, according to the Stoics, one cannot learn about mankind without learning about the rational cosmos, nor can one learn about the cosmos without gaining an understanding of humanity.

The Stoic universe consisted of two central principles: the Active and the Passive. The Passive is “primary matter,” the unformed substance of the world, constituted by the four Empedoclean elements of fire, air, water, and earth. These elements are not equally passive, however. Fire and air are relatively active, earth and water relatively passive.

The Active is rather more complex, and it has a number of interpretations. In general it gives form and order to all physical objects. Owing to this capacity, it is equated with the logos of the universe, the rational principle governing all things. The logos, in turn, is seen as the supreme organizing power and thus is equated with god: “the Active is the rational principle [logos] in [the universe], i.e. god.”^20 Because it was the highest of cosmic divine powers, it sometimes took the name Zeus. And because of its ability to control the destiny of all things, it functioned as a kind of providence or fate. Thus we read that “God and mind and fate and Zeus are one thing, but called by many different names.”^21

Also central to Stoicism, and intimately related to the Active principle, was the concept of pneuma. As a material compound, pneuma had to have an elemental structure; its active, energetic, and refined nature led to the conclusion that it was a joint composition of fire and air. The importance of these two elements was seen in our own human bodies, wherein warmth and breath were the two primary indicators of life. These two elements, when conjoined as pneuma, served as the omnipresent life energy of the universe. Citing the Stoic Posidonius, Sandbach (1975: 130) writes that “a ‘life-force’ could be recognized everywhere.”

Furthermore, since all things have form, and this form is given to inert matter by the Active, and the Active is effective through the pneuma, it is clear that pneuma is present in all things. There are, of course, strong affinities here to Aristotle’s theory. Aristotle died just as Zeno was reaching maturity, and his views would certainly have circulated among Zeno and his followers in Athens. By all appearances, Zeno adopted Aristotle’s late development of the pneuma and elevated it to a central cosmic force.

Pneuma is—like fire—active, energetic, and inherently in motion. It is a fire that gives form and order; it constructs and builds, rather than destroys. In the words of Zeno, pneuma is a pyr technikon—a “creative fire”—that creates and animates the natural world. We find a number of interesting discussions of the pyr technikon in the literature. Sandbach (1975: 73) calls it “the god that makes the world” and “fire that is an artificer.” Seneca, in the Epistles, refers to it as “creative reason” (Long 1974: 165). Inwood and Gerson (1997: 138) translate the phrase as “craftsmanlike fire.” Then there is this famous and beautiful passage in Diogenes Laertius: “Nature is an artistic fire going on its way to create.”^22 In On the Nature of the Gods, Cicero cites the same passage, informing us that this, in fact, was Zeno’s definition of nature.^23

This creation of the world is clearly intelligent and mindful, and it demonstrates the god, or logos, in nature. Thus we see a linkage of several terms—Active, logos, god, mind, pneuma, fire, pyr technikon—which together paint a picture of the cosmos as, in the words of Diogenes Laertius, “an animal, rational and alive and intelligent” (Inwood and Gerson 1997: 135)—as well as divine. Sambursky sums up this idea nicely:

Pneuma became a concept synonymous with God, and either notion was defined by the other. … Natural force (i.e. pneuma) was seen as endowed with divine reason, and pneuma was given epithets like “sensible” or “intellectual,” thus alluding to its god-like nature. … [Conversely] God was identified with the all-pervading pneuma, being totally mixed with shapeless matter, and divine reason was defined as corporeal pneuma. (1959: 36)

In addition to its cosmic role, pneuma has a number of important physical functions, each of which supports one aspect of Stoic panpsychism. First, pneuma acts as the cohesive force of the universe. Cicero tells us that “there is, therefore, a nature [physis, i.e. pneuma] which holds the entire cosmos together and preserves it.”^24 This recalls Anaximenes’ view, cited earlier, that “our souls … being air, hold us together.” Importantly, pneuma acts not only on the cosmos but also on individual objects. Referring to its cohesive force, Long (1974: 156) writes: “This function of pneuma in the macrocosm is equally at work in every individual body.” The cohesive force exists in three distinct degrees of intensity, or tension (tonos). At the lowest level—that which holds all objects together, including inorganic objects such as stones and tables—it is called hexis, meaning a condition, state, or tenor. At a higher level, that of living organisms, it is called physis (nature). At the highest level, that of animals and humans, it is psyche. All are pneuma, though existing in varying degrees of tonos. Pseudo-Galen explains it as follows:

There are two forms of the inborn pneuma, that of nature [physis] and that of soul [psyche]; and some [the Stoics] add a third, that of hexis. The pneuma which holds things is what makes stones cohere, while that of nature is what nourishes animals and plants, and that of the soul is that which, in animate objects, makes animals capable of sense-perception and of every kind of movement. (in Inwood and Gerson 1997: 171)

Clearly, soul is not attributed to all things, only to animals. Unlike the pre-Socratics, the Stoics had differentiated soul from mind, equating mind and reason with the pneuma, which was in all things. Thus we do not find statements like “soul moved all things”; rather, we see an intelligent universal force that accounts for all motion. Consequently, the Stoics were panpsychists, but of a different type than Plato and the earlier philosophers. And their identification of pneuma with the rational mind was a step Aristotle was unwilling to take.

In a related role, pneuma not only holds things together; it also makes them one. It accounts for the unity of being. The unity of a thing is described as that which rules over the object and determines its character. This ruling unity, another important concept in Stoic philosophy, is given a special name: hegemonikon, from hege (“lead”) and monos (“alone,” “single”), often translated as “the leading part of the soul.” The hegemonikon, like the pneuma, is present at all levels of existence. Cleanthes argued that the sun was the hegemonikon of the cosmos. Cicero explained the concept as follows:

There is … a nature [i.e. pneuma] which holds the entire cosmos together and preserves it. … For every [natural object] … is joined and connected with something else, [and] must have in itself some “leading part,” like the mind in man and in a brute beast something analogous to mind which is the source of its desires for things; in trees and plants which grow in the earth the leading part is thought to reside in their roots. By “leading part” I mean that which the Greeks call hegemonikon; in each type of thing there cannot and should not be anything more excellent than this.^25

Something mind-like was thus seen as the unifying force in all objects: “The vital function of the hegemonikon [is] as the central seat of consciousness.” (Sambursky 1959: 22) It was therefore central to the mind-body relationship.

It is important to clarify the Stoics’ view of the mind-body relationship. In one sense they were mind-matter dualists. Pneuma and the four elements were matter; mind was something else, something immaterial. Mind was the Active, the form, that impressed itself upon matter and created individual objects. Long (1996: 228) describes it well: “All things in the Stoic universe are combinations of god and matter, stones no less than humans … . The entire universe is a combination of god and matter, and what applies to the whole applies to any one of its identifiable parts.” Their dualism is thus perhaps best seen as a kind of dual-aspect monism: There is only body, and it expresses itself both as matter, on the passive side, and mind, on the active side.

The Stoic fragments help to elaborate this view. Diogenes Laertius informs us that “mind penetrates every part of [the cosmos] just as soul does us. But it penetrates some things more than others.”^26 This is an interesting observation, as it indicates that mind exists in different degrees, depending on the nature of the thing penetrated. Regarding the things in themselves, Cicero explicitly states that “the parts of the cosmos … contain the power of sense-perception and reason” (146)—a clear statement of pluralistic panpsychism. And Cicero reiterates the view, which began with Plato, that the stars individually have souls:

Now that we have seen that the cosmos is divine, we should assign the same sort of divinity to the stars. … They too are also said quite correctly to be animals and to perceive and to have intelligence. [And furthermore], the sun too should be [considered] alive. (148–149)

As to the Stoic rationale, Cicero informs us that the “orderliness and regularity of the heavenly bodies is the clearest indication of their powers of sense perception and intelligence,” for “nothing can move rationally and with measure except by the use of intelligence.” The Stoics thus had hard empirical evidence to support their claim.

Collectively, then, the Stoics employed several extant arguments for panpsychism. The psychic pneuma provides a cohesive force that acts as the seat of consciousness (Indwelling Powers). Pneuma exists in all things, human or otherwise (Continuity). It is the embodiment of the Active principle, and it accounts for such physical qualities as unity of form and orderliness of motion (Design). The Stoics were thus thoroughly panpsychist in their outlook on the world, and they developed a theory of the cosmos that was perfectly compatible with that outlook.

As has already been mentioned, Stoicism held a dominant position in both Greek and Roman society for centuries. The late period of Roman Stoicism peaked with the work of Seneca (1–65 AD) and Epictetus (55–135 AD) and reached a pinnacle of sorts with emperor and philosopher Marcus Aurelius (121–180 AD). Unfortunately, that occurred just as Stoicism’s influence began to wane, and so the vision of a true Stoic society went largely unfulfilled. Upon the death of Marcus Aurelius, the Empire began to fall into decline, and Stoicism yielded to a resurgent interest in the Platonic and Aristotelian philosophies, especially in the form of Neo-Platonism. Ultimately those philosophies would be displaced by the emerging monotheistic religious worldviews, Christianity most of all.

2.6 Echoes of Panpsychism in the Christian Era

Throughout the entire pre-Christian era, people acknowledged the presence of spirit and mind in nature. But this began to change with the Judeo-Christian worldview. Christianity took spirit out of nature and placed it largely, and ambiguously, within the monotheistic figure of God. But when it did so, it carried along much of the terminological baggage that was associated with the idea of spirit. It is therefore interesting and relevant to briefly examine the concept of spirit in the Biblical tradition, particularly as it pertains to the panpsychist ideas of the Greek philosophers.

A central precept of Christianity is the Trinity: the Father (God), the Son (Jesus), and the Holy Spirit.^27 It is striking that in both the original Greek of the New Testament and the original Greek translation (from Hebrew) of the Old Testament^28 the word for Spirit is pneuma. Virtually every reference to spirit or Spirit is either pneuma or some close variant, such as pneumatos or pneumati. Spiritual things are pneumatika; the spiritual man is a pneumatikos. This suggests a connection to Stoic and Aristotelian philosophy, and also to panpsychism. If there were such a connection, one would expect to find not just the occurrence of the word itself, but also that its usage would be consistent with Stoic principles. For example, one might expect to find such things as (1) the word ‘pneuma’ in reference to both air and fire, (2) pneuma as God, (3) pneuma as a creative force in the cosmos (recall pyr technikon), (4) pneuma as intelligence or mind, (5) pneuma as life-giving, and (6) pneuma as omnipresent and as filling or penetrating things.

In fact, there are references to all these Stoic concepts in the Bible.^29 In particular, these are characteristics of the Holy Spirit itself.

(1) There are passages in which ‘pneuma’ plays on its multiple meaning of wind, breath, and spirit: “The wind (pneuma) blows wherever it pleases. … So it is with everyone born of the Spirit (pneumatos).” (John 3:8) “The Spirit of God has made me; the breath of the Almighty gives me life.” (Job 33:4) Regarding reference to fire, we have the following: “For the Lord your God is a devouring fire.” (Deuteronomy 4:24) “Do not put out the Spirit’s fire.” (1 Thessalonians 5:19) There is also the incident of the burning bush in which God first speaks to Moses: “And the angel of the Lord appeared to him in a flame of fire.” (Exodus 3:2) Wind and fire are combined in Psalm 104: “He makes winds his messengers, flames of fire his servants.”
(2) The most explicit identification of God and spirit is found in John 4:24: “God is spirit (pneuma o theos), and his worshippers must worship in spirit (pneumati) and truth.” Pneuma is also equated with deity in Acts 5:3–4 (“a lie to Spirit equals a lie to God”) and in 2 Corinthians 3:17–18 (“The Lord is the Spirit”). Additionally, one finds that pneuma has a number of God-like attributes and powers; it is omnipresent (Psalm 139:7ff.), self-existent (Romans 8:2), and involved with the Creation (Genesis 1:2) and the Resurrection (Romans 8:11).
(3) Pneuma as creative force is found in Genesis 1:2; at the first moment of Creation, we read that “the Spirit of God moved upon the face of the waters” (KJV).
(4) The Holy Spirit has a number of qualities related to intelligence and mind: “The Spirit searches all things, even the deep things of God. … No one knows the thoughts of God except the Spirit of God.” (1 Corinthians 2:10–11) Furthermore, it teaches (“the Holy Spirit … will teach you all things”—John 14:26), and it intercedes in prayers (“We do not know what we ought to pray for, but the Spirit himself intercedes for us. … He who searches our hearts knows the mind of the Spirit, because the Spirit intercedes for the saints.” —Romans 8:26–27). Also, the Spirit can control the human mind (“the mind controlled by the Spirit is life and peace”—Romans 8:6).
(5) The Spirit gives life; note again the passage in Job cited above: “The Spirit of God has made me; the breath of the Almighty gives me life.” And in John 3:6 we have “the Spirit (pneumatos) gives birth to spirit (pneuma).”
(6) Psalm 139 contains passages that describe the omnipresence of the Spirit: “If I go up to the heavens, you are there; if I make my bed in the depths, you are there. If I rise on the wings of the dawn, if I settle on the far side of the sea, even there your hand will guide me.” (Psalm 139:7–10) There are numerous references to the Spirit “dwelling in” or “filling” the believer: “the Spirit of God lives in you” (Romans 8:9); “God’s Spirit lives in you” (1 Corinthians 3:16); “the Holy Spirit, who is in you” (1 Corinthians 6:19). The Bible also says that believers will “walk in the Spirit” (Galatians 5:16).

Thus there appears to be good justification for claiming Stoic influence in the Bible, at least within the figure of the Holy Spirit, which has always had an odd and troubling status within a monotheistic system. It is perhaps not surprising, then, that this influence is widely ignored by Christian theologians.

Furthermore, the Bible acknowledges the existence of numerous other spiritual beings in the world: Satan, the angels, and others, not to mention the many distinct human souls. At the beginning of 1 John 4 we find the following: “Dear friends, do not believe every spirit (pneumati), but test the spirits (pneumata) to see whether they are from God.” The spirits that fail the test are naturally those “of the Antichrist,” and they must be defeated. So the Bible does convey a world of numerous spirits even as it puts forth a single God. But the spirits are otherworldly, and they are not connected with physical things—except, of course, human beings. Any conception of individual and independent spirits “in things,” not to mention in all things, is decidedly anti-Christian.^30 Predictably, theologians typically dismiss all references to panpsychism as heathen or pagan primitivism.

One last point on the connections to Stoicism: It is not only pneuma that carries over into the Bible. There are also references to logos that resonate with Stoic principles. Recall that logos refers to reason or intelligence. In the Greek of the New Testament, we also find the word ‘logos’, and it is translated as “Word,” as in “the Word of God.” At the start of John 1, we learn that “in the beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God, and the Word was God.” This phrase, which is problematic from a traditional Christian standpoint, makes perfect sense as a carryover from a Stoic system in which logos (“Word”) is God. In his study of Stoic philosophy, Sandbach (1975: 72) states unequivocally that “God is logos.” Other connections between God and logos occur at John 1:14, 2 Timothy 4:2, 1 John 1:1, and Revelation 19:13. Again we seem to have an important biblical concept that was borrowed from the panpsychist Stoics.

Early Christian theology merged with Platonic, Aristotelian, and Stoic ideas to create a number of new perspectives on philosophy, most notable of which was Neo-Platonism. The third-century-AD founder of this school, Plotinus, combined notions of an ideal Realm of Forms with a monotheistic system in which the One was the divine and mystical source of all existence. The One exhibits a logos or reason-principle as it creates and sustains the natural world.

Plotinus’ major work, the Enneads, contains a number of scattered and cryptic references to a panpsychic cosmos. The most relevant of these, as was mentioned earlier, is Ennead VI, 7, in which we find Plotinus’ enigmatic discussion on life and soul as existing in all things, both in the physical world and in the “higher realm” of Platonic Forms. Furthermore, he explicitly cites Plato as holding the same view:

[I]n the plant the Reason-Principle … is a certain form of life, a definite soul. … The growing and shaping of stones, the internal molding of mountains as they rise, reveal the working of an ensouled Reason-Principle fashioning them from within. … The earth There [in the Platonic realm] is much more primally alive, … it is a reasoned Earth-Livingness. … Fire, similarly, with other such things, must be a Reason-Principle established in Matter. … That transcendent fire, being more truly fire, will be more veritably alive; the fire absolute possesses life. And the same principles apply to the other elements, water and air. … It is with this in mind that Plato says there is soul in everything of this [earthly] sphere. … It is of necessity that life be all-embracing, covering all the realms, and that nothing fail of life.

In itself, the fact that “Plato says there is soul in everything of this sphere” could simply be a reference to the world-soul. Yet it is clear from the context that Plotinus sees everything individually as alive—the Earth, fire, water, air, and the other elements. And he clearly attributes the same view to Plato. Plotinus’ reference is thus a further confirmation that Plato himself adopted a subtle form of panpsychism, a fact that evidently had some effect on the Neo-Platonist worldview.

Apart from the indirect biblical references to pneuma and logos, Christianity had little use for panpsychism. In fact, as has already been mentioned, it was positively opposed. The Bible attributes soul to man and to nothing else in nature. Only man is in God’s image, and only man was given dominion over the soulless Earth. Humanity is unique, different, and better than everything else in the world. And yet Christian thinkers valued the insights of the Greeks, and in their attempts to incorporate Greek ideas they inadvertently picked up hints of panpsychist metaphysics.

A case in point is Augustine. In The City of God (ca. 410 AD), he appropriated and further developed Aristotle’s ideas on matter. Recall that Aristotle held that each of the elements endeavors to move to its natural place: fire and air upward, earth and water down. In Physics, for example, he writes that it is “the property of fire to be carried upwards” (193a1). And in De caelo we read “For if the natural motion is upward, it will be fire or air, and if downward, water or earth.” (269a16) Augustine accepted this view, believing that all natural objects sought their appropriate station in this world in order to preserve and protect themselves:

[E]ven the lifeless bodies, which want not only sensation but seminal life, yet either seek the upper air or sink deep, or are balanced in an intermediate position, so that they may protect their existence in that situation where they can exist in most accordance with their nature. (book XI, chapter 27)

This wanting or desiring that is present in all natural things is a manifestation of love:

If we were stones, or waves, or wind, or flame, or anything of that kind, we should want, indeed, both sensation and life, yet should possess a kind of attraction towards our own proper position and natural order. For the specific gravity of bodies is, as it were, their love, whether they are carried downwards by their weight, or upwards by their levity. (book XI, chapter 28)

Augustine evidently believed that God’s love was somehow impressed into all things made by him, such that they themselves were also able to love.^31 Again, though, the panpsychist implications seem to have been lost on Augustine and his followers.

At least one Christian thinker, however, openly embraced the implications: Francis of Assisi. Francis (1181–1226) saw the presence of God in all parts of nature, and thus he viewed all things as enspirited beings. He is famous for his love of animals, but he also held insects, plants, and even rocks in highest regard. One of his earliest disciples, Thomas of Celano, wrote of Francis:

When he found many flowers growing together … he would speak to them and encourage them, as though they could understand, to praise the Lord. It was the same with the fields of corn and the vineyards, the stones in the earth and in the woods, all the beauteous meadows, the tinkling brooks, the sprouting gardens, earth, fire, air and wind. … He was wont to call all created things his brothers and sisters. (in Armstrong 1973: 9)

Armstrong further refers to Saint Bonaventure’s accounts in The Mirror of Perfection as evidence of Francis’ “being caught up in ecstatic contemplation of inanimate as well as animate things of God’s creation” and “thus [treating] even inanimate things as, to all intents and purposes, children of God” (10). Others came to the same conclusion. In his quest for a Christian solution to the environmental crisis, the historian Lynn White Jr. (1967: 1207) observes that “[Francis’] view of nature and of man rested on a unique sort of panpsychism of all things animate and inanimate.” White cites as evidence Francis’ “Canticle of the Sun,” an ode to the Sun, the Moon, Wind, Air, Water, and Fire in which each of them is treated as an animate “Brother” or “Sister” and the planet is called “Mother Earth.” Nature, Francis seems to say, is like us: ensouled, God-created, and capable of worshipping the divine.

Francis was apparently the first religious figure to explicitly employ a belief in the Christian God on behalf of a form of panpsychism. This strongly anticipated the work of Tommaso Campanella, who argued from a similar basis for his panpsychic beliefs.^32 But Francis did not lay down a systematic philosophy of spirit in nature, and so it is more correct to attribute such a theological argument for panpsychism to Campanella.

By the thirteenth century, Christian theology dominated Western philosophical views. Francis’ beliefs notwithstanding, panpsychist or pantheist ideas were largely pushed from the mainstream. If the matter was given any consideration at all, it was rather abruptly dismissed.

Aquinas did precisely that. His Summa Theologiae (circa 1260) contains just a single brief discussion of the question “What things have life?” (question 18, part Ia) Summarizing the hylozoist position—and appropriately citing Aristotle—he presents three distinct arguments:

For Aristotle says that motion is a kind of life possessed by all things that exist in nature. But all natural objects participate in motion. Therefore all natural objects participate in life.

Further, plants are said to live because [they undergo] growth and decrease. But local movement [i.e., locomotion, or physical displacement] is more perfect than that. … Since, then, all natural bodies have in themselves a principle of local movement, it would seem that all natural bodies have life.

Further, among natural bodies the elements are the less perfect; but life is attributed to them: e.g., we speak of “living water.” Therefore a fortiori other natural bodies have life.

“On the other hand,” Aquinas then cites Pseudo-Dionysius as saying that “plants live with life’s last echo,” interpreting this to mean that nothing lower than plants is alive. He completes his discussion by defining life much as Plato defined soul: as self-generating motion. Animals and plants have this power and thus are alive. Inanimate natural bodies, such as flowing waters and moving stars, have only the “appearance of self-movement.” They are in fact moved by something else—“the cause which produces them”—not “from themselves.” Hence, we call inanimate moving objects “living” only “by a metaphor,” or “by analogy.” This is clearly approaching a modern definition of life. And Aquinas is committed to the Christian view of the soul, something only humans possess. God, furthermore, is not a world-soul but a supernatural deity. Thus he sees no reason to accept any view approximating panpsychism. This, then, is the standard Christian position, essentially unchanged for the subsequent 800 years.

Notes

1. Cf. Guthrie 1962–1981, volume 1: 140–145.

2. The rough equivalency of the terms ‘mind’ and ‘soul’ continued at least through the time of Lucretius, who wrote in The Nature of Things, “Be sure that under one name you join the two, and when … I say ‘the soul,’ believe that the word will mean ‘the mind’ as well, since both make up a unit, a thing conjoint.” (III, 420–425)

3. Some modern writers refer to “analogical” arguments for panpsychism. It is true that analogy is essential in many cases, but this designation is insufficiently precise. There are many forms of analogy at play, and we need to distinguish them.

4. Aetius (I, 3, 4), in Kirk et al. 1983: 158–159.

5. Cited in Guthrie 1988 (p. 310).

6. Trepanier (2004), for example, dedicates a lengthy section to “Empedoclean panpsychism.”

7. Lucretius confirms this view: “[T]he soul is subtly built of infinitesimal atoms. … Whatever is so mobile [as the soul] must be made of very round and very tiny atoms. … Now since the soul has been revealed to be uncommonly mobile, we must grant it made of atoms very tiny, smooth, and round.” (III, 175–205)

8. This idea is most fully laid out in Timaeus (31–36), but reference to a world-soul also occurs in Philebus (28d–30a) and in Statesman (269–273).

9. One finds a few scattered references in his later works to apsychon, or inanimate and lifeless things, but none of these conclusively show that inanimateness is a distinct ontological category. In fact Plato uses the term in a variety of contexts, sometimes simply indicating “non-animal,” as we understand the term today; examples of this would include Sophist (220a, 265c) and Laws (782d, 873e). Other uses (e.g., Laws 896b) indicate that soul is historically prior to matter, and thus that matter is in this sense apsychon. But this fact, of course, doesn’t prevent soul from inhabiting material objects, or driving their movements and changes.

10. Original: tithemai gar horon horizein ta onta hōs estin ouk allo ti plēn dynamis. For Sophist I use Jowett’s translation. White (in Cooper 1997) is somewhat less clear in these passages.

11. The four categories are limit, unlimited, mixture of limit and unlimited, and cause of the mixture.

12. Some authors emphasize this fact by using the term ‘pluralistic panpsychism’.

13. Notably, the Demiurge did not create the universe ex nihilo, as did the Judeo-Christian God. He simply gave form to shapeless matter.

14. Star-souls are also discussed in Laws (898d) and in Epinomis (981e–983e).

15. The case for animals is not explicitly called out, but rather taken as self-evident. One finds in Phaedrus, for example, reference to souls in wild animals (248d, 249b).

16. The rational soul is of a different order than the others; it alone survives the body, and is immortal.

17. In the same essay we read that the swerve acts with a certain minimal interval called elachiston. This is a remarkable anticipation of quantum theory, which states that atoms can only change energy states by certain discrete or “minimal” amounts.

18. It is an open question whether all atoms swerve or only certain ones. Epicurus seems to have abandoned the idea of the special soul-atom, and so the implication is that all atoms swerve. But this was apparently never clearly spelled out. Cicero notes this ambiguity: “For if it is by natural necessity that atoms move [downward] … then it is also necessary for certain atoms (or, if they prefer, all atoms) to swerve naturally.” (in Inwood and Gerson 1997: 49) Arguably, if only some atoms swerve willfully, then this is not panpsychism—unless all objects have some minimal quota of swerving atoms. I will set this issue aside for now.

19. As to the notion that particles simply behave randomly, Conway dismisses this idea: “Randomness doesn’t help. If the action of each particle were a predetermined function of its past plus a random string of bits, then we might as well suppose that this string of bits was produced just before the universe was created, and this is excluded just as well as totally deterministic behavior.” (Schleicher 2013: 570)

20. Diogenes Laertius, cited on p. 132 of Inwood and Gerson 1997.

21. Inwood and Gerson 1997: 133.

22. Long 1974: 147.

23. “Zeno, then, defines nature thus: he says it is a craftsmanlike fire which proceeds methodically to the task of creation.” (Inwood and Gerson 1997: 150)

24. Inwood and Gerson 1997: 146.

25. On the Nature of the Gods (2, 29), in Inwood and Gerson 1997.

26. Inwood and Gerson 1997: 133.

27. Though, oddly, this concept is all but nonexistent in the Bible. The only plausible reference is in 1 John 5:8, and this is very tenuous at best: “There are three witnesses, the Spirit, the water, and the blood; and these three agree.”

28. The origins of the Old Testament may go back to 1000 BC or even further, but the majority of it probably was first written down, in Hebrew, during the period 400–200 BC—just about the time that Stoicism emerged. The oldest extant texts of this Hebrew bible are the Dead Sea Scrolls, which were probably created during the period 200 BC–0 AD. The translation of the OT from its original Hebrew into Greek occurred over the period 250–50 BC, during the height of Stoic influence. This translation is known as the Septuagint (or LXX), and it is the source of all modern-era Christian texts of the Old Testament—the oldest surviving example being the Vatican Codex of 350 AD. ‘Pneuma’ of the Septuagint was translated from the Hebrew word ‘rû(a)h’, and it appears nearly 300 times in the OT. Thus, even though the original term ‘rû(a)h’ may have predated Stoicism, its translation into ‘pneuma’, and accompanying conceptual language, was certainly subject to Greek philosophical influences. Appearances of the various forms of pneuma are even more numerous in the New Testament, which dates from the first and second centuries of the Christian era. It is in this Testament that we find the most fully developed articulation of the Spirit; and perhaps not surprisingly, the clearest association with Stoic ideas.

29. Except where another version is specified, the following passages are taken from the New International Version.

30. There is a lingering and problematic sense in which Christian theology does allow for a weak form of panpsychism. If God is omnipresent, then he is obviously in all things; this points toward panentheism. If a portion of God is in a thing, and if this portion assumes any sense of independent individuality or autonomous existence, then this could qualify as a “monistic panpsychism.” Renaissance philosophers exploit this issue, as I will show.

31. For an elaboration of this aspect of Augustine, see O’Brien 1958.

32. Campanella’s views are elaborated in chapter 3.

7 Panpsychism in the Years 1900–1950

Vigorous discussion of panpsychism continued into the 1900s. William James, Josiah Royce, and Morton Prince published important new works (cited in the preceding chapter). A significant number of major philosophers—among them Henri Bergson, Ferdinand Schiller, John Dewey, Alfred North Whitehead, and Bertrand Russell—entered the debate, offering important insights on behalf of panpsychism. Additional support came from such diverse thinkers as Pierre Teilhard de Chardin, Charles Hartshorne, Samuel Alexander, Charles Strong, Nicholai Lossky, William Montague, and Leonard Troland.

7.1 Bergson and the Early-Twentieth-Century Panpsychists

In 1903, Charles Strong (1862–1940) published Why the Mind Has a Body, a work that continued the Schopenhauerian argument that things-in-themselves have a mind-like nature. Like Schopenhauer, Strong interpreted this as a fundamentally panpsychist ontology. James was impressed with the book; he called it “a wonderful piece of clear and thorough work—quite classical in fact, and surely destined to renown.”^1

Why the Mind Has a Body is presented as a kind of textbook on the state of philosophy of mind. It addresses various arguments for interactionism and parallelism, each in a variety of forms. As was usual at the time, Strong doesn’t present an objective study but rather steers the reader toward a particular viewpoint: “psycho-physical idealism.” In support of that viewpoint, he makes arguments by Continuity and Non-Emergence^2 (287–293). Though he doesn’t explicitly mention the word ‘panpsychism’ until the very end, it is clear that he takes the panpsychist worldview. That “thought [is] to be extended to inorganic matter [thus] making mind omnipresent in nature” is said to be “precisely the conclusion at which we have arrived” (291–292). In closing the book, Strong admits that he has no “positive conception” of the mentality that underlies all things, and thus is in no position to effectively argue whether this mentality “consist[s] of as many separate feelings as there are atoms, or of one great feeling or consciousness, or of something between the two” (354).

The missing analysis of mind was addressed in Strong’s next book, Origin of Consciousness (1918), in which he explicitly advocated a panpsychist outlook. Regarding the nature of the mental, Strong adopts and expands on Clifford’s mind-stuff theory. Mind-stuff, he writes, has four central qualities: It is “in space,” “in time,” and “capable of change,” and most important, it “possesses the psychic character.” The last quality is “the core of the whole matter, without which our panpsychism would be merely materialism” (319). Manifest in humans as “attention,” it is, more generally, an intensity or vividness of experience that varies with the nature of the material object—an “accumulation of energy in a psychic state” (320).

In Origin of Consciousness Strong also addresses a potentially major weakness of the mind-stuff view: the combination problem. Any mind-stuff theory, he observes, necessarily adopts an atomistic conception of mind. Innumerable “minute feelings” must fuse to create a single high-level psychic state. A human, as a large-scale organism, lacks the perceptive ability to differentiate these many atomistic feelings, and thus by default experiences them collectively as a whole: “The fact of the case … is not that we [directly] perceive the unanalyzable feeling to be one, but only that we are unable to perceive it to be many. This, of course, in no way interferes with its actually being many.” (310) Just as ordinary objects appear to us as solid only because we are unable to see the individual atoms, so too our subjective feelings feel as one only because we cannot differentiate its components. Hence Strong’s novel solution: Combination is an illusion, owing to our cognitive limitations. It is an epistemological problem, not an ontological problem.

It was clear to contemporary readers that Strong “regarded a panpsychistic metaphysics as the key to the mind-body problem,” writes Klausner (1967: 273). Also clear, unfortunately, was “the tremendous difficulty of presenting [this] in a convincing way.” Strong explicitly admitted that, with a definite note of resignation: “The difficulty of making people believe that there is in suns and atoms anything of the nature of feeling is so mountainous that I sometimes wish I had devoted my energies to something else.” (1937: 5) Nonetheless, Strong stands out as one of the more consistent and open advocates of panpsychism in the first part of the twentieth century.

In 1905, William Montague (1873–1953) wrote a short piece, titled “Panpsychism and Monism,” in which he defended Strong’s panpsychism against criticisms raised by Theodore Flournoy—the primary one being that panpsychism is “merely verbal” and thus “methodologically useless.” This is a standard mechanistic critique. The inner mental experiences of non-human things are inherently unknowable, and thus unverifiable. They further seem to be epiphenomenal, having no causal effects in the physical world. Empirical evidence, such as a magnet’s motive power, can be described without recourse to any intrinsic noetic abilities. Of course, panpsychism is “methodologically useless” only if one chooses to ignore the broader implications. Clearly there are many potential ways in which one’s thoughts, actions, or values could be altered by adopting a panpsychist outlook.

In a 1912 article, “A Realistic Theory of Truth and Error,” Montague contrasted materialism—or “panhylism”—with two forms of panpsychism: a positive view (all matter “has something psychical about it”) and a negative view (“all matter is nothing but psychical”). After criticizing the negative or idealist version, Montague lays out his own theory, a positive variation of panpsychism that he calls hylopsychism. It is a brief and rather cryptic theory, but it attempts to make some interesting connections between time, energy, and mind.^3 He seems to be operating more on intuition than on formal reasoning, and this suggests that there must be a path allowing for all things to participate in mind without their being at root either pure mind or pure matter.

Montague continued his defense for decades. A late piece, “Human Soul and Cosmic Mind” (1945), further develops the connection between energy and mind. In it he argues that the physical manifestation of mind occurs as potential energy—a scientific concept defined as any system capable of doing work, such as a compressed spring or an object raised up into the air. Potential energy is ubiquitous in nature, and if it is equivalent to mind then mind is universal: “If mental states are identical with forms of potential energy then the extent to which some sort of mental reality is present in the universe will be the extent to which potential energy is present—and that is everywhere.” (1945: 60)

One of the most important and visionary philosophers of the turn of the twentieth century was Henri Bergson (1859–1941). His philosophical system is complex, insightful, and unusually difficult to categorize. His central themes of time and evolution tend to paint him as a process philosopher, but his discussions of mind, creativity, freedom, and numerous other themes make for an intricate, emotionally powerful, and often enigmatic philosophy.

One of the more striking features of Bergson’s thought is his flirtation with panpsychism. At times he seems to believe that mind, consciousness, or life pervades the universe and animates all matter, and yet he always stops short of clearly advocating a fully panpsychist or hylozoist position. His suggestive writings began in the late nineteenth century, one of the first being Matter and Memory (1896). He wrote of a phylogenic continuum from matter to life, the latter culminating in the human species: “[W]e can conceive an infinite number of degrees between matter and fully developed spirit. … Each of these successive degrees, which measures a growing intensity of life, corresponds to a higher tension of duration.” (221)

The concept of duration implies time, and in the realm of life this implies memory. As the complexity of organisms increases, so too does the corresponding element of memory. Humans have the greatest capacity for memory; matter has none, yet matter still possesses pure perception—that is, perception without memory. “Now,” Bergson writes, “as we have shown, pure perception, which is the lowest degree of mind—mind without memory—is really part of matter, as we understand matter.” (222) In the book’s conclusion, he characterizes consciousness as a universal phenomenon that somehow counterbalances individual beings and minds, unifying them while allowing them their uniqueness. “No doubt,” he says, “the material universe itself, defined as the totality of images, is a kind of consciousness, … a consciousness of which all the potential parts … reciprocally hinder each other from standing out.” (235) He refers repeatedly to the “confluence of mind and matter,” of “seeing the one flow into the other”—again, with matter representing pure perception and mind representing pure memory. Ultimately he concludes, in a manner not unlike that of the ancient Greeks, that movement itself is mind-like because it necessarily involves duration (i.e., continuation) and memory:

Only one hypothesis, then, remains possible: namely, that concrete movement, capable, like consciousness, of prolonging its past into its present, capable, by repeating itself, of engendering sensible qualities, already possesses something akin to consciousness, something akin to sensation. (247)

Nature, on this reading, is a latent consciousness with the inherent power of mind.

We find similarly suggestive passages in Bergson’s most famous book, Creative Evolution (1907). Recalling Schopenhauer, he calls “pure willing” the “current that runs through matter, communicating life to it” (260). In an almost hylozoistic manner he argues that both matter and life are like an “undivided flux,” each interpenetrating the other. But he is silent on any further implications or articulations of panpsychism.

A lecture Bergson delivered in 1911 at the University of Birmingham was included, under the title “Life and Consciousness,” in a volume published in French as L’Energie spirituelle and in English translation as Mind-Energy. In his preface to English edition, the translator, H. Wildon Carr, comments that just as the earlier conceptions of physical reality have been unified under the concept of energy, so too can the ultimate psychical reality be described as such: “[The] dynamic conception of psychical reality has replaced the older concept of mind [identified with awareness or consciousness], and the physical analogy suggests energy as the most expressive term for it.” (in Bergson 1911/1920: vi)

In the published version of the lecture, Bergson argues for an identity between mind and consciousness, and posits memory—along with “anticipation of the future”—as a leading feature of consciousness. “In principle,” he then claims, “consciousness is co-extensive with life.” (11) As to whether inert matter has any aspects of mind, he claims that “matter is necessity, consciousness is freedom.” Yet mind is an energy-form that somehow inserts itself into matter and animates it—something that can happen only if the two are fundamentally linked:

We may surmise that these two realities, matter and consciousness, are derived from a common source. If … matter is the inverse of consciousness … then neither matter nor consciousness can be explained apart from one another. (23)

Matter would not be receptive to life unless it had a preexisting and inherent tendency to it. “In other words, life must have installed itself in a matter which had already acquired some of the characters of life without the work of life.” (26–27) Again, highly suggestive, but something less than outright panpsychism.

The last and perhaps clearest indication comes from Duration and Simultaneity (1922), which contains Bergson’s strongest statement of his process philosophy. All space-time events proceed literally from moment to moment, each phase at once both something new and something old. Every event retains some aspect of preceding events; otherwise there would be no continuity to the world. Things persist in space and in time, energy flows continuously, and characteristics and qualities carry over from past into future. There are both novelty and stability in all aspects of reality. The aspect of stability, of the carryover of past into future, is, again, an aspect of memory. The future always remembers the past, if only to a small degree, even as it creates something new. Thus memory necessarily inheres in all things. Since memory is equated with mind, the obvious conclusion is that mind is in all things. Bergson is notably clear on this point:

What we wish to establish is that we cannot speak of a reality that endures without inserting consciousness into it. … It is impossible to imagine or conceive a connecting link between the before and after without an element of memory and, consequently, of consciousness.

We may perhaps feel averse to the use of the word “consciousness” if an anthropomorphic sense is attached to it. [But] there is no need to take one’s own memory and transport it, even attenuated, into the interior of the thing. … It is the opposite course we must follow. … Duration is essentially a continuation of what no longer exists into what does exist. This is real time, perceived and lived. … Duration therefore implies consciousness; and we place consciousness at the heart of things for the very reason that we credit them with a time that endures. (1922/1965: 48–49)

Capek (1971: 302) calls this passage “the basis of Bergson’s panpsychism,” noting that it makes little difference whether we apply the term ‘panpsychism’, the description “organic view of nature,” or the term ‘proto-mentalism’. The net result is the same: “there is no question that [Bergson] regarded physical events as ‘proto-mental’” (308).^4

In the end Bergson’s panpsychism is still perplexing. The relevant passages are somewhat isolated, and the deeper implications seem to be unexplored. Bergson never explicitly mentions panpsychism, nor does he discuss other comparable theories, nor does he cite any of the extensive history on the matter. This is due in part to his writing style, but one is still left wanting further elaboration.

7.2 Schiller

A major milestone in the development of panpsychist philosophy occurred in 1907: the publication of Ferdinand Schiller’s book Studies in Humanism. Schiller (1864–1937) is best known as a humanist and pragmatist, and his unique interpretation of these approaches was original and insightful. The four major pragmatist philosophers of the early twentieth century—Peirce, James, Dewey, and Schiller—all held panpsychist views. Yet this fact doesn’t appear to bear directly on pragmatism, which traditionally includes the notion that truth is not absolute but depends in some sense on human interaction and the notion that the critical factor in a philosophical theory is its consequence, its implications in the real world. Perhaps openness to panpsychism is attributable to the flexibility of thought engendered by pragmatism—the willingness to repudiate standard or fixed notions of truth—and to a view of experience as an ongoing process that is in some sense constitutive of both subject and object.

Schiller took up the personal and subjective aspects of pragmatism and developed them in light of a deeply humanistic and panpsychic perspective. Even in his first major book, Riddles of the Sphinx (1891), he demonstrates an openly panpsychist worldview. The central idea of that book is that matter is driven by evolutionary forces toward an ever-greater form of spirit, and in fact is essentially a spiritual substance: “Matter ultimately [is] but a form of the Evolution of Spirit.” (276) This is a striking interpretation of evolution, anticipating many of the ideas that Teilhard would take up some 40 years later. Schiller observes—as Teilhard would—that “the single process of Evolution is a correlated development of both [matter and spirit]” (288). He also anticipates Teilhard’s thesis of complexity-consciousness: “the growth of the complexity of material organization should be the invariable accompaniment of the growth of consciousness.”

Schiller’s panpsychist idealism draws heavily on scientific ideas for confirmation. He reiterates the dynamist position that atoms are simply centers of force, and that force, as an ontological category, is to be interpreted as a spiritual or mental entity:

Force is a conception which inevitably implies the spiritual character of ultimate reality. Historically it is undeniable that Force is depersonalized Will, that the prototype of Force is Will. … The [related] sense of Effort also … is irresistibly suggestive of the action of a spiritual being. For how can there be effort without intelligence and will? (274)

The reference to Schopenhauer’s system is clear. In the end, a form of intelligence exists in all levels of matter. The force-atoms can properly be thought of as monad-like spiritual things possessing proto-mental characteristics: “it is not very much more difficult to conceive of an atom as possessing rudimentary consciousness and individuality” (277).

Schiller observes that most contemporary forms of idealism are classically humanist, in that mind either requires or is reflected in human mentality. Evolution shows that the Earth existed long before humans, and critics have used this fact to argue that without spiritual beings there could be no idealism. His “evolutionary idealism” answers that objection by claiming that “material evolution is an integral part of the world-process, and obeys the same law as spiritual evolution.” Thus we must rightly conceive of atoms as “spiritual beings,” for “the material is but an earlier and less perfect phase of the spiritual development” (306).

These early themes are developed more fully in Schiller’s 1907 book Studies in Humanism, in which the notions of truth and reality are central. He directly challenges the dominant mechanistic view of objective reality, of a reality unaffected by the thoughts and perceptions of the observer. Objective reality implies a notion of absolute truth, fixed and eternal, awaiting our discovery. For Schiller such ideas are nonsensical. Both truth and reality are literally created by human beings. Our minds, working on the raw chaos of the material world, condition and shape that which we ultimately call facts or reality. Humans are active participants in the world; the making of truth is “an active endeavor, in which our whole nature is engaged” (425). He is emphatic: “reality can, as such and wholly, be engendered by the consequences of our dealings with it” (428).

Schiller takes our “making of truth” and “making of reality” to be central to any acceptable epistemology. The mere act of knowing, of encountering and contemplating, changes both the knower and the known. The knower is affected by his encounter with any given object; his active selection of things and his reactive bodily states are the most direct ways in which he is changed. The object known is affected either by physical consequences of being known or by its sensitivity to the state of the knower—something like when an actor suffers stage fright as a result of “being known” by the audience. Since obviously both the knower and the known are aspects of reality, it is clear that reality is actually changed by the act of knowing.

One can perhaps see how humans or the so-called higher animals may be affected by the processes of knowing and being known. But what about the lower animals, or plants, or inanimate objects? Schiller is adamant that all objects are altered by such processes. He takes the standard example: a stone—an object that displays an “apparent absence of response” and seems utterly unconcerned about its environment. But this apparent unresponsiveness is illusory:

A stone, no doubt, does not apprehend us as spiritual beings. … But does this amount to saying that it does not apprehend us at all, and takes no note whatever of our existence? Not at all; it is aware of us and affected by us on the plane on which its own existence is passed. … It faithfully exercises all the physical functions, and influences us by so doing. It gravitates and resists pressure, and obstructs … vibrations, etc., and makes itself respected as such a body. And it treats us as if of a like nature with itself, on the level of its understanding … . (442)

The common world of knowledge, the common reality between a person and a stone, is clearly not the same level of complexity as that between two people, but it is no less real. It is a brute plane of existence, one of mass, force, and temperature; it is one in which the two objects, knower and known, come together with different histories and different sensitivities. The stone “plays its part and responds according to the measure of its capacity.” Schiller responds to the charge that this view is “sheer hylozoism” as follows: “What if it is, so long as it really brings out a genuine analogy? The notion that ‘matter’ must be denounced as ‘dead’ … no longer commends itself to modern science.” (443) He then correctly notes that his outlook is best described as panpsychism—as seeing all things with a mind analogous to that of a human. This is why he emphasizes that his view is that of humanism. And it also is humanistic in the sense that it seeks to fully and deeply integrate the human into the universe. After all, the true end objective of any valid system of philosophy is “to make the human and the cosmic more akin, and to bring them closer to us, that we may act upon them more successfully.”

Thus Schiller makes his case that, in the process of knowing, both the knower and the known are altered, changed, re-made. The critic may reply with the charge that this is not what one means by “making reality,” but that is beside the point. Of course Schiller doesn’t mean that we can create something out of nothing, or that we have some strange paranormal powers. We work with the stuff of the universe, which is meaningless and in a sense non-existent in itself until we act on it and make it something known, something real.

Schiller was the first to make the leap of understanding and to see that all things have an aspect of mentality after the manner of the human, and that therefore all things, not just humans, have some power to make reality. This is not merely panpsychism, but an articulated theory of mind as an active and universal quality. He is very explicit on this point: Humanism, as he conceives it, sees “the occurrence of something essentially analogous to the human making of reality throughout the universe” (437).

Such a theory of mind has gone completely unexamined by twentieth-century philosophers—predictably so, because it was in direct opposition to the positivism and realism that has dominated recent discussions. And yet, Schiller argued, something approaching a realist position is obtained, because of our common human physiology, culture, and history. Of course, the common world among humans will be different from the one that includes other animals, or the one with inanimate objects. Such a view might be called a qualified or conditional realism. Of recent philosophers, only Skolimowski (1994) has developed this line of thinking further.

Schiller maintained this overall philosophical outlook throughout his subsequent writings. In one of his last works, Logic for Use (1929), he reiterates many of the themes found in Studies of Humanism. In discussing the meaning of humans as makers of reality, he comments: “For what is real and true for us depends on our selecting interests: the answers we get follow from the questions we put.” (445) He emphasizes his pragmatism and his thesis of action: “Real knowledge does not lie idle—it colours our life. We act on it, and act differently. So reality is altered, not only in us but through us.” And he again points out that every object has some qualified power to make reality and to display dynamic sensitivity to the world:

[W]e can say that inanimate objects also are responsive to each other, and modify their behavior accordingly. A stone is not indifferent to other stones. On the contrary, it is attracted by every material body in the physical world. … The stone responds, after its fashion, to our manipulation. Treat them differently, and they behave differently: that is as true of stones as of men. (447)

Thus all objects participate in a common world based on their own capacities and sensitivities. From Schiller’s panpsychist perspective, this is the process by which things collectively create an inter-subjective world. Panpsychism is the true and only basis for a reified existence.

7.3 Alexander, Lossky, Troland, and Dewey

In 1914 Samuel Alexander (1859–1938) published an important article titled “The Basis of Realism.” Alexander was, along with Moore, Russell, James, Holt, and Montague, one of the so-called new realists; they argued, among other things, that objects exist independent of the human mind, but not necessarily of mind in general. Alexander proposed a metaphysical system for an evolving universe in which there are six levels of emergent reality: space-time, primary qualities of matter, secondary qualities of matter, life, animal mind, and deity. This emergent hierarchy is significant for two reasons. First, it indicates his conception of an evolutionary universe, moving from space and time through matter, life, and on to God. Alexander was one of the first philosophers, along with Schiller, to envision such a grand sweep of evolution, and he thereby anticipated some of the more important ideas of Teilhard and Skolimowski.^5 Second, it emphasizes his unique dual conception of mind: mind in the ordinary human sense, and mind as a more ontological and panpsychist reality. On the latter view, mind is seen as representing the connection between levels in the hierarchy. In particular, each specific level functions as the mind of the levels below. At the level of space-time, space is seen as primary, time as secondary; thus Alexander can claim that “time is the mind of space.” Similarly, life is seen, when viewed from below, as the mind of space, time, and matter. We humans are the “mind of life,” and we tend to identify this mind as true mind only because it is our privileged point of view.

The central point of “The Basis of Realism” is that our cognitive relationship with things is essentially the same as the relationship between any two objects. Alexander (1914/1960: 189) first notes that “mind and things are continuous in kind.” This continuity between knower and known is described as one of “compresence,” or co-present existence. Thus, he writes, “our compresence with physical things … is a situation of the same sort as the compresence of two physical things with one another” (191), or, more generally, “between any two existences in the world whatsoever.”^6 The focus is on the comprehension of things of an equal or lower order in the ontological hierarchy:

Mind enjoys itself and contemplates life and physical things. The living being, the tree, enjoys itself and contemplates the air it breathes. … The distinction may be carried further down … and it may be carried up [to the realm of the divine]. … The universe consists of distinct real existences of different order, compresent with each other and “knowing” each other in such measure as is possible to them at their various stages of development. (195)

He concludes the essay with an argument by analogy:

[M]atter receives much more [potency] than materialism credits it with. … It is even possible that the union of body and mind which we find in the human person may turn out in the end to be typical of every form of existence from the lowest to the highest and perhaps of the universe as a whole.

Thus he argues on the basis of first principles for panpsychism, defining mind as integral to the very structure of reality.

In perhaps his most famous work, Space, Time, and Deity (1920), Alexander develops these ideas further, rejecting strict parallelism between the physical and psychical and opting to see mind as an emergent aspect of each level of existence. The standard response to anti-parallelism is, he says, some form of animism in which the psychical is present in all things but is independent of the physical (volume II: 12–13). Instead of animism, he proposes a panpsychist quasi-identity theory in which physical events are causal on the physical, mental events are causal on the mental, many physical events are identical to their corresponding mental events, but some physical events have no mental counterpart. Each emergent mental level is “expressible completely or without residue in terms of the lower stage” (67). The mind is therefore “equivalent only to a portion of [a] thing”; that is, it is a subset of the total entity. Alexander thus arrives at a hierarchical form of panpsychism, with higher levels of mind building on lower levels:

For though matter has no life, it has something which plays in it the part which life plays in the living organism and mind plays in the person; and even on the lowest level of existence [i.e. motion], any motion has its soul, which is time. Thus matter is not merely dead as if there was nothing in it akin to life. It is only dead in that it is not as alive as organisms are. … We are compelled to the conclusion that all finite existence is alive, or in a certain sense animated. (67)

The human mind is an emergent phenomenon of our lower levels of existence—our life, our matter, etc.—and this is a process that is repeated universally; “everywhere this result appears to be secured as it is in our own persons.” Hence, “all existence is linked in a chain of affinity, and there is nothing which does not in virtue of its constitution respond to ourselves … ; so there is nothing dead, or senseless in the universe, [even] Space-Time itself being animated” (69).

The early years of the twentieth century witnessed a minor wave of panpsychist thinking in Russia. Among the more notable philosophers in that vein was Peter Ouspensky (or Uspenskii) (1878–1947). In Tertium Organum (1912/1981) he elaborates a startlingly clear and explicit panpsychism; in places, it is unparalleled in its candor. Adopting a strong form of the Continuity argument, Ouspensky argues passionately that, since man is alive and enspirited and is an integral part of nature, these same phenomena must be omnipresent:

If intelligence exists in the world, then intelligence must exist in everything, although it may be different in its manifestations. … There can be nothing dead or mechanical in Nature. If life and feeling exist at all, they must exist in everything. … We must admit that every phenomenon, every object has a mind. A mountain, a tree, a river, the fish in the river, drops of water, rain, a plant, fire—each separately must possess a mind of its own. (1912/1981: 165–166)

Shortly after the release of Tertium Organum, Nicholai Lossky (or Losskii) (1870–1965) published an important book detailing a panpsychist ontology: Mir kak organicheskoe tseloe (The World as an Organic Whole) (1917/1928). Lossky was the most influential of the Russian neo-Leibnizians, a Christian-oriented movement that began in the 1880s with Alexey Kozlov. For his part, Kozlov envisioned a form of monadology in which the monads, unlike Leibniz’s variation, had the essential ability to interact. These interacting, spiritual, conscious monads were conceived as the basis of all reality. Lossky elaborated on Kozlov’s system in the 1901 article “Kozlov: His Panpsychism.”^7

Lossky called his system “intuitivism.” It was more articulated and far-reaching than Kozlov’s, incorporating a radical interpretation of Christian metaphysics. Aligned with both the new realism of Alexander and Montague and the classical idealism of Berkeley, intuitivism held that perception is reality—that is, that reality is identical to that which is presented in the mind of the perceiver. “Knowledge,” Lossky writes, “is not a copy … but reality itself.”^8 Following Leibniz, he argues that the world is composed of innumerable “substantival agents,” each superspatial and supertemporal, each interacting with the entire cosmos, and each creating reality through cognitive acts. This is the basis for the vision elaborated in The World as an Organic Whole. All objects of the material world, including humans, other animals, plants, rocks, the Earth, are in fact just substantival agents in different stages of evolution. Natural processes, forces, and events are all the result of actions of such agents. This was Lossky’s view even many years later:

[A]ll events, all processes—i.e. all real being—are created by substantival agents: the singing of a tune, the experiencing of feelings or desires is the manifestation of some self. Acts of attraction and repulsion and movements in space are produced by human beings and also by electrons, protons, etc., in so far as substantival agents also lie at their basis. (1951: 253)

These agents are to be conceived as spiritual entities, and thus the world is profoundly ensouled. Starchenko (1994: 661) explains that, on Lossky’s view, spirituality “is spread throughout the world, even through material nature, but in discrete, strictly apportioned portions, so that even a small portion of rock crystal had a special ‘indistinct soul’ that aspired to a definite goal known only to it.”

Substantival agents fundamentally reflect human personhood, and thus are to be considered as persons in their own right. These persons are structured in a hierarchical fashion, from subatomic particles up to the cosmos itself. Each level of being, and each object or system within those levels, is a “person of persons,” both composed of lesser agents and a part of larger-scale ones. This is Lossky’s doctrine of hierarchical personalism; it recalls both Cardano’s and Fechner’s hierarchical views of the world, but is more explicit and more articulated. Agents surrender a portion of their independence to enter into alliances, forming larger-scale beings:

The combination of several agents … is a means of attaining more complex stages of existence. … That results in such a hierarchy of unities as an atom, a molecule, a crystal, a unicellular organism, a multicellular organism, a community of organisms like a beehive or a nest of termites; in the sphere of the human life there are nations and mankind as a whole; further, there is our planet, the solar system, the universe. Each subsequent stage of unification possesses higher creative powers than the preceding and is headed by a personality on a higher stage of developments. (1951: 256)

The preceding passage suggests an elaboration of Leibniz’s thesis of the dominant monad and of Whitehead’s “organism of organisms” concept.

Lossky, however, denied that his view was a form of panpsychism, which he defined as making an identification between mental and physical processes. Mental and physical events are not identical but are related via a common basis in spirit. The net result, however, clearly fits the broader definition of panpsychism: “Since all matter is active and purposive in character, so that it is capable of progressing to higher levels of being, it must be recognized that there is no lifeless matter. … Matter is living because the basis of it is spirit.” (1917/1928: 171)

In 1918, Leonard Troland, a professor of psychology at Harvard University, argued for an analytical form of panpsychism that he called “paraphysical monism.” Following Clifford’s mind-stuff theory, Troland claimed that the psychic realm has elementary atomic particles that are counterparts of the physical atoms. At the time, physics recognized only two elementary particles, protons and electrons; thus he argued that there must exist “at most only two kinds of psychical atoms”: “para-electrons” and “para-protons.” All conceivable mental states and feelings, then, would be seen as combinations of these two psychical atoms.

Since physical atoms know only two forces, attraction and repulsion, Troland claimed by analogy that the psychical atoms feel only the corresponding psychical qualities, “pleasantness” and “unpleasantness”—yet another implicit reference to Empedocles’ Love and Strife. Evolution in the physical world tends toward greater cohesion and integration, and therefore the parallel psychical realm tends toward ever-greater pleasantness or happiness in an objective sense of the word. He called this the “psychical law of hedonic selection” (1918: 58).

Troland revised and developed his thesis in a 1922 article, titled “Psychophysics as the Key to the Mysteries of Physics and of Metaphysics,” in which he offers an early insight into the philosophical importance of relativity theory: that it implies active participation by the observer: “all three of the fundamental dimensions of physics [space, time, mass] are conditional for their objective significance upon the conditions of observation” (145).^9 Troland then notes that the parallelism between physics and the mental realm implies the existence of a certain regularity or law-like behavior between them—“psycho-physical bridging laws.” He was one of few philosophers to argue that “consciousness is at least in part representable as a mathematical function of certain aspects of organic structure and activity” (148). This led him to conclude that a form of the identity theory must be true—that “there exists a point-to-point correspondence between the constitution of immediate experience and that of the cortical activity” (150). As a consequence, “we are required to treat mind as if it were a substance and to identify it with the reality of matter” (152). He called this new, revised view “psychical monism.” He claimed that it had originated with Fechner in the mid 1800s, but he also cited Clifford, Prince, Strong, and Paulsen as advocates. In spite of these panpsychic references, Troland doesn’t make it clear that psychical monism is necessarily panpsychism until the end of the article. He notes that psychical activity must be associated not only with the brain as a whole but with each level of structure, from individual neuron down to atom: “For every neuron in the nervous system and for every atom in each neuron there must be a real psychical fact which is related to my consciousness.” (156) Thus, each person’s individual field of consciousness must be “considered the focus of a vast psychical nervous system … made not of protons and electrons but of atoms of sentiency.” This is a straightforward application of the mind-stuff theory.

But, Troland continues, “you cannot stop here,” because the continuity of physical nature compels us to envision a psychical universe “which corresponds point-for-point … with all the constituents of my organism and of my environment; indeed, with the totality of the physical universe” (157). He refers to this as “the panpsychic extension of consciousness” to all physical reality. Furthermore, he argues, this view, far from being inconsequential, suggests a new method of metaphysical research:

This new method … consists simply in determining carefully the laws which link the factors of human consciousness with those of brain function and then generalizing these laws … to any physical structure or process whatever. The possibility of doing this rests upon the continuity of nature and upon the belief that human consciousness is sufficiently complex to exemplify all of the elementary psycho-physical relationships. (161)

According to Troland, panpsychic “psychical monism” has great merit and “should be expected … to take the philosophical world by storm” (153). That it has not done so is due, he says, to the “habitually fuzzy methods of thinking” of professional philosophers and psychologists.

In 1925, the fourth major pragmatist, John Dewey (1859–1952), published his most significant philosophical work, Experience and Nature. In examining the connection between body and mind, Dewey comments that medieval views of causality led to stark contrasts between the two; as a result, “there were no intermediates to shade gradually the black of body into the white of spirit” (1925: 251). He then compares the physical bases of organic and non-organic things, concluding that, when properly understood, both types of objects share in comparable “qualities of interaction.” This continuity between organic and inorganic is the basis for his quasi-panpsychism.

Dewey explains that any living organism exhibits certain basic qualities that we typically associate with life: needs, efforts, and satisfactions. But these processes are not unique to life. He proceeds to define each of those qualities more closely: A need is a “condition of tensional distribution of energies” wherein a body is placed in an “unstable equilibrium,” efforts are movements or changes that “modify environing bodies” in such a way that equilibrium is restored, and satisfaction is the actual restoration of that equilibrium (253). The need-effort-satisfaction process is a “concrete state of events” that is common to all things, including plants:

[T]here is nothing which marks off the plant from the physico-chemical activity of inanimate bodies. The latter also are subject to conditions of disturbed inner equilibrium, which lead to activity in relation to surrounding things, and which terminate after a cycle of changes … .

There is, of course, a difference between a plant and something like an iron molecule, and the difference “lies in the way in which physico-chemical energies are interconnected and operate, whence different consequences mark inanimate and animate activity respectively” (254). The emphasis on consequences again displays Dewey’s pragmatist orientation. A plant, he claims, actively seeks to maintain its original structure. An iron molecule, on the other hand, “shows no bias in favor of remaining simple iron; it had just as soon, so to speak, become iron-oxide.” Yet, of course, an iron atom retains its structure even when bound with oxygen atoms in the form of rust. The interaction with oxygen becomes dominant, and thereafter the combined structure that we call rust is what acts differently than pure iron.

Dewey doesn’t attribute mind or psyche to iron molecules. These are qualities of the specially organized forms that we call “life.” And yet something like sensitivity may apply to iron, in that it has the power of selection in its interaction with the environment. Iron reacts only with oxygen (under normal circumstances), and thus discriminates in favor of it. “Discrimination,” Dewey adds (256), “is the essence of sensitivity.”

The critical issue then is the continuity between humanity and nature, and once again a Continuity argument tends toward panpsychism. In his 1940 article “Time and Individuality,” Dewey elaborates this idea from the perspective of temporality. Adopting something of a process view, he observes that time-embeddedness is central to the meaning of the human: “Temporal seriality is the very essence … of the human individual.” (1940/1988: 102) Our life-history and progressive interactions with the world are the defining characteristics of our existence as individuals. Furthermore, science reveals that “temporal quality and historical career are a mark of everything” (104), from human beings to atomic particles. This, therefore, implies a kind of individuated personality in all things, including human individuals and non-human “physical individuals.” Such a viewpoint, Dewey argues, “does not mean that physical and human individuals are identical, nor that the things which appear to us to be nonliving have the distinguishing characteristics of organisms. The difference between the inanimate and the animate is not so easily wiped out. But it does show that there is no fixed gap between them.” (108)

Dewey sought to avoid supernaturalism, and in a unified, naturalistic universe a compelling case can be made for attributing mind-like or person-like qualities to all things. Putting it concisely, Hartshorne (1937: 40) says of his view that “if man is natural, then nature is manlike.” For Hartshorne, such continuity logically and necessarily implies panpsychism: “Consistently carried out, [Dewey’s] attitude here must, if I am not deceived, carry him all the way to a radical panpsychism, according to which all process has a psychic character.” (40–41) And yet Dewey himself was apparently unwilling to embrace this logical conclusion. He has been justly criticized for his half-hearted stance. Rorty (1995: 1), for example, acknowledges that “[a] sort of panpsychism … loomed large in … Dewey’s mind.” He proceeds to construct a “hypothetical Dewey” who was “a naturalist without being a panpsychist,” the point being “to separate … what I think is dead in Dewey’s thought” (3).^10 Of course, it is not the panpsychism itself that is dead, but rather, perhaps, Dewey’s formulation of it.

Panpsychist ideas continued to draw attention throughout the 1920s. In Mind and Its Place in Nature (1925), the philosopher Durant Drake (1878–1933) advocated another mind-stuff form of panpsychism. He argued that the basic building blocks of matter—energy, force, electricity—must be understood as having noetic components: “these units of matter are psychic units” (94). Such an understanding supplements rather than challenges the scientific view. These psychic units, furthermore, are neither conscious nor aware, as those qualities are reserved for highly evolved organisms. Thus, he writes, “it would be wrong to use ‘mental’ or ‘feeling’ to denote the stuff of which things are made” (98). Likewise with the notions of thought, sensation, emotion, and will. Such “poetic and fanciful” anthropomorphization would be an inaccurate portrayal.

Yet Drake sees the stuff of reality as intimately psychic. “The term ‘panpsychism’,” he writes,

may properly be applied to our theory; but we must understand that it is only mind-stuff that is universal, not mind itself. … The whole world is indeed, in a sense, alive. … It is an enormously intricate pattern of psychic units, continually changing their interrelations. (99)

Drake’s main argument is based on continuity. Humans are made of the same materials as all things. Hence, “we are therefore free to believe that the stuff that is deployed in this or that order throughout the universe is the same sort of stuff that composes us, sentient being that we are.” Such a worldview has no effect on science, but despite this it has a number of virtues:

It does assert our thoroughgoing kinship with all the rest of the natural world. It puts an end to the need of introducing such magical entities as “souls” or “entelechies,” and … explains consciousness in natural terms. It enables us to explain the origin of minds [and] to see how matter affects mind, and how mind affects matter. (100–101)

Panpsychism, for Drake, solves important philosophical problems and offers an integrative worldview that places humans and the human mind in a larger natural order.

Philosophers of science were becoming aware of panpsychist theories in the late 1920s, and a long period of scientific interest in the topic was beginning (as I explain in the following chapter). For example, the fields of psychiatry and psychoanalysis were developing and branching away from philosophy, and they too brought certain panpsychist concepts into their realm of discussion. The psychoanalyst Wilhelm Reich, following Hartmann, advanced ideas connecting the unconscious with all of nature and thus leading to a putative resolution of the mind-body problem.^11 According to Brown (1959: 315), the psychologist Sandor Ferenczi believed that a movement toward a “sophisticated” form of animism was useful in psychoanalysis:

Ferenczi saw psychoanalysis as marking a significant step forward in general scientific methodology, a step which he defined as “a return to a certain extent to the methods of ancient animistic science” and “the reestablishment of an animism no longer anthropocentric.”

According to Ferenczi (1926/1950: 256), Sigmund Freud himself had supported such a move:

Naive animism transferred human psychic life en bloc, without analysis, on to natural objects. [Freudian] psycho-analysis, however, dissected human psychic activity, pursued it to the limit where psychic and physical come in contact … and thus freed psychology from anthropocentrism.

The result was a “purified animism” that Freud employed to the benefit of his psychoanalytic technique.

7.4 Whitehead and the Emergence of Process Philosophy

The best-known and most controversial panpsychist of the twentieth century was Alfred North Whitehead (1861–1947). The nominal founder of process philosophy, Whitehead took the insights of Heraclitus, Bergson, James, and Russell and combined them with the revelations of the so-called new physics of the day to create an intricate and complex philosophical system. Process philosophy saw time as a fundamental ontological entity, something deeply implicated in the nature of being. Given that all matter is dynamic, and that space is more properly viewed as space-time, there is clearly a sense in which all things can be seen as “events”—that is, occurrences in space and time. On this view, the event is the fundamental reality of the world.

The importance of Whitehead’s system and its continuing role in panpsychist thought demand a relatively detailed discussion of his ideas.

The third phase of Whitehead’s philosophical career—the so-called metaphysical phase—began in 1924, when at age 63 he accepted a professorship in philosophy at Harvard. In the next year he published the first of a number of works that included either intimations or outright affirmations of panpsychism. His panpsychist theory of mind is relatively well known and has been widely discussed, most recently by Griffin (1998), De Quincey (2002), and Clarke (2003).

As the focal point of Whitehead’s metaphysical system, events—also called “occasions” or “actual occasions”—constitute the substance of the world and hence are truly fundamental. They are the sole components of reality in a creative cosmos. Occasions are “the final real things of which the world is made up. There is no going behind actual [occasions] to find anything more real.” (1929/1978: 18) They constitute everything from God down to “the most trivial puff of existence in far-off empty space.” Though they differ greatly in intensity, importance, and functionality, all occasions are at root fundamentally alike. Most important for present purposes, these transitory actual occasions all embody an aspect of mind, namely as “experience”: “these actual entities are drops of experience, complex and interdependent.” If all real things are occasions, and all occasions are “drops of experience,” then all things contain an experiential, and hence mental, quality.

Panpsychism is thus at the core of Whitehead’s worldview, and even more so of his conception of mind. Human beings, as natural entities, experience a particularly high-grade sort of mind—one that includes consciousness, complex feelings, and analytic abilities. Our qualities of mind, which are unique to us, do not apply to other beings. In no sense would Whitehead attribute complex, human-like mental qualities to all things. But this fundamental mode of existence—experientiality, subjectivity—is, he says, built into the very fabric of the universe. Experience is inseparable from existence.

The first major book of Whitehead’s metaphysical phase was Science and the Modern World (1925). Nominally a history of science, it also articulates a new conception of science based roughly on quantum wave theory. Quantum particles, as we know, can assume only discrete energy states. Energy is not infinitely divisible, but exists as multiples of certain minimal quanta, or quantum units. That may have been the idea that had led James to speculate that experience too, and even time itself, was likewise quantized into discrete units. Whitehead seems to have adopted the idea and developed it further. In addition, quantum particles are defined by temporally evolving probability functions, and hence must be viewed dynamically. Matter is not a substance, it is a process. “Nature is a structure of evolving processes. The reality is the process.” (Whitehead 1925/1967: 72) He calls this approach the “new doctrine of organism” (36), offering it as a replacement for conventional materialism.

Processes are naturally defined in terms of events. Every event has a past, a set of contemporaries, and a future; thus each event has “anticipation”—a feeling or sense for its place in the sequence of the universe. This constitutes a kind of self-knowledge, not unlike the self-knowledge that each person has. We have a fundamental knowledge of our own “total bodily event”—of ourselves as whole organisms. And this knowledge is the model on which we must view all events:

I generalize by the use of the principle that this total bodily event is on the same level as all other events, except for an unusual complexity and stability of inherent pattern. The strength of the theory of mechanistic materialism has been the demand that no arbitrary breaks be introduced into nature. … I accept this principle. But if you start from the immediate facts of our psychological experience, as surely an empiricist should begin, you are at once led to the organic conception of nature … . (73)

And in “organic” Whitehead intends to include “the organic unities of electrons, protons, molecules, and living bodies.” This is his first step toward panpsychism.

On the one hand Whitehead finds it “difficult to believe that the experienced world is an attribute of our own personality” (90), as subjectivism would have it; on the other hand, it is clear to him that mind or mentality is somehow intimately involved in the substance of reality. He explains that the more appropriate view of a provisional realism—or, following Peirce, objective idealism—is a combination of the other two views: “[T]he world disclosed in sense-perception is a common world, transcending the individual recipient. … [But also], cognitive mentality is in some way inextricably concerned in every detail.” This passage may be read more as a description than as an endorsement, but clearly Whitehead favors the approach it sets forth.

Later in the book he elaborates further: “A natural event is only an abstraction from a complete actual occasion.” (170) More to the point, “A complete occasion includes that which in cognitive experience takes the form of memory, anticipation, imagination, and thought.” Just as every event can anticipate, so can every event remember, imagine, and even “think” to some degree. These qualities seem to belong to all events, and to characterize their mentality, as it were. Using his infamously obscure terminology, Whitehead describes the situation as follows:

In each case there is one finite eternal object prehended within the occasion as the vertex of a finite hierarchy. This breaking off from an actual illimitability is what in any occasion marks off that which is termed mental from that which belongs to the physical event to which the mental functioning is referred. (171)

Hence it seems that, at a minimum, every occasion—that is, every event whatsoever—possesses both a mental and a physical aspect or dimension. This foreshadows his later assignment of mental and physical “poles” to all events.

A closing indication of panpsychist thinking comes in Whitehead’s declaration that every occasion possesses experientiality: “Consider an occasion a … . What a is in itself, is that it is a unit of realized experience.” (174) At the very least, all this points to an advocacy of panexperientialism, which by most accounts is a form of panpsychism.

The dual mental-physical nature of occasions or events returns more explicitly in Whitehead’s 1926 book Religion in the Making. He describes humans and animals as embodying a sequence of occasions obviously both mental and material; these proceed together “in the very closest connection” (1926a: 106). But “in the case of a bit of inorganic matter, any associate route of mentality seems to be negligible”—and by ‘negligible’ he means approaching, but not equal to, zero. Thus even something as small as an electron follows both mental and physical routes, even if the former are vastly outweighed by the latter. This point is emphasized a few pages later: “[T]he most complete concrete fact is dipolar, physical and mental. But … the proportion of importance, as shared between the two poles, may vary from negligibility to dominance of either pole.” (114) There is some latent ambiguity here, because in principle it is possible that not all occasions (“facts”) are “complete” and thus not every occasion would necessarily have a mental pole. But in context it is reasonably clear that all occasions are dipolar in nature, and that panpsychism is the result.

Any remaining ambiguity is erased with Whitehead’s short essay “Time,” also published in 1926.^12 In it he writes that “each occasion is dipolar, and that one pole is the physical occasion and the other pole is the mental occasion” (303). He further explains that there is a relationship between the two poles: “the mental occasion supersedes the physical occasion.” The suggestion here is that an occasion begins with a physical unification of past occasions, which are then prehended, or unified, into a mental experience. This moment of experience then passes away and the occasion becomes “completed,” ready to serve as the physical basis for future occasions. “With ‘Time’,” Ford writes (1995: 28), “panpsychism is clearly affirmed in the sense that every actuality has mentality.”

By the time of his central work, Process and Reality, Whitehead is fully comfortable in referring to all occasions, in Jamesian fashion, as “drops of experience.” “Each actual entity,” he writes, “is a throb of experience including the actual world within its scope.” (1929/1978: 190) Discussing the organic or “social” nature of all actual entities, he comments:

[The] development of mentality is characteristic of the actual occasions which make up the structured societies which we know as “material bodies.” … These material bodies belong to the lowest grade of structured societies which are obvious to our gross apprehensions. They comprise societies of various types of complexity—crystals, rocks, planets, and suns. (101–102)

Physical causality between material bodies is expressed in terms of feelings: “A simple physical feeling is an act of causation. … [A]ll our physical relationships are made up of such simple physical feelings, as their atomic bricks.” (236–237) Later Whitehead adds: “The physical theory of the structural flow of energy has to do with the transmission of simple physical feelings from individual actuality to individual actuality.” (254) And elsewhere in Process and Reality we find further elaboration of the dipolar nature of actual entities (239), and of the notion of value as an expression of the subjectivity of an occasion (240–241, 248). Thus we see a multi-level reconfirmation of panpsychism, with mind and subjectivity present in all events.

Adventures of Ideas (1933) continues Whitehead’s examination of persistence, a subject he had explored in great detail in Process and Reality. If the ultimate reality is the occasion of experience, and if that occasion somehow exists outside the scope of time, how do we account for such durable objects as molecules, human bodies, rocks, planets, and galaxies? Persistent objects are, on Whitehead’s view, collections or “societies” of occasions that somehow share a close family relationship. Societies are thus the only material things that endure. “A society must exhibit the peculiar quality of endurance. The real actual things that endure are all societies. They are not actual occasions.” (1933/1967: 204)

Societies, furthermore, are composed of individuals who are themselves societies. We thus arrive a picture of the world in which things are seen as nested hierarchies of social orders, from lowest to highest: “The Universe achieves its values by reason of its coordination into societies of societies, and in societies of societies of societies.” (206) Certain of these enduring societies—such as human beings—attain a high-grade form. Others—among them cells, atoms, and electrons—achieve only very low-grade forms of mentality. Humans are therefore societies of mental subjects of varying degrees of complexity: “in a man, the living body is permeated by living societies of low-grade occasions so far as mentality is concerned” (208). All enduring things are constructed on the same general plan.

Thus, it is a mistake to posit an absolute distinction between minded and unminded entities on the basis of empirical observation. The distinction is illusory. “Nature suggests for our observation gaps, and then as it were withdraws them upon challenge.” Whitehead makes this point explicitly in the late work Modes of Thought. The chapter “Nature Alive” includes this comment:

[T]his sharp division between mentality and nature has no ground in our fundamental observation. … I conclude that we should conceive mental operations as among the factors which make up the constitution of nature. (1938: 156)

The social or organismic structure of material reality thus accounts for the appearance of things around us, but Whitehead never lets us forget that the experiential occasions themselves are at the foundation of things: “The actualities of the Universe are processes of experience, each process an individual fact. The whole Universe is the advancing assemblage of these processes.” (1933:1967: 197)

A final confirmation of Whitehead’s generally panpsychist or pan-experientialist outlook comes from a late speech, published as “Immortality,” in which he contrasts the universe as a place of great variety and differentiation (“World of Activity”) with the underlying metaphysical unity of things at the level of process (“World of Value”). Things appear to be Many, but philosophically we know that they are ultimately One. Insofar as things are unified, they are all manifestations of occasions of experience, each an expression of intrinsic value. Insofar as things are manifold, they appear to separate into two groupings: the purely physical and the physical/mental. But again, this is a false distinction. “[T]here is no need to postulate two essentially different types of Active Entities, namely, the purely material entities and the entities alive with various modes of experiencing. The latter type is sufficient to account of the characteristics of that World.” (Whitehead 1941: 695) Experience, then, is the ultimate reality of existence.

Whitehead’s process panpsychism has proved exceptionally fruitful. Russell and Hartshorne are among his more notable followers, but many others have found inspiration there. Even today it is one of the most active lines of metaphysical research, and is a direct beneficiary of more analytic defenses of panpsychism such as that offered by Strawson (2009). In one form or another, process thinking has been influential for more than 2,000 years; no doubt it has another millennium or two to go.

7.5 Russell

Whitehead’s student and colleague Bertrand Russell (1872–1970), in the latter part of his career, held to a neutral monist process view in which events were the primary reality, comprising both mind and matter. In that sense he continued the line of thinking of Bergson and Whitehead. Russell’s neutral monism was unique, however, in that he proposed that mind and matter each resulted from a set of causal laws; matter from physical laws of science, mind from “mnemic” laws that were not yet understood.^13 The relationship between these two sets of laws (if there was one) was not clear.

The connection between neutral monism and panpsychism is relevant and illuminating. If, for example, all things are composed of events, then an event is capable of giving rise to mind as well as matter. Therefore, either an event undergoes some kind of bifurcation that steers it in one of two fundamentally different paths, resulting in two fundamentally different modes of existence, or an event retains both a mind-like and a matter-like aspect. The former case presents a difficult ontological problem that Russell attempted to resolve with his two classes of causal laws. The latter is the more logically coherent alternative; this seems to have been the choice of Bergson and Whitehead, and even Russell appears to have endorsed it at times. It is this alternative that urges one toward panpsychism.

Passages suggestive of panpsychism appear early in Russell’s work. One of the first can be found in the 1915 article “The Ultimate Constituents of Matter.” Although the article preceded his neutral monist phase, in it Russell offered up an alternative theory of matter in which sense data compose the ultimate reality of things; this thesis is a clear extension of Mach’s idea that reality consists of sensations. As with Mach, the concept of sense-data seems to imply a psychological or mental aspect to reality, though at the time Russell apparently denied this interpretation.

Into the 1920s, and upon his acceptance of neutral monism, Russell argued that sensations belonged equally to mind and matter. In The Analysis of Mind he wrote: “I should admit this [neutral monist] view as regards sensations: what is heard or seen belongs equally to psychology and to physics. … Sensations are subject to both kinds of [causal] laws, and are therefore truly ‘neutral.’” (1921: 25–26) Sensation, then, is apparently part of the stuff of reality. This is not necessarily panpsychism, or even pansensism. Later in the book, however, Russell puts forth a kind of qualified pansensist position:

We may say generally that an object whether animate or inanimate, is “sensitive” to a certain feature of the environment if it behaves differently according to the presence or absence of that feature. Thus iron is sensitive to anything magnetic. (260)

But he is quick to add that this form of sensitivity doesn’t even constitute knowledge, let alone intelligence. As such, it is a rather trivial form of pansensism—yet one that he apparently held for much of his life. He reiterated it nearly 20 years later: “Perceptive awareness is a species of ‘sensitivity,’ which is not confined to living organisms, but is also displayed by scientific instruments, and to some degree by everything.” (1940/1949: 13)

In The Analysis of Matter (1927a) Russell reveals his process orientation, positing events as the neutral, ultimate elements of reality. He continues to narrow the mind-matter gap, characterizing matter as “less material, and mind less mental, than is commonly supposed” (7). As a consequence, “physics must be interpreted in a way which tends towards idealism, and perception in a way which tends towards materialism.” Both matter and mind are “logical structures” composed of events. Significantly, these events are in themselves to be seen, as in Russell’s earlier works, as sense data or “percepts”: “As to what the events are that compose the physical world, they are, in the first place, percepts, and then [secondarily] whatever can be inferred from percepts.” (386) “Mental events,” he adds, “are part of that stuff [of the world], and … the rest of the stuff resembles them more than it resembles traditional billiard-balls.” (388) He concludes that “from the standpoint of philosophy, the distinction between physical and mental is superficial and unreal” (402). Again, this is highly suggestive but less than definitive.

Russell clearly rejected the mechanistic model of reality, but it is uncertain whether a form of panpsychism was implicated in the reason. He was, however, repeatedly willing to blur the distinction between mind and matter. In An Outline of Philosophy (1927b) he addresses that distinction directly, again in a way suggestive of panpsychism: “My own feeling is that there is not a sharp line, but a difference of degree [between mind and matter]; an oyster is less mental than a man, but not wholly un-mental.” (209) One reason why we cannot draw a line, he says, is that an essential aspect of mind is memory, and a memory of sorts is displayed even by inanimate objects: “[W]e cannot, on this ground [of memory], erect an absolute barrier between mind and matter. … Inanimate matter, to some slight extent, shows analogous behavior.” (306) In the summary at the end of the book, he adds this:

The events that happen in our minds are part of the course of nature, and we do not know that the events which happen elsewhere are of a totally different kind. The physical world … is perhaps less rigidly determined by causal laws than it was thought to be; one might, more or less fancifully, attribute even to the atom a kind of limited free will. (311)

Recalling the ancient Epicurean idea, this modern reference to an atomic free will is based on the newly discovered phenomenon of quantum indeterminacy. Notably, it even finds confirmation in recent physics; see Conway and Kochen 2006, 2009.^14

Perhaps Russell’s clearest articulation of panpsychism came near the end of his writing career, in the 1956 book Portraits from Memory. He asks a simple question: “What is the difference between things that happen to sentient beings and things that happen to lifeless matter?” (152) The common view is that inanimate things undergo many stimuli and reactions, but experience—as a mental property—is not one of them. Recalling his idea from Outline of Philosophy, he notes that the chief characteristic of experience is “the influence of past occurrences on present reactions,” that is, memory. Memory is “the most essential characteristic of mind,” and “using this word [memory] in its broadest sense to include every influence of past experience on present reactions” (153–154). As before, Russell points out that such a notion of memory must apply, properly speaking, to all physical objects and systems. He is explicit:

This [memory] also can be illustrated in a lesser degree by the behavior of inorganic matter. A watercourse which at most times is dry gradually wears a channel down a gully at the times when it flows, and subsequent rains follow [a similar] course. … You may say, if you like, that the river bed “remembers” previous occasions when it experienced cooling streams. … You would say [this] was a flight of fancy because you are of the opinion that rivers and river beds do not “think.” But if thinking consists of certain modifications of behavior owing to former occurrences, then we shall have to say that the river bed thinks, though its thinking is somewhat rudimentary. (155)

This is as clear a statement as can be found in his body of writings. Yet his reticence about fully endorsing such a view is obvious. Later in the book he tends toward agnosticism with respect to any intrinsic mental nature in physical objects, stating that “we cannot say either that the physical world outside our heads is different from the mental world or that it is not” (164).^15

Panpsychist readings of Russell are traditionally rare, though less so in recent years. Hartshorne (1937) thinks he is virtually there. Popper (1977) locates him very close to a Leibnizian panpsychism. Chalmers (1996) has placed him in the panpsychist camp; referring to The Analysis of Matter (without quotation), he writes: “Perhaps, as Russell suggested, at least some of the intrinsic properties of the physical are themselves a variety of phenomenal property [i.e. of sense-data]? The idea sounds wild at first, but on reflection it becomes less so.” (154) And we know the reason it is wild: “There is of course the threat of panpsychism.” Chalmers raises the issue because he is sympathetic to the view, as I explain in a later chapter.

Recently there has been focused interest in so-called Russellian monism, much of which touches on the question of panpsychism in Russell himself. Consciousness in the Physical World, an anthology edited by Alter and Nagasawa and published in 2015, includes numerous references to the topic. Galen Strawson (2015a: 203) notes that Russell is “open to panpsychism,” if not already there. Leopold Stubenberg, on the other hand, argues that “Russell would want to resist his being classified as a panpsychist” (2015: 75) because the neutral elements of his neutral monism are conceivably non-mental. Thus Stubenberg says that, despite the arguments of some recent Russellian monists, it is “inaccurate” to “view Russell as a panpsychist” (82). Certainly Russell was reluctant to fully endorse the view, but on the basis of the passages quoted above it is clear that he was strongly oriented in that direction and deeply sympathetic to it.

7.6 Phenomenology

Phenomenology, as a loosely bound school of philosophical concepts that defies concise definition, is generally centered on the notion of mind and consciousness as a primary aspect of existence. Its development in the work of Edmund Husserl, Martin Heidegger, and Maurice Merleau-Ponty, and the related elaborations by Jean-Paul Sartre and Gabriel Marcel, seem to imply that mentality is a fundamental feature of the world, intimately bound up with any meaningful conception of being. This ontological essentialism has prompted some to suggest a connection with panpsychism. Hartshorne comments as follows—though without supplying clear evidence:

[Heidegger holds] that a cautiously positive form of anthropomorphism [i.e. panpsychism]—that which attributes to other creatures neither the duplication, nor the total absence, but lesser degrees and more primitive forms, of those properties exhibited in high degree, and more refined or complex forms, of those in us—is the only rational initial hypothesis for us to form. (1979: 52)

Abram (1996) also drew inspiration for his neo-animism from the work of Husserl and Merleau-Ponty. He depicts the phenomenological worldview as one in which “the sensible world … is described as active, animate, and, in some curious manner, alive” (55). But the passages Abram cites are obscure and indirect, with no clear correlation to any recognizable form of panpsychism. The statement by Hartshorne quoted above included a footnote reference to two vague passages in Heidegger, but, as with much of Heidegger’s writing, neither is conclusive.

Generally speaking, the obscurity of most phenomenological writing makes it difficult to discern any clear connection to panpsychism. There are, however, certain ideas that, under the appropriate interpretation, are suggestive of it. For example, Heidegger’s Being and Time (1927) attempts an analysis of being through the characteristics of Dasein (literally “being-there”). Dasein is typically taken as pertaining to the human essence, but is amenable to a broader interpretation of being or existence in general. Thus, Heidegger’s conclusions about Dasein logically should pertain to all forms of being. The human “taking-account-of” and the relations such as “for-the-sake-of” and “in-order-to” seem to apply to all entities whatsoever, as Heidegger demonstrates no clear ontological distinction between humans and objects generally. Even simple physical encounters, such as a raindrop’s hitting a leaf, can be seen as episodes of awareness or experience not unrelated to that of humans.

One study of Heidegger that suggests such a view is Graham Harman’s Tool-Being (2002). Harman aims to extend Heidegger’s insights, further than even Heidegger did, to reach their full logical conclusions. Harman sees the key to Heidegger’s whole philosophical system in his analysis of tools. Heidegger related tools to human Dasein, but on Harman’s view “the tool-analysis does not rely in the least on any priority of the human standpoint” (29). Any particular object may serve as a tool, and it stands in some relationship to every other object; using Heidegger’s terminology, we may say that each entity exists “for the sake of” (Um-willen) any other thing that it encounters. In Harman’s words, “the structure known as the ‘for-the-sake-of’ occurs even on the level of soulless matter” (30). If so, the presumed particularity of human consciousness in our everyday encounters is swept away. The network of relationality that we are embedded in, the “as-structure,” is no longer the private domain of the human mind. “The ontological status of sentient awareness has been radically altered: it no longer has the entire as-structure to itself, and therefore has lost its previous ontological distinction.” (225) Harman adds that “the as-structure of the human Dasein turns out to be just a special case of relationality in general. We ourselves are no more and no less perspectival than are rocks, paper, and scissors.”

Yet Harman resists casting this interpretation in a panpsychist light. Discussing an example of a metal stove sitting on a frozen lake, he says: “I see no reason to accept the animistic claim that such a stove … ‘perceives’ the lake in the usual sense.” (223) He makes no explicit claim that his thesis of “pan-relationality” is any variant of panpsychism. Elsewhere he has stated that, even though he is “not inherently opposed” to panpsychism, he wants “to be careful in not jumping from the claim that all objects are involved in relations to the much more far-ranging claim that all relations are psychic relations.”^16 Yet this raises the question of the precise nature of the relationship, if any, between “psychic relations” and relationality in general. And all this, of course, relates to Harman’s own interpretation, not to Heidegger. According to Harman, “there is no real panpsychist tendency in Heidegger.”

Likewise, Merleau-Ponty’s Phenomenology of Perception (1945) appears to articulate a sympathetic relationship between perceiver and perceived wherein each actively apprehends the other. Merleau-Ponty imputes a kind of animate quality to the sensory world: “Hardness, softness, roughness and smoothness … present themselves in our recollection … as certain kinds of symbioses, certain ways the outside has of invading us.” (1945/1962: 317) Elsewhere in the book (211) he describes this process as one of an active world taking possession of the body. But such references are rare, and are subject to various interpretations. Generally speaking, elements of panpsychism in phenomenology are faint at best. In Harman’s opinion, “it’s safe to say that there is no panpsychist strain anywhere in the phenomenological movement.”

7.7 Teilhard de Chardin

There was perhaps no more visionary and exuberant panpsychist than Pierre Teilhard de Chardin (1881–1955). Teilhard—geologist, paleontologist, Jesuit priest, and philosopher—combined elements of Bergson’s evolutionism and its transcendental ethos with a devout if radical interpretation of Christianity to produce a unique and visionary metaphysical system. The core of his thesis was an elaboration of an idea from Schiller and Lossky: the concept of “complexity-consciousness.” This involved the notion that, as matter evolves into increasingly complex forms, so too does the corresponding dimension of consciousness that is attributed to it. Consciousness equals complexity; simple elements of matter possess a low-grade consciousness, and the more complex forms, like the human, possess it in great degrees. In Teilhard’s words (1959: 301): “this particular involution ‘of complexity’ is experimentally bound up with a correlative increase in interiorisation, that is to say in the psyche or consciousness.”

The Phenomenon of Man, Teilhard’s masterpiece, was his first substantial work of philosophy. It was written over the course of several years and completed circa 1938 in the midst of a 20-year stay in China performing paleontological work. The book has many varied dimensions and implications, and panpsychism is only one aspect of Teilhard’s comprehensive vision.

Early in The Phenomenon of Man Teilhard establishes his view that the realm of matter is driven by an evolutionary energy that carries it toward increasingly complex and intricate organization. This universal concept of energy presents itself in varying forms, including its different physical manifestations, but nonetheless is an energy that yields mind: “All energy is psychic in nature.” (1959: 64) Teilhard argues that the evolutionary process results in matter that possesses, at all levels of complexity, an interior that is inherently mental or psychical. Much like Spinoza, he writes that “there is necessarily a double aspect to [matter’s] structure,” and that “co-extensive with their Without, there is a Within to things” (56). The process of evolution, in its most universal sense, is thus one of increasing articulation of mind and consciousness: “We regard evolution as primarily psychical transformation.” (167) The natural result is a panpsychic worldview: “From the cell to the thinking animal, as from the atom to the cell, a single process (a psychical kindling or concentration) goes on without interruption and always in the same direction.” (169) As he reiterates in the postscript,

[W]e are logically forced to assume the existence in rudimentary form … of some sort of psyche in every corpuscle, even in those (the mega-molecules and below) whose complexity is of such a low or modest order as to render it (the psyche) imperceptible. … The universe is, both on the whole and at each of its points, in a continual tension of organic doubling-back upon itself, and thus of interiorization. (301–302)

For Teilhard the becoming of mind is a monumental, universal process of unending progress from dim and unarticulated mentality to ever-greater depth of intensity and interiorization. This is the leitmotif—“noogenesis,” as he calls it—that pervades his works.

In a 1941 essay titled “The Atomism of Spirit,” Teilhard again emphasizes the continuity of psychic evolution in all things, from atoms to Homo sapiens: “[W]e do not immediately recognize in man the natural extension of the atom. Nevertheless … it becomes clear that in each one of us the same movement [of interiorization] is being continued.” (1970: 34) In a 1947 article, “The Place of Technology,” he notes that “interiority, the rudiment of consciousness, exists everywhere; … ‘the within’ is a universal property of things” (1970: 156). Three years later he argued that “matter and Spirit [are] two states or two aspects of one and the same cosmic Stuff,” and that Spirit is on the ascension while Matter is on the decline (1950/1979: 26–27). And in one of his last pieces, “The Reflection of Energy” (1952), Teilhard discusses the universal complexification of energy with respect to the tendency of thermodynamic decay, or entropy. Evolution is driven by “some powerful magnetic force, psychic in nature” (1970: 334), and by this fact it overcomes entropic degradation.

Teilhard thus combined a kind of non-emergence argument with a panpsychist ontology based in first principles. For him, emergence of species and other forms of being was clearly possible, just as new and more complex forms of mind could emerge, but mind as an ontological category was present from the beginning of time. The evolutionary imperative of noogenesis was for him a central cosmological principle, and thus a fundamental metaphysical assumption.

Teilhard’s philosophical legacy has been mixed. For some he has been immensely influential, but in an era dominated by materialistic, analytic, and secular philosophy he has typically been seen as too theological—or, worse, too mystical. Theologians have tended to look skeptically at his fundamental endorsement of evolution and his radical conception of God. In this sense he was very much like his panpsychist contemporary Charles Hartshorne—both men were radical theologian-philosophers who articulated visions too unconventional for either academia or religion.

7.8 Hartshorne and the Problem of the Aggregate

After Whitehead, the preeminent process philosopher of the twentieth century was Charles Hartshorne (1897–2000). A sort of counterculture figure in the world of philosophy, he was, to a significant degree, shunned by mainstream philosophers, both for his failure to embrace the analytic and linguistic tradition and for his open advocacy of panpsychism and theological philosophy. On the other hand, he was seen as too radical by conventional theologians, primarily because of his pantheistic process view of God. Though clearly in the vein of Whitehead’s philosophy, Hartshorne’s writing is in a sense its mirror image—he wrote clearly and elegantly, avoided abstruse technical phases, and was very direct and personal in tone.

Hartshorne was the first philosopher to extensively employ the term ‘panpsychism’ and thus may be credited with bringing the word into something approaching mainstream philosophical discourse. He was open and explicit about his panpsychist beliefs; panpsychism, he claimed, offers the only viable third way between mechanism and vitalism. It also treads a middle ground between “extreme materialism” (eliminativism) and Cartesian dualism. And it allows for a new, more naturalistic vision of God—approaching a form of pantheism. Writing very much like William James, with echoes of Empedocles and Campanella, Hartshorne argued that panpsychism offers a sympathetic view of the world, and in particular a sympathetic epistemology that holds great promise for society.

All these ideas were introduced in one of Hartshorne’s first major works, Beyond Humanism (1937). The entire book is panpsychist in tone, but it is the central theme of two chapters: “Mind and Matter” and “Mind and Body: Organic Sympathy.” The former begins with a critique of science and the scientific method, which, Hartshorne says, treats objects in nature not as individuals but as “crowds,” “swarms,” and “aggregates.” Mind and sentience are not to be found in aggregates but only in true individuals, and thus science overlooks the possibility of panpsychism—interpreted as meaning that all true individuals possess minds. The latter chapter outlines a panpsychist epistemology in which the mind knows the body through “organic sympathy” with sentient cells.

The issue of “aggregates” versus “true individuals” is central to Hartshorne’s interpretation of panpsychism. In fact some philosophers, among them David Ray Griffin, claim that this point is crucial to the entire process view, as it allows Whitehead’s system to avoid potentially debilitating criticisms of standard dual-aspect panpsychism. It furthermore directly addresses a question that is central to virtually all panpsychist theories—the combination problem: How can a unified collective consciousness arise from the mental qualities of lower orders of matter, such as atoms or subatomic particles? This question requires further examination, beginning with a brief historical review.

There is a significant context to this issue of aggregates that the process philosophers have generally neglected, and thus they overlook essential weaknesses in their position. The problem relates to the notion of substance, which began with Democritus’ atomic theory. Since Democritus held that only atoms and the void were real, he was compelled to argue that all ordinary large-scale objects only appeared to be solid substances. A rock, a tree, and a human being were only sophisticated aggregations of imperceptibly small atoms; their unity was real only in the sense that they appeared as singular objects. “The objects of sense are supposed to be real and it is customary to regard them as such, but in truth they are not.”^17 The solidity of ordinary objects is taken strictly “by convention.” Aggregates thus have no true unity; they are not true individuals.

Giordano Bruno read Democritus and embraced his ideas. Yet Bruno also believed in the world-soul and in a universe animated throughout all its parts. He wrote that “all the forms of natural things are souls,” and that all things “possess life, or at least the vital principle” (1584a/1998: 44). As was noted earlier, he believed that so-called inanimate objects, such as a table or items of clothing, are not animate as wholes, but that “as natural things and composites, they have within them matter and form” and thus “part of that spiritual substance.” This spiritual substance or vital principle is a kind of latent soul that becomes fully animate when absorbed into the body of a plant or an animal. Since the vital principle is present in the smallest portions of matter, Bruno concluded that all atoms, or monads, must be in some sense ensouled: “Here is the monad, the atom: and the whole Spirit extending hence upon every side.” (in Singer 1950: 74) All things are made of monads, and therefore all things have, at least, this atomic soul in them. But the object as a whole, if it is “inanimate,” possesses no unified higher-order soul.

Leibniz was also well acquainted with Democritus and cited him often. And he probably was familiar with Bruno’s work, though he doesn’t seem to have mentioned it. Like Democritus, he held that solidity of ordinary matter was only an appearance, an “accidental unity,” a “phenomenon,” something like a rainbow. Leibniz followed Bruno in attributing mental qualities to all monads, but that left him with some daunting problems. First, he had to explain why such things as rocks and tables, though composed of sentient monads, were not in themselves somehow animate. Bruno simply made a flat assertion that this was so, but offered no real argument. Leibniz had some ideas on how to solve that problem. A second and related problem, which Democritus and Bruno completely bypassed, was an accounting of the human soul, or mind: How could a single, large-scale, unified mind arise from monadic souls? That is, how can we account for the combination problem?

To his credit, Leibniz attempted to address both problems directly, arguing that objects were collections of monads and that some of these objects—those, such as animals and plants, with “a thoroughly indivisible and naturally indestructible being” (1686b/1989: 79)—possessed a unifying and dominant monad. This served as the soul or mind of the individual. Such individuals were considered both “living beings” and “composite substances.” The other, non-dominant monads composed the body of the living being, and were linked to the dominant monad either by pre-established harmony or, in Leibniz’ later theory, by the vinculum substantiale.

Yet it must be admitted that Leibniz never gave any explanation of how the dominant monad came to be, or why it appeared only in animals. His discussion of borderline cases is informative. Only once does he directly address the issue of larger-scale objects: “[I]f I am asked in particular what I say about the sun, the earthly globe, the moon, trees, and other similar bodies and even about beasts. I cannot be absolutely certain whether they are animated, or even whether they are substances.” (1686b/1989: 80) His uncertainty about trees, and presumably all plants, apparently subsided soon thereafter; by 1687 he clearly included plants among the sentient. “I do not dare assert” he wrote, “that plants have no soul, life, or substantial form.” (1687/1989: 82) Later he added this:

[I]t seems probable that animals, which are indeed analogous to us, and similarly plants, which correspond to animals in many ways, are not composed of body alone, but also of soul, by which the animal or plant, the single indivisible substance … is controlled. (1690/1989: 104)

Near the end of his life, Leibniz observed that “the limbs of [each] living body are full of other living beings, plants, animals, each of which also has its entelechy, or its dominant monad” (Monadology, section 70). The issue of plants is relevant because Hartshorne, ignoring Leibniz and dubiously citing Whitehead, pointedly excludes them from the ranks of the animate.

Two hundred years later, Whitehead developed his theory of the organism as the model for reality, apparently employing some of Leibniz’s ideas. But, like his predecessor, he had an ambiguous conception of the aggregate. Whitehead was faced with the same issue as the monadists: how to account for combination and unity of the human mind. In his system, point-like occasions of experience with both physical and mental poles were likened to “monads with windows”—that is, they were considered capable of interaction. But Whitehead did not say clearly how they were unified, or in what types of beings.

In Whitehead’s last four major philosophical books—Science and the Modern World (1925), Process and Reality (1929), Adventures of Ideas (1933), and Modes of Thought (1938)—there is virtually no discussion of Leibniz’s notion of aggregates. Leibniz’s dominant monad theory is largely ignored, except for a few passing mentions in Process and Reality. This is rather surprising, especially in light of the generally high regard Whitehead seems to have had for Leibniz. Furthermore, the discussion of aggregates—or, as Whitehead prefers, societies—is sporadic and obtuse throughout. Science and Adventures make almost no mention of the topic. Process and Reality, by contrast, contains a lengthy discussion of the nature of a society. The one consistent theme is that all objects, from atoms to stones to humans, are in reality “societies of [point-like] actual occasions,” much as Leibniz saw things as aggregates of point-like monads. However, Whitehead offers nearly a dozen different categories of society, including “electromagnetic,” “corpuscular,” “structured,” “specialized,” “stabilized,” “living,” and “subordinate.” It is never clear which of those categories possess unified sentience and which do not.

A number of passages in Process and Reality are vague and conflicting. First, the critical passage on “the ultimate metaphysical principle”—the “advance from disjunction to conjunction,” or, more succinct, “the many become one, and are increased by one” (1929/1978: 21)—seems to apply to any aggregate of occasions. Whitehead bears the burden of explaining why, though an ultimate principle, this advance to unity doesn’t occur in all things.

Second, “structured societies” are those that have both “dominant” and “subordinate” sub-societies. The overall structure provides a protected environment that sustains the sub-societies. “Molecules are structured societies, and so in all probability are separate electrons and protons. Crystals are structured societies. But gases are not.” (99) Elsewhere Whitehead includes “crystals, rocks, planets and sun” (102) in this list. Structured societies have two ways of creating a protective environment. The first is by “massive average objectification of a nexus,” which would appear to apply to stones and such. However, “this mode of solution requires the intervention of mentality”; further, “this development of mentality is characteristic of the actual occasions which make up the structured societies we know as ‘material bodies’” (101). Whitehead adds that “such mentality represents the first grade of ascent,” possessing “some initiative of conceptual integration, but no originality in conceptual prehension.” Apparently, then, there is a latent mentality in even the simplest structured society. The second way is “appetition,” i.e., the ability to “originate novelty to match the novelty of the environment” (102). This ability ranges from “thinking” (in higher organisms) to “thoughtless adjustment of aesthetic emphasis” (in lower ones). Societies that act in this second way are deemed living or organic, the others inorganic. However, “there is no absolute gap between ‘living’ and ‘non-living’ societies.” Thus, they seem to exist on a continuum of mentality—again, implying mentality in all.

Third, the standard view of post-Whitehead process philosophers is that atoms, molecules, and individual cells are included among the sentient. On the one hand, the above point suggests this. On the other, Whitehead explicitly notes that “a cell gives no evidence whatsoever of a single unified mentality” (104). Later he goes further: “In the case of single cells, of vegetation, and of the lower forms of animal life, we have no ground for conjecturing living personality.” (107)

Fourth, and by contrast, Whitehead suggests elsewhere that all aggregates can be seen as individuals in their own right:

[T]here is the … potential aggregation of actual entities into a super-actuality in respect to which the true actualities play the part of coordinate subdivisions. In other words, just as … one atomic actuality can be treated as though it were many coordinate actualities, in the same way … a nexus of many actualities can be treated as though it were one actuality. This is what we habitually do in the case of the span of life of a molecule, or of a piece of rock, or of a human body. (286–287)

Such is the case as presented in Process and Reality. One would have hoped for a clearer and more decisive account of this central issue.

In Modes of Thought we find other passages that conflict with the standard view. Whitehead initially informs us that “a vegetable is a democracy; an animal is dominated by one, or more centers of experience” (1938: 24). Unfortunately, he adds that “our statement is oversimplified” because “the distinction between animals and vegetables is not sharp cut. Some traces of dominance can be observed in vegetables, and some traces of democratic independence can be found in animals.”

Whitehead continues by articulating four types of aggregations: the “lowest” or “nonliving,” which is “dominated by the average”—though even here he allows that “flashes of selection” are possible, if only “sporadic and ineffective” (27); “vegetable grade,” which “has added coordinated, organic individuality to the impersonal average of inorganic nature”; “animal grade,” with “at least one central actuality”; and “human grade,” with “novelty of functioning.” He reiterates a similar sequence at the end of the book, again emphasizing “the aspect of continuity between these modes” (157). The conclusion would seem to be either that Whitehead was trying to articulate a tremendously complex theory of the aggregate or that he in fact saw some degree of mentality in all things as wholes, and not simply in the mental poles of their constituent occasions.

Reading Whitehead in light of Leibniz’s monadology, Hartshorne claims that only things with a deep organic unity qualify as true or “genuine” individuals.^18 In the absence of a clear theoretic structure, Hartshorne concludes that precisely which objects qualify is not definable a priori, but is rather a function of empirical study.^19 Generally speaking, true individuals exhibit some—if even only a slight—degree of spontaneity and unpredictability, which is indicative of a unifying, dominant force. Aggregates, on the other hand, behave very predictably and mechanistically. They display absolutely no degree of unified action. Any inherent dynamics, such as those of the constituent atoms, are averaged out by the aggregate, leaving no net force to serve as a unified individual.

Based on his rough empirical assessment, and drawing from certain passages in Whitehead, Hartshorne determines that not only humans but all animals clearly display spontaneous unified behavior, even down to the level of one-celled creatures. At the level of the micro-constituents of matter, he includes molecules, atoms, and sub-atomic particles; their unpredictability and their spontaneity had been confirmed by then-recent advances in quantum theory and by the probabilistic behavior of such particles.

At the higher end of the scale, Hartshorne jumps directly from humanity to the universe as a whole, including it among the ranks of animate beings. He explicitly excludes virtually everything else, including inorganic objects such as rocks, tables, and houses. Also excluded are all higher-order systems—e.g., a forest, a social group, or the Earth as a whole—even though these contain sentient parts. Even individual plants are excluded; apparently basing his view on Whitehead’s “vegetables are a democracy” statement, Hartshorne sees plants as mere colonies of sentient cells rather than as truly integrated individuals. Hence, all aggregates, even though composed of sentient atoms, molecules, and perhaps cells, are not in themselves sentient. Only the genuine individuals, as determined empirically, are unified animate beings.

In this sense, process philosophy effectively advocates a dualistic theory of mind. Objects and structures classified as true individuals possess mind and have experiences; all others do not. Experience or sentience is posited as a fundamental, ontological characteristic of reality, and thus there exists a clear divide between the experiencers and the non-experiencers. Griffin (1998: 169–198) and some other recent writers attempt to downplay this distinction, characterizing it as upholding a form of monism because the aggregates are not “true beings.” But the distinction is there nonetheless. There is no clear ontological separation between the mere aggregates and true individuals. This point is important because, as Griffin notes, it is presented as the way out of a number of critical attacks against process panpsychism.

Like Leibniz and Whitehead, Hartshorne doesn’t offer much in the way of argumentation for his particular list of animate things. The reliance on empiricism is a matter of epistemological concern, but it says nothing about the theoretical and ontological basis for such a divide. Why should it be that only certain aggregates are blessed with mind and experience, while others are not? And what is the ontological basis by which a dominant or “regnant” monad takes control and serves as the mind? Are these to be taken as unfathomable mysteries? Are they simply brute facts of reality? One is led to suspect that process theory is significantly incomplete on this matter.

Ultimately this dichotomy between true individuals and aggregates seems entirely too arbitrary. If one postulates a fundamental distinction in nature, then one ought to have a compelling reason for doing so.^20 Both a rock and an animal are aggregates of sentient atoms, yet one is seen as sentient in its own right and the other is not—what is the difference? Of course they differ in many ways—internal complexity, dynamic relation to the environment, etc.—but they are alike in their constitution as aggregates. A living aggregate is clearly different from a non-living aggregate, but not in its aggregateness. The process view argues not merely that they are different in degree, but that they are ontologically different, different in kind; the true individuals are said to possess something real and fundamental that the others do not have. Even a priori, it seems that any two coherent and persistent structures of mass-energy should share certain core characteristics, and that (unless one is prepared to argue for eliminativism) mind is among them—which is essentially Schopenhauer’s argument.

Apart from the problem of aggregates, Hartshorne tackles the issue of “proving” panpsychism. Rather than attempting to do so directly, he adopts Paulsen’s tactic and turns the question around. First he asks whether science, which is in the business of proofs, can disprove panpsychism. He answers No, both because it treats things primarily in aggregate form and also because it cannot distinguish the fact that an object feels from how it feels. He goes on to explain that philosophical reasoning offers no inherent basis for rejecting panpsychism. On the contrary, there are “great philosophical advantages” (1937: 175) to panpsychism, including explaining the relation between sensation and feeling, and a deeper comprehension of the concepts of space and time. Relying on a Bergsonian argument for memory in all aspects of reality, he states that “the idea of time is unintelligible unless panpsychism is true” (174).

Hartshorne then argues that panpsychism has been damaged by its association with idealism. In the early 1930s, as the views of Kant and Berkeley were being discredited by the rising positivist philosophy, panpsychism too was disparaged. Moore and Perry were among the leading critics. Yet it should be clear, Hartshorne says, that panpsychism, while conceivably a form of idealism, is substantially different from a Berkelian or a Kantian position. Hartshorne associates it with the so-called idealism of Leibniz and Whitehead, which is almost a realist or even objectivist view.^21 The “absurdity of [traditional] idealism,” he says, “has no bearing upon panpsychism” (177).

Hartshorne proceeds to claim that organic sympathy, and its accompanying panpsychism, is capable of resolving six major philosophical problems: mind-body, subject-object, causality, the nature of time, the nature of individuality, and the problem of knowledge. In short, the human mind results from a “sympathetic participation” or “sympathetic rapport” with the sentient cells of the body, whose sentience is itself a product of the rapport with the sentient atoms. The relation of subject to object is, similarly an exchange between enminded participants, without which knowledge would be impossible. More generally, all causality is manifested through such a resonance between two minds. Moments in time are a “sympathetic bond” between past and future, much as Bergson and Whitehead described. The “individual” is a result of a balance between the integrative power of sympathy and the disintegrative power of its opposite, antipathy; in the manner of Empedocles, Hartshorne asserts that pure sympathy would destroy individuality (by merging all into one), and that pure antipathy would not allow for any structure or knowledge at all.^22

These ideas, and especially the emphasis on panpsychism, recurred frequently throughout Hartshorne’s long career. They appeared in one of his discussions of freedom and free will,^23 and they were featured in his entry on panpsychism in A History of Philosophical Systems (1950: 442–453)—a woefully incomplete survey of the field, incidentally. Then, in the late 1970s, he published some important articles directly arguing for panpsychism. The most notable of these was “Physics and Psychics: The Place of Mind in Nature” (1977), in which he again presents panpsychism—now preferring to call it “psychical monism” or “psychicalism”—as a third way between dualism and materialism: “Psychical monism avoids the most obvious demerits of its two rivals. It is a monism, yet it is not a materialism.” (1977: 90) He offers a straightforward case for panpsychism, beginning with four reasons why inanimate objects appear devoid of mind: apparent inactivity or inertness, lack of freedom and initiative, absence of a clear distinction between parts and the whole, and lack of purpose. He disposes of these four by recalling the distinction between aggregates and true individuals. Rocks and chairs are, he says, not sentient individuals but only aggregates of sentient atoms and molecules. Matter is not inert but is continuously active and dynamic at the atomic level. Quantum indeterminacy is a kind of freedom. And “purpose” probably is reflected over varying lengths of time, which may be exceedingly short or exceptionally long; it would require superhuman abilities to grasp the full range of temporality and to declare definitively that purpose was nonexistent.

On the positive side of the argument, Hartshorne asks “What are the advantages of giving up the notion of mere dead, mindless physical things?” He concedes that the advantages are mostly theoretical, but he argues that giving them up “enable[s] us to arrive at a view of life and nature in which the results of science are given their significance along with the values with which art, ethics, and religion are concerned” (92). In other words, spiritual and reverential values are strengthened by such a worldview. More specifically, Hartshorne cites some strictly philosophical advantages: (1) The problem of how matter produces mind is dissolved. (2) It supports the intuitive view that organic and inorganic substances lie along one continuum of existence. (3) The problem of causality is resolved by taking account of memory and perception or anticipation. (4) It provides the most satisfactory solution to the mind-body issue, describing it as “a relation of sympathy.” (5) It solves the old problem of primary and secondary qualities by ascribing secondary or subjective qualities to all things. (6) It provides for an account of behavior of all things in psychical terms, relating to perception, emotion, memory, and so on.

In the final analysis, Hartshorne concludes that panpsychism or psychicalism has little direct bearing on matters of science per se but does profoundly influence our human attitudes, and consequently our actions. “For logical, aesthetic, and religious reasons our view of the general [panpsychic] cosmic status of quality (and value) influences our behavior, and in this sense its consideration is pragmatically significant.” (1990: 397) It is, after all, the most viable ontology available to us—certainly preferable to an utterly unintelligible materialism: “[T]he concept of ‘mere dead insentient matter’ is an appeal to invincible ignorance. At no time will this expression ever constitute knowledge.” (1977: 95)

Notes

1. James 1920, volume 2: 198.

2. He considers the latter “absolutely conclusive.”

3. For example, Montague defines consciousness under this theory as “the potential … presence of a thing at a space or time in which that thing is not actually present.”

4. For another perspective, see Bjelland 1981.

5. Skolimowski’s idea of “evolutionary God” as an endpoint of universal evolution is notable. See his 1993 work A Sacred Place to Dwell.

6. For a good discussion of this concept that “mind-object relations have analogues at each level of finite existence,” see Brettschneider 1964.

7. Lossky 1901.

8. Lossky, cited in Starchenko 1994 (p. 656).

9. It was this idea that observation (more generally “experience” or “sentience”) was implicated in any valid concept of reality that John Wheeler later developed into his notion of the participatory universe.

10. Rorty’s bias against panpsychism comes out loud and clear. He calls “futile” any attempt to “invoke panpsychism in order to bridge the gap between experience and nature” (6). He sees the only valid approach as contrasting experience, consciousness, or mind with nature, not in seeking to understand their connection and overlap. This is a typical objectivist, positivist approach. He claims that Dewey “dodg[ed] hard epistemological questions” in viewing nature as continuous with experience. Rorty’s answer is to create a break in continuity “between non-language-users (amoebae, squirrels, babies) and language users,” assigning mind and cognition only to the latter. But this approach has at least three major problems. First, what is the definition of ‘language’? Certainly any form of information exchange could constitute a kind of language. Second, at what point do babies acquire mind? Does mind gradually come into existence, or does it leap into being at some initial utterance? Either answer is fraught with difficulties. Third, one cannot help but feel that this distinction based on language is an even more arbitrary and indefensible break, a dodging of hard ontological problems. The most definitive evidence of Rorty’s stance occurs in a footnote to the article cited above: “All I have to say about [panpsychism] is contained in ‘The Subjectivist Principle and the Linguistic Turn’” (211). The 1963 article doesn’t contain a single mention of the term ‘panpsychism’ or even any discernible reference to the concept.

11. See chapter 6 of Berman 1981.

12. Reproduced in Ford 1984. Citations are of that work.

13. See Russell 1921: 25.

14. Recall the discussion on Epicurus in chapter 2 above.

15. Hartshorne (1937: 222) makes the same observation: “only sheer agnosticism separates Russell from panpsychism.”

16. Personal communication, January 2003.

17. Fragment 9 (Smith 1934: 40).

18. Elsewhere Hartshorne called Leibniz’s position “the first clear statement of panpsychist theory” (1950: 444), apparently overlooking all the developments after the early Greeks—most notably, Renaissance naturalism.

19. Interestingly, Plato flatly disagreed with this view. For him, the only way to determine anything about the psyche in apparently inanimate objects was via rational reflection. Recall the passage cited earlier, reflecting on the soul of the sun: “Everyone can see [the sun’s] body, but no one can see its soul—not that you could see the soul of any other creature, living or dying. [Such a thing] is totally below the level of our bodily senses, and is perceptible by reason alone.” (Laws, 898d)

20. Griffin believes he has a compelling reason, in that the dominant monad preserves the freedom of action of the individual (1998: 97). The dominant monad both acts on and is acted upon by the body. On the process view, this two-way causality is the basis of freedom. There are at least two problems with this: (1) It assumes a fairly conventional view of freedom of the will, when in fact there are other ways to conceive this, apart from determinism. (2) Nothing Griffin says rules out the possibility that all things have a dominant monad. Simply because we see no apparent spontaneity in rocks doesn’t mean it isn’t there at some low level, or on some long time scale. This issue is discussed further below.

21. Hartshorne was not entirely enamored of Leibniz’s philosophy. He criticized his notorious mechanistic stance, and was fundamentally opposed to the mechanistic worldview in general: “mechanism and materialism are really two aspects of the same view—the view that the world is fundamentally dead, blind, uncreative, insentient” (1937: 180).

22. See Hartshorne 1937: 194–199.

23. Hartshorne 1949.

8 Scientific Perspectives

From a scientific perspective, the human mind is an unexplained and perhaps unexplainable mystery. Mind that may exist elsewhere in nature is scientifically unintelligible and methodologically superfluous. Modern analytic philosophy generally concurs with the scientific outlook that nonhuman minds are incomprehensible or irrelevant. It furthermore accepts uncritically the scientific view that matter is intrinsically non-experiential. Both science and modern philosophy, therefore, generally find no credibility in panpsychist theories.

As I stated early in this book, virtually all present-day naturalistic theories of mind are forms of emergentism, arguing that mind is a rare and unique phenomenon that arises only in highly specialized circumstances. The standard versions of emergentism—including the identity theory, functionalism, and various forms of behaviorism—attribute mind to only those structures that have achieved sufficient biological or functional complexity.^1 They are, however, generally at a loss to explain either the criterion for this emergence or how the qualities of mind or consciousness are linked to such complexity. Emergentism, in all its forms, is thus profoundly incomplete at present. This fact alone suggests that panpsychist theories deserve greater attention.

8.1 Historical Arguments from the Scientific and Empirical Perspectives

The failings of emergentism constitute what might be called a negative argument on behalf of panpsychism. Yet there are many positive arguments, some from within the realm of science. Numerous scientist-philosophers (including Gilbert, Kepler, Leibniz, LaMettrie, Herder, Fechner, Haeckel, Mach, and Teilhard) found grounds for panpsychism in the fields of physics, chemistry, and biology. Their arguments were based not only on rationalism but also on empirical evidence and evolutionary principles. It is helpful to briefly retrace some of these older scientific arguments in order to set the context for the more recent developments.

Scientific arguments are traditionally based on a combination of empirical evidence and so-called scientific reasoning. Given a conjecture or proposed theory, evidence is sought that can confirm it. This raises two questions long known to philosophers of science: What counts as evidence? What qualifies as scientific reasoning? It is clear that any observed data about the world can be interpreted in many ways and may count for or against widely divergent theories. Scientific reasoning is roughly defined as a logical and empirically based process that leads to positive theories about some aspect of reality, and ideally to the truth about the world. Applying similar reasoning to issues of philosophy of mind has led some thinkers to panpsychist conclusions.

Consider Thales’ evidence: that a magnet has a psyche because it can move metallic objects. He held to a theory of mind in which psyche was the source and cause of motion. On that definition, it is clear that a magnet must be ensouled. It was, then, a rational process that led Thales to consider whether psyche was shared only by humans, animals, and certain rocks (such as those from Magnesia) or was a universal property that was manifest in all objects by degrees.^2 We don’t fully know Thales’ rationale, but we know that he ultimately concluded that “all things are full of gods” and thus that panpsychism was true.

Anaximenes noted the commonly observed fact that living, ensouled beings must breathe, and that loss of breath was a fairly certain indication of loss of psyche. Furthermore, breath, in the form of air (pneuma), seemed to surround and permeate all things. Thus, a reasonable “scientific” conclusion was that psyche was present everywhere, in all things.

Plato saw psyche as the principal source of motion and, like Thales, held that where there was evident power of motion the presence of a soul had to be inferred. He observed the regular motions of the heavens and concluded that only a world-soul could regulate such motions with orderly precision. As to the psyche itself, Plato stated the obvious: that it cannot be directly observed and is thus “perceptible by reason alone”—that is, on the basis of ultimate metaphysical principles.

Aristotle was confronted with the puzzling phenomenon of spontaneous generation of life out of heaps of decaying matter. To make sense of such generation, he was compelled to postulate a soul-like pneuma as pervasive in the physical world. Pneuma, as the earthly life-principle, was the analogue of the heavenly ether, which was thought to animate the stars and other celestial bodies. Only the ether could account for the appearance of life from a non-living substrate. Aristotle was wrong about spontaneous generation, but his methodology was logical and plausibly scientific.

Centuries later, Gilbert’s study of magnets in the late 1500s considered two different empirical results. The first was his observation that a magnet can magnetize a previously nonmagnetic piece of metal. For him, this “power to confer power” was evidence of a magnet’s psyche-like ability. Second, Gilbert documented the consistency and orderliness of the magnetic force: the repulsion of like poles, the attraction of opposite poles, inverse-square action with respect to distance, and so on. He saw this as evidence of “reason” in the magnet—a disputable but putatively scientific conclusion if one assumes that the psyche acts in an intelligent and orderly manner, much as Plato had assumed. The jump to panpsychism required additional presumptions, such as “whatever is in the effect is in the cause.” Gilbert showed that the Earth was a large magnet, then rightly determined that magnetism was thereby bestowed on individual rocks. Since the Earth granted its magnetic psyche to the magnet, and (evidently) the animal psyche to humans and animals, it was reasonable to generalize that all Earthly things were endowed with a kind of animation.

Like Plato and Gilbert, Kepler saw soul as the motive force behind the planets—at least until 1621, when he decided that the rational orderliness of planetary motion was indicative of a corporeal, non-psychic force. Newton viewed gravity as an occult quality, something perhaps lifelike in nature. As I noted earlier, his theory of universal attraction had implicit panpsychist overtones. He understood that gravity could be quantified, but this did not explain its basis or its origin.

In the mid to late 1600s, various new scientific technologies began to emerge, some of which supported panpsychist theories. Leeuwenhoek’s work with the microscope revealed tiny “animalcules” in ordinary water—a startling discovery that impressed a number of thinkers, including Spinoza, Leibniz, and LaMettrie. Suddenly there was indisputable empirical proof of life and sentience in the smallest portions of nature. Later discoveries of the cellular nature of plants and animals, and of the ubiquitous presence of microorganisms, only furthered this belief.

Fechner’s work in the mid 1800s relied less on empirical data than on a scientific form of argumentation by analogy. He observed the functional similarities between animals and plants, and concluded that plants were animate. He then considered the Earth as a system, arguing that its internal dynamics and sentient components supported such notions as an Earth-soul. Empirical evidence of the Earth’s ability to self-regulate did not appear until about 100 years later, with the work of Wright and Lovelock.

Advances in physics in the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries moved toward unification of physical forces. More important, with the dynamist and energeticist theories, even matter itself was seen as an ethereal, quasi-spiritual entity. This “spiritualization” of matter—in a scientific context—was important to the panpsychist theories of Priestley, Schelling, Herder, Lossky, and the early Schiller.

Darwin’s theory of evolution (1859) initiated a series of new scientific arguments. Even before On the Origin of Species, the early anticipations of Maupertuis, LaMettrie, and Diderot suggested that an evolutionary perspective would entail some form of panpsychism. After Darwin, it became evident that all life shared a common ancestry, and that conscious humans had no claim to ontological uniqueness. This was further supported by chemical analyses that showed human bodies to be composed of the same elements that existed in other life forms, in the Earth, and even throughout space. These scientific facts supported the Continuity arguments of Haeckel, Spencer, James, Teilhard, and others. Evolution was not empirical per se, but empirical evidence supported it and indirectly served as a form of confirmation for certain panpsychist theories.

8.2 Panpsychism in Twentieth-Century Science

Into the twentieth century, further developments in physics, biology, and mathematics were presented as scientific evidence in favor of panpsychist claims. The equation of mass and energy furthered the notion that the underlying nature of matter was something vaguely spirit-like. Quantum mechanics emerged as an accepted theory of atomic and subatomic particles; its bizarre, indeterminate implications led a number of scientists to panpsychist conclusions, beginning with John Haldane in 1932 and continuing with Jeans, Sherrington, Wright, Rensch, Walker, Cochran, Dyson, Bohm, and Hameroff. More recently, concepts in mathematical analysis, especially cybernetics, state-space analysis, and chaos theory, have been employed on behalf of panpsychism.

To many scientists of the early twentieth century, panpsychism was uncomfortably close to the recently discredited theory of vitalism. As a result, they largely avoided discussing it. But there were exceptions. The first notable scientist to tentatively put forth panpsychist views was the British astronomer Arthur Eddington, who concludes his book Space, Time and Gravitation (1920) with the observation that physics only addresses the surface structure of matter and energy and doesn’t have anything to say about the inner content of reality. Arguing roughly in the manner of Schopenhauer, Eddington claims that the inner content of reality must be like the inner content of the human, i.e., consciousness:

In regard to the nature of things, this knowledge [of relativity] is only an empty shell—a form of symbols. It is knowledge of structural form and not knowledge of content. All through the physical world runs that unknown content, which must surely be the stuff of our consciousness. Here is a hint of aspects deep within the world of physics, and yet unattainable by the methods of physics. (200)

This somewhat vague passage can be read either as a form of pure idealism or, in the manner of Schopenhauer, as a panpsychic idealism.^3

Eddington’s 1928 book The Nature of the Physical World contains a section titled “Mind-Stuff” in which Eddington, explicitly acknowledging the views of Clifford, bluntly states:

The universe is of the nature of a thought or sensation in a universal Mind … . To put the conclusion crudely—the stuff of the world is mind-stuff. … The mind-stuff of the world is something more general than our individual conscious minds; but we may think of its nature as not altogether foreign to feelings in our consciousness … . (276)

Again we are lacking in details, but the statement seems to support a panpsychist form of idealism.

Eddington’s quasi-panpsychism appeared for a third time in 1939, leaning more toward conventional idealism and arguing that physics “abolishes all dualism of consciousness and matter” (150). Dualism, he claimed, contains a logical inconsistency: “Dualism depends on the belief that we find in the external world something of a nature incommensurable with what we find in consciousness.” Since physics shows that all reality is structurally the same, it must all be commensurate with consciousness—that is, it must be of the nature of a mental sensation:

Although the statement that the universe is of the nature of “a thought or sensation in a universal Mind” is open to criticism, it does at least avoid this logical confusion. It is, I think, true in the sense that it is a logical consequence of the form of thought which formulates our knowledge as a description of the universe. (151)

Eddington’s reference to a universal Mind is somewhat Berkelian—matter as consciousness only with respect to an observing mind, not as a mind in itself. His argumentation comes across as a bit confused, but his intention seems to be to argue that the unified view of physics supports a belief that the content of mental reality is comparable and even equivalent to the content of mind.

The biologist John (J. B. S.) Haldane speculated on mind in nature in the early 1930s, and he addressed the thorny problem of the emergence of life and mind from inanimate matter: “It is clear that aggregates of a certain kind do manifest qualities which we cannot observe in their components.” (1932: 113) This is an important and subtle observation; Haldane doesn’t say that emergent qualities do not exist in their components, but rather that we cannot see them there. The problem is epistemological, not ontological. In fact, if consciousness were not present in matter, that would imply a theory of strong emergence that is fundamentally anti-scientific. Such emergence is “radically opposed to the spirit of science, which has always attempted to explain the complex in terms of the simple.” Haldane rejected this thesis, and hence was driven to the conclusion that life and mind exist to some degree everywhere:

We do not find obvious evidence of life or mind in so-called inert matter, and we naturally study them most easily where they are most completely manifested; but if the scientific point of view is correct, we shall ultimately find them, at least in rudimentary form, all through the universe. (113)

Two years later Haldane offered thoughts on the philosophical implications of quantum mechanics. In “Quantum Mechanics as a Basis for Philosophy” (1934) he proposes that mind is a “resonance phenomenon” that is associated with the wave-like aspect of atomic particles. This is a reasonable assertion, he claims, because the characteristics of mind are comparable to those of atomic particles: Both arise from dynamical systems, both exhibit a continuity and wholeness, both are at once localized yet spatially diffused. For example, the wave nature of an electron allows it to penetrate through an insulating barrier; this is the so-called tunneling effect. Haldane interprets this as a primitive variety of “purposive behavior.” He offers the suggestion that “man also has a ‘wave system’ which enables him to act with reference to distant or future events, this system being his mind” (89). Anywhere this resonance phenomenon occurs, there we must accept the presence of mind. He speculates that this may happen even inside stars:

It is not inconceivable that in such [stellar] systems resonance phenomena of the complexity of life and mind might occur. … It is conceivable that the interior of stars may shelter minds vastly superior to our own, though presumably incapable of communication with us. (97)

Haldane had previously cited Plato, and one cannot help but suspect that he had Plato’s “star-souls” in mind.^4

The physicist and astronomer Sir James Jeans was likewise drawn to philosophical speculations on mind. Like Eddington, he saw evidence for mind as present throughout nature, concluding that a form of idealism must be true: “the universe can be best pictured … as consisting of pure thought” (1932: 168). Jeans was clear that this conception undermines the mechanistic worldview: “[T]he universe begins to look more like a great thought than like a great machine. Mind no longer appears as an accidental intruder into the realm of matter.” (186) In a later work he arrived at a strongly Berkelian idealism (or “mentalism”), arguing that the new physics provides three substantial reasons for seeing reality as “wholly mental”: (1) Electromagnetic fields fail to qualify as objective, and hence are effectively “not real at all; they are mere mental constructs of our own” (1942: 200). (2) The reality of the theories of physics is essentially mathematical, and therefore essentially mental. (3) As Haldane suggested, the wave-particle duality implies a view in which “the ingredients of the particle-picture are material, those of the wave-picture mental. … The final picture consists wholly of waves, and its ingredients are wholly mental constructs.” (202) Jeans’ philosophical reasoning thus pushed him toward a strong idealism, one that would seem compatible with a form of panpsychism.

In the early 1940s three notable British biologists ventured theories with panpsychist dispositions. Sir Charles Scott Sherrington was known for his research on the physiology of the brain, but in Man on His Nature (1941) he delved into mind-brain philosophy. Sherrington argued, much like Bruno, for a dual-aspect theory of reality, one consisting of mind and energy: “[O]ur world resolves itself into energy and mind. These two concepts … divide, and between them comprise, our world.” (348) He was agnostic about interaction between these two realms, stating that we are left with

acceptance of energy and mind as a working biological unity although we cannot describe the how of that unity. … The evolution of one is of necessity the evolution of the other. There is no causal relation between them; they are both inseparably one. Their correlation is unity. (351–352).

One consequence of this view is that the animate blends seamlessly into the inanimate: “We have difficulty in assigning the lower limit of the mental. It may therefore be that its distribution extends to all organisms, and even further.” (354) In other words, “it is as though the elementary mental had never been wanting” (266)—that is, present in all matter throughout the history of evolution.

The second of the three men was Wilfred Agar. A follower of Whitehead’s process philosophy, Agar was attracted to Whitehead’s concept of the “philosophy of the organism,” and he sought a biological theory of the living organism that would correspond to Whitehead’s philosophy. Agar’s central thesis was that organisms are both percipient subjects and composed of elements—cells—that are themselves percipient; living cells “must also be regarded as feeling, perceiving, subjects” (1943: 8). The logic continues down the chain of being: “A cell, though a subject, must probably also be considered a nexus of living sub-agents.” (11)^5

Agar asserted that “Whitehead’s system essentially involves a form of panpsychism” (66), and his analysis demonstrated a deeper philosophical awareness than the other scientists discussed. He accepted most aspects of Whitehead’s process philosophy but disagreed on the nature of consciousness. Whitehead saw consciousness as a special and limited case of the more general phenomenon of feeling or experiencing, whereas Agar believed that

the more satisfying hypothesis is that … all experience is in its degree conscious. … We must ascribe consciousness to every living agent, such as a plant cell or bacterium, and even (if the continuity of nature is not to be broken) to an electron. (91)

Agar’s panpsychism is thus more literal and more far-reaching than Whitehead’s, adopting a universalized conception of consciousness.

The third of the biologists was Sir Julian Huxley. Arguing, like the others, that physics and evolution have demonstrated the underlying unity of nature, Huxley embraced a strongly monist perspective that established a deep link between mind and matter. He then adopted a dual-aspect Spinozist ontology: “there exists one world stuff, which reveals material or mental properties according to the point of view” (1942: 140). The material was reality “from the outside”; the mental was “from within.” If we accept the continuity of mind and matter that science imposes,

then mind or something of the nature as mind must exist throughout the entire universe. This is, I believe, the truth. We may never be able to prove it, but it is the most economical hypothesis: it fits the facts much more simply … than one-sided idealism or one-sided materialism.

This is among the clearer and more unambiguous panpsychist statements of the early-twentieth-century scientists.

In fact the arguments of Huxley and the others mentioned above so closely link panpsychism with the scientific worldview that one is inclined to see panpsychism not as a usurper of mechanism but rather as a logical extension of it. All but the most dogmatic critic must allow for at least the possibility that matter itself possesses a mind-like dimension or aspect. On the one hand, such a quality of matter may ultimately be deemed “objective” in some empirical sense, and thus confirmable through the methodologies of science—though perhaps in dramatically revised form. If such is the case, then science may eventually reach a conclusion that undermines its own original mechanistic presumptions.

On the other hand, perhaps something of a Kuhnian paradigm shift will be required before widespread acceptance of panpsychism occurs; this indeed seems to be the more likely alternative. In such a case, the very same physical phenomena will be viewed in a new light—as possessing (perhaps) both mechanical and mental aspects. The mind-like aspects of matter, though, would seem to have no conventional scientific consequences, and hence such a shift would appear to be unlike those which have occurred in the past few centuries of Western thought. One would have to go back to the origins of the mechanistic worldview itself, in the sixteenth and seventeenth centuries, to find a comparable shift in thinking.

In “Gene and Organism” (1953), the zoologist Sewall Wright, then president of the American Society of Naturalists, takes up Whitehead’s and Agar’s proposal that the concept of the organism should apply to all structures of matter. He defines an organism as any structure in which interrelated parts communicate and cohere in a persistent and self-regulatory manner. He then notes that the concept applies not only to plants and animals, but to human society, and even—anticipating Gaia theory—to the Earth’s biosystem as a whole:

[T]he entire array of plants and animals and peripherally the soil and waters of a given region [constitute] an interdependent self-regulatory system, with considerable persistence. … Since regions [of the earth] are connected, the entire biota and peripherally the surface of the earth form one great organism. (7)

This is one of the few acknowledgments since the time of Fechner that the Earth may be considered as a single organic entity. Furthermore, says Wright, not only the Earth, but the solar system and the universe as a whole each qualify as organisms. At the other end of the scale, atoms and molecules are to be considered organisms; subatomic particles are questionable—not having parts, as he believes—but he feels that their “vibratory character” and persistence put them in the same general category.

As to the question of mind, Wright again invokes an argument by non-emergence, showing that mind must exist both in single-celled organisms and in their constituent parts: “If we are not at some point to postulate the abrupt origin of mind, mind must be traced to the genes, which presumably means to nucleo-protein molecules.” (13) This has implications for humans because it entails that “our own apparently unified stream of consciousness is somehow a fusion of the minds of the cells” of our bodies. Wright ultimately concurs with Eddington and Jeans that “the essential nature of all reality is that of mind” (16), though he does acknowledge that his is more of a pluralistic idealism: “reality consists primarily of a multiplicity of minds”—a critical issue from the panpsychist perspective.

Wright continued to elaborate on his panpsychist views over the subsequent 20 years. In an article published in The Monist in 1964, for example, he explicitly argues for “dual-aspect or monistic panpsychism.” He presents a hierarchy of mind in which each level in the chain of being is enminded, and participates in higher-order mind: “The very fact of interaction, at any level, implies … that minds are not entirely private. … They [also] exist as components of a more comprehensive mind.” (1964: 284) In a contribution to Cobb and Griffin’s 1977 compilation Mind in Nature, titled “Panpsychism and Science,” he reiterates the same themes and, with admirable clarity, places even more emphasis on the problem of emergence: “Emergence of mind from no mind at all is sheer magic.” (1977: 82) Wright asserts that dual-aspect panpsychism is the only logically consistent position.

Several other scientists began speaking out on panpsychism in the 1960s and the 1970s. In The Nature of Life (1961), C. H. Waddington discusses approvingly the ideas of Haldane mentioned above. Once again citing evolutionary continuity, Waddington asks:

Are we not forced to conclude that even in the simplest inanimate things there is something which belongs to the same realm of being as self-awareness? … Something must go on in the simplest inanimate things which can be described in the same language as would be used to describe our self-awareness. (121)

The biologist Bernhard Rensch published about half a dozen pieces arguing for a panpsychic theory of mind. In Evolution above the Species Level (1960) he reiterates the evolutionist line that “because of [a] lack of any serious evolutionary gap” one cannot limit mental abilities to the higher organisms. The evolutionary ancestry of living organisms represents a “gapless series of phylogenetic transformations” (334) in which at no point can we logically envision the sudden appearance of psychic abilities; “it is not very probable that in the continuous process of transformation entirely new laws of psychic parallelism [i.e. a mental aspect of things] should have suddenly emerged.” On Rensch’s view, the defining mental characteristic is sensation; he attributes it not only to all animals but also to plants, owing to the blurring of categories at the micro-organismal level. Even the gap between living and non-living systems is illusory:

Here again it is difficult to assume a sudden origin of first psychic elements somewhere in this gradual ascent from nonliving to living systems. It would not be impossible to ascribe “psychic” components to the realm of inorganic systems … . (352)

This “hylopsychic” view, Rensch claims, is supported by cognition theory and atomic physics. He concludes that “a hylopsychic concept is well in accord with many findings and facts of the natural sciences, and … is possibly the most suitable basis for a universal philosophy” (355).

In 1971 Rensch began referring to his system as panpsychistic identism. He generalized the conventional identity theory of mind, attributing “protopsychical” qualities to all levels of material organization, and asserting that “all ‘matter’ is protopsychical in character” (298). Here Rensch begins to treat the subject more systematically. He offers ten nominal facts in support of his thesis: (1) The only reality of which we are aware is that of “experienced phenomena.” (2) Dualism is obviously false, and mind and body are an indivisible unity—a fact supported by numerous thinkers throughout history. (3) Phylogenetic development is gapless, and there is no point at which any psychical element could suddenly emerge. (4) The same process occurs in individual development, i.e., from single-celled egg to fetus to person. (5) Sudden emergence of an interactive psychic quality would violate the conservation of energy, or at least introduce an inconsistency in it. (6) Life is rare throughout the universe, and to conjecture the sudden appearance of mind is “more hypothetical” than to presume it present from the beginning. (7) Matter is really just “complexes of energy,” and hence amenable to mind-like qualities. (8) Human consciousness arises from chemo-physical brain processes, and thus it is reasonable to believe that the “molecules, atoms, and elementary particles involved are protopsychical in character.” (9) Fetal cell tissue is capable of developing into any organ, including the brain, and hence all cells have the ability to yield mind. (10) “It is impossible to point to any fact which would prove that matter is not protopsychical in character.” (299–301) Such facts, individually, may not be compelling, but for Rensch the overall picture clearly supports a form of panpsychism.

In a 1972 article titled “Spinoza’s Identity Theory and Modern Biophilosophy” Rensch compares his views to those of Spinoza, in whom he found the philosophical basis for panpsychistic identism. Then in 1977 Rensch presented five arguments for his system; four of these were reiterations from 1971, and to these he added the fact that since DNA molecules can transmit inherited psychic characteristics from generation to generation, the molecules themselves must naturally have a protopsychic nature.

Rensch’s work is notable because he sought detailed empirical, scientific evidence of a panpsychist universe. This, however, is arguably an impossible task, in light of the intrinsic nature of mental experience and the apparent causal closure of the physical world.^6 Perhaps the only such route to panpsychism can be through a detailed understanding of the physiology of human consciousness. If, for example, a basis for our mental experience can be found in certain objective yet universal criteria (such as the quantum collapse theory of Hameroff and Penrose; see below), that could conceivably serve as an objective basis for panpsychism. Apart from such approaches, one is left largely with analogical and metaphysical arguments.

8.3 Bateson

Gregory Bateson researched and wrote on an impressively wide range of subjects, including biology, anthropology, psychology, cybernetic theory, and natural philosophy. A contrarian to the trend of increasing specialization, he was uniquely qualified to comment on the interconnection between nature and mind. His vision of ecological philosophy and the relationship between organic wholes was a predecessor to the more fully developed eco-philosophies of Henryk Skolimowski, Arne Naess, and other environmental philosophers. And his awareness of the importance of concepts such as energy, feedback, and information led to new arguments for panpsychism, anticipating later developments in chaos theory and non-linear dynamics.^7

Bateson’s inquiry into mind and nature initially brought him to a qualified version of panpsychism, though he seems to have ultimately abandoned it—for reasons that are not entirely clear. His first investigations in this area occurred in 1968. In an article titled “Conscious Purpose vs. Nature,” he expresses—like many other scientist-philosophers of the time—a belief that “the study of evolution might provide an explanation of mind” (35). Bateson’s first notable point is that the mind is essentially a natural phenomenon, bound up with the complexity of matter. He cites approvingly Lamarck’s view that “mental process must always have a physical representation” (36). Furthermore, he asserts that “wherever in the Universe we encounter [a certain degree] of complexity, we are dealing with mental phenomena.” In an attempt to elaborate this issue, Bateson observes that complex dynamic systems involve a process of feedback through which they are self-corrective. Examples of natural self-corrective systems include the individual organism, a society of organisms, and the self-sustaining ecosystem. All these levels of organization embody comparable system dynamics, and—by implication—should exhibit qualities of mind. To use his example, a forest ecosystem such as an “oak wood” is fundamentally like an individual organism, reflecting mind from within its bodily, material structure. Bateson refers to this kind of embodiment as “total mind”: “This entity [i.e. the individual organism] is similar to the oak wood and its controls are represented in the total mind, which is perhaps only a reflection of the total body.” (40) But he drops the matter there, only later following up on the implications.

Bateson’s 1972 compilation Steps to an Ecology of Mind includes the above-mentioned article and a number of other relevant pieces. Preeminent among these is “Form, Substance, and Difference,” originally published in 1970. It was in this article that Bateson first presented his famous but vague definition of information as “difference which makes a difference” (1970: 7). He attempts to relate the phenomenon of mind to feedback systems of energy circulation, deciding that it is “pure difference” that matters the most. He is emphatic that it is the circular feedback system itself that is important—that it is in precisely such a system that we observe what can rightly be called mind. On this point he is quite explicit:

The elementary cybernetic system with its messages in circuit is, in fact, the simplest unit of mind … . More complicated systems are perhaps more worthy to be called mental systems, but essentially this is what we are talking about. The unit which shows the characteristic of trial and error will be legitimately called a mental system. … We get a picture, then, of mind as synonymous with cybernetic system … . (1972: 459–460)

Notably, cybernetic feedback systems are ubiquitous in nature. They exist at all levels of organization, from molecular to galactic—anywhere parts interact and persistent structures appear. Therefore, cybernetic mind must be present throughout the universe. That, in fact, is Bateson’s conclusion: “we know that within Mind in the widest sense there will be a hierarchy of subsystems, any one of which we can call an individual mind.” His elaboration makes clear that such a conception of mind extends not only to small cybernetic systems but also to large-scale ones:

It means, you see, that I now localize something which I am calling “Mind” immanent in the large biological system—the ecosystem. Or, if I draw the system boundaries at a different level, then mind is immanent in the total evolution structure.

The individual mind is immanent but not only in the body. It is immanent also in pathways and messages outside the body; and there is a larger Mind of which the individual mind is only a subsystem. This larger Mind is comparable to God and is perhaps what some people mean by “God,” but it is still immanent in the total interconnected social system and planetary ecology.

It is not just a universal Mind, but mind at all levels of existence—true pluralistic panpsychism.^8

Still, Bateson qualifies his view. The only exceptions for him are the fundamental atomic particles (“atomies”). These particles, being without parts, lack the dynamic feedback interrelationships that he sees as necessary for the process of mind. One of his footnotes is illuminating:

I do not agree with Samuel Butler, Whitehead, or Teilhard de Chardin that it follows from this mental character of the macroscopic world that the single atomies must have mental character or potentiality. I see the mental as a function only of complex relationship. (465)

He repeats the same view in his most philosophical work, Mind and Nature (1979: 103): “I do not believe that single subatomic particles are ‘minds’ in my sense because I do believe that mental process is always a sequence of interactions between parts. The explanation of mental phenomena must always reside in the organization and interaction of multiple parts.” But this is a relatively minor issue, and it doesn’t substantially affect Bateson’s generally panpsychist outlook.^9

It is in Mind and Nature, however, that Bateson seems to back away from the panpsychist implications of his earlier writings—though, oddly, maintaining the same theory of mind, with presumably the same consequences. Mind still exists in the interrelationship and interaction between dynamic parts. But now this is only a necessary, not a sufficient condition for mind. He lays out six somewhat cryptic criteria for complex systems to possess mind, noting that any system meeting them must be designated as possessing mind.^10 The criteria are very general and would seem to apply to any dynamic system whatsoever. Yet he excludes not only (as before) subatomic particles, but other physical systems too:

There are, of course, many systems which are made of many parts, ranging from galaxies to sand dunes to toy locomotives. Far be it from me to suggest that all of these are minds or contain minds or engage in mental process. The … galaxy may become part of the mental system which includes the astronomer and his telescope. But the objects do not become thinking subsystems in those larger minds. The [six] criteria are useful only in combination. (1979: 104)

This puzzling statement is potentially inconsistent with Bateson’s own standards. If the criteria are valid, they should be valid universally. They appear to occur in combination everywhere. He thus backs away from the logical implications of his own theory—implications he had accepted only a few years earlier. Whether he was ultimately able to construct a cohesive and consistent theory of mind remains an open question.

8.4 Other Scientific Interpretations

From the 1970s on, physicists became increasingly involved in the discussion about panpsychism. Evan Walker (1970), for example, argued that quantum processes in brain synapses account for a number of characteristics of consciousness, in particular its existence and non-physicality. He also remarks that, more generally, “consciousness may be associated with all quantum mechanical processes” (175). He closes the 1970 article with this observation:

[S]ince everything that occurs is ultimately the result of one or more quantum mechanical events, the universe is “inhabited” by an almost unlimited number of rather discrete conscious, usually nonthinking entities that are responsible for the detailed working of the universe.

It is a striking view, one that follows from Haldane’s related ideas of the 1930s.

Breaking from the evolutionary-continuity approach, Andrew Cochran (1971) argued for a similar perspective. In a rather ingenious argument, he observes that the elements of organic compounds—carbon, hydrogen, nitrogen, and oxygen—have among the lowest atomic heat capacities, which corresponds to a high degree of “wave predominance” (as opposed to “particle predominance”), and hence are the most endowed with the qualities of consciousness. He suggests that “the quantum mechanical wave properties of matter are actually the conscious properties of matter,” and therefore “atoms and fundamental particles have a rudimentary degree of consciousness, volition, or self-activity” (236). These ideas would be reflected in the later work of David Bohm, Freeman Dyson, and other physicists.

Beginning in the early 1970s, the biologist Charles Birch wrote a series of essays (1971, 1972, 1974, 1994) and a book (1995) presenting a new interpretation of process philosophy, arguing for a panexperientialist form of panpsychism. His 1974 essay, for example, claims that panpsychism represents a form of evolutionary teleology in which the primordial psychic phenomena of atoms and molecules in the early universe foreshadowed the later appearance of mind and consciousness. And his 1994 speech presents six reasons for adopting the panexperientialist viewpoint: (1) Biology points away from crass mechanism. (2) The process view of true individuals as possessing experience makes intuitive sense. (3) Panexperientialism avoids the emergence category mistake. (4) The “doctrine of internal relations” suggests that true individuals possess unique experiential phenomena. (5) Computers and other mechanisms are not organisms, and thus are inherently limited in their ability to model consciousness. (6) The reality of subjectivity suggests that it has a fundamental place in the universe.

In Disturbing the Universe (1979), Freeman Dyson presents his views on a range of subjects, from physics and cosmology to politics and economics. In the penultimate chapter he examines mechanistic philosophy and the concept of the universe as a clockwork machine. He notes that, as one descends the ladder of complexity, things at first appear more mechanical, but then at the level of molecular physics this process reverses itself: “If we divide a DNA molecule into its component atoms, the atoms behave less mechanically than the molecule. If we divide an atom into nucleus and electrons, the electrons are less mechanical than the atom.” (248) At the quantum level the observer is intimately bound up with physical events, and thus “the laws [of physics] leave a place for mind in the description of every molecule” (249). The logical continuity of nature then presses us to accept that mind is present and active at all levels of existence:

In other words, mind is already inherent in every electron, and the processes of human consciousness differ only in degree but not in kind from the processes of choice between quantum states which we call “chance” when they are made by electrons.

Dyson readily admitted that such a view is antithetical to conventional science. He cited Jacques Monod as typical of the conventional view, noting that Monod holds out “the deepest scorn” for such an “animist” conception of the world.^11 But Dyson was unfazed. For him the “importance of mind in the scheme of things” is undeniable, whether one considers the role of mind in the electron or in a conception of the world-soul.

Chronologically speaking, Bohm’s writings of the 1980s were the next events of significance. I defer this discussion to the next section, which is dedicated to his work.

A brief word is warranted for Michael Lockwood’s 1989 book Mind, Brain, and the Quantum. Following the approach of Paul Churchland (discussed in chapter 9), Lockwood employs the methodology of phase-space analysis for his discussion of mind. He concludes that a form of the identity theory is true, one in which mind doesn’t reduce to matter but rather “represents the physical world as infused with intrinsic qualities which … constitute the basis of its causal powers and which include immediately introspectible qualities in their own right” (1989: 159).

Chalmers (1996), Seager (2001), and others have suggested that this view is in itself panpsychist. But Lockwood is very evasive in his terminology. At one point he argues for “a conception of the world as, in some sense, a sum of perspectives” (1989: 177), and later adds “I wish to argue that, in consciousness, that intrinsic nature makes itself manifest” (238). But it is not clear whether such a view qualifies as panpsychism, as he defines it. Other passages seem contradictory. He claims that consciousness comprises only a portion of these intrinsic qualities: “The qualities of which we are immediately aware, in consciousness, precisely are some at least of the intrinsic qualities … specifically, states and processes within our own brains.” (159) He then speaks negatively of the panpsychist view in his discussion of unsensed qualities: the “major advantage of holding that phenomenal qualities can exist unsensed” is that “it enables one to halt this slide into panpsychism” (170). And none of his later works suggests anything like an endorsement. If Lockwood’s position is a panpsychist one, it is a very tenuous and vague interpretation.

The most recent articulation of a scientific approach to panpsychism, again from quantum theory, was introduced by medical scientist Stuart Hameroff. Working in conjunction with mathematician Roger Penrose, Hameroff developed a theory of human consciousness that was centered on the coordinated collapse of superposed quantum conditions in the brain. Their various presentations of the theory (Hameroff 1994, Penrose 1994a, Hameroff and Penrose 1996, Hameroff 2009) indicate that quantum collapse might be associated with a “moment of experience” in the Whiteheadian sense. This, incidentally, is an interesting reversal of the so-called Copenhagen interpretation of quantum mechanics, in which consciousness causes quantum collapse. On the view of Hameroff and Penrose, precisely the opposite occurs: Collapse causes consciousness.

According to standard theory, atomic and sub-atomic particles appear to evolve into multiple simultaneous superposed states. When an act of measurement is performed, the condition of superposition collapses randomly into one of the states, which then appears as the actual state of the particle. At present there are conflicting views on whether reduction happens in reality or whether it is some kind of artificial or illusory phenomenon. Hameroff and Penrose take it as fact, and further suggest that it happens not merely upon measurement by a subjective observer but independently—as a spontaneous process that they call objective reduction (OR). They argue that certain microstructures of neurons—tubular skeletal structures called microtubules—serve as the sites for sustained quantum superposition. Microtubules also allow for a coordination between individual tubulin molecules that results in a large-scale “orchestrated OR” that may produce a unified, large-scale sense of consciousness. Large numbers of tubulin molecules coordinating their effects, and collapsing repeatedly on the order of every 0.5 to 5 milliseconds, are said to account for the apparently continuous stream of consciousness that we normally feel.

On the theory of Hameroff and Penrose, superposed states must be maintained until a quantum gravity threshold is reached; only at that point can OR, and thus conscious experience, take place. A system of fewer elements—fewer neurons, or fewer tubulin molecules—requires a longer, and therefore less likely, time in which to reach the threshold. Complex living organisms are ideal for the OR process, since they possess large numbers of quantum-coherent structures.

Hameroff and Penrose’s analysis is primarily focused on the brain and its neurons, but they emphasize that such a process could appear anywhere microtubules are present. Since they are universally present in all living cells, from animals to plants to one-celled life forms, all living beings would presumably experience some degree of consciousness. Fewer tubulin molecules, though, would imply a longer period of time between state collapses, and thus a longer time between moments of experience.^12

Hameroff independently proceeded to further develop the philosophical implications of the OR theory, linking this process of quantum collapse to a realization of “proto-conscious” events occurring ubiquitously in the quantum realm (1998a, 1998b, 2009) and suggesting that “perhaps panpsychists are in some way correct and components of mental processes are fundamental, like mass, spin or charge” (1998a: 121). This would seem to be the logical extension of the Hameroff-Penrose theory, although Penrose seems reluctant to endorse it. He apparently holds that only certain collapse conditions, namely those occurring upon reaching a quantum gravity threshold, count as conscious; and yet it is hard to see what is ontologically unique, with respect to mind, about this particular mode of collapse. And even on this view, a panpsychist interpretation is still possible. Any physical system has at least a statistical likelihood of sustaining a superposed state until the critical threshold is reached. Even a single subatomic particle has a small but finite chance of sustaining superposition until OR occurs: “As OR could, in principle, occur ubiquitously within many types of inanimate media, it may seem to imply a form of panpsychism.” (Hameroff and Penrose 1996: 38) Indeed it is, with the qualification that the incidents of psyche are, for simple particles, extremely rare: “a single superposed electron would spontaneously reduce its state … only once in a period longer than the present age of the universe.” Other theoretical estimates indicate a somewhat more frequent occurrence, such as once every 10 million to 100 million years (Penrose 1994b: 332, 340). Still, a rare psychic event is psyche nonetheless.

Hameroff (1998b) adds that his theory “suggests that consciousness may involve a self-organizing quantum state reduction process occurring at the Planck scale [10–33 centimeters],” and that “in a panexperiential Platonic view consistent with modern physics, quantum spin networks encode proto-conscious ‘funda-mental’ experience.” With many ongoing developments in quantum theory in general, such a view of mind is likely to undergo continual refinement for the foreseeable future.

The final word in this section goes to John Wheeler. Along with Bateson and Bohm, he was among the first to suggest that information was a potential ultimate ground of reality—see his 1994 essay “It from Bit.” Wheeler’s acceptance of the quantum as a fundamental principle of the universe suggests that quantum collapses, driven by some kind of observer-process, are universally present. Given the speculative connection between quantum collapse and conscious observation, it is natural to consider the universe as filled with elemental conscious events. Wheeler suggests (1994: 307) that “we may someday have to enlarge the scope of what we mean by a ‘who’”—that is, a “who” as any observer or system that induces a quantum collapse. Observing minds could in principle be present even throughout the so-called inanimate realm. A few years before his death, he all but admitted as much: “I find it hard to draw a line between the conscious observer and the inanimate one.” (2002)

8.5 Bohm and the Implicate Order

Like many other physicists, David Bohm (1917–1992) had a longstanding interest in developing the philosophical implications of quantum physics. He wrote numerous pieces on the philosophy of physics, and seems to have been especially interested in the process of mind. More than any other scientist-philosopher of the twentieth century, Bohm developed and openly endorsed a form of panpsychism that was grounded in fundamental physical laws—in his case, laws of quantum mechanics.

Bohm’s interest in panpsychism began as early as 1957. In his book Causality and Chance in Modern Physics, he made just one passing reference to the concept, in the midst of a discussion of his idea of strong emergence—that “new qualities and new laws” can appear because of the “universal process of becoming” (1957: 163) that dominates the universe. Bohm noted that processes of living matter do not fundamentally differ from those of non-living matter: “[W]hen one analyzes processes taking place in inanimate matter over long enough periods of time, one finds a similar behaviour [to living processes]. Only here the process is so much slower … .” Such a standpoint recalls the arguments of Royce, examined earlier in this volume.

Bohm edged closer to panpsychism in Wholeness and the Implicate Order (1980). He states that quantum theory presents a fundamental challenge to mechanism because it exhibits radically discontinuous or quantized behavior, simultaneously wave-like and particle-like properties, and extreme non-locality (a phenomenon in which coupled particles form an instantaneous relationship over any distance whatsoever, leading to a form of communication that exceeds the speed of light). Indeed, he notes that the structure of the universe “is much more reminiscent of how the organs constituting living beings are related, than it is of how parts of a machine interact” (175).

Bohm goes on to argue for a form of neutral monism wherein “both inanimate matter and life [are comprehended] on the basis of a single ground, common to both” (193)—something he designates as the “implicate order.” Repeating his earlier observation, he comments that “even inanimate matter maintains itself in a continual process similar to the growth of plants.” In the same way that this common ground unites living and non-living, so too does it unite mind and non-mind: “the implicate order applies both to matter and to consciousness” (196). Bohm sees both sets of dualities as false and fundamentally mistaken. Consequently, he argues, there is a sense in which all matter is both alive and conscious. In his words, “in a wide range of … important respects, consciousness and matter in general are basically the same order (i.e. the implicate order as a whole)” (208).

Something approaching panpsychism is a natural consequence of such a view. Consider memory, for example. “The recurrence and stability of our own memory … is thus brought about as part of the very same process that sustains the recurrence and stability in the manifest order of matter in general.” The temporally persistent structures of mass-energy that we see around us reflect an ongoing process of recollection by the implicate order, and thus are aspects of mentality.

Bohm explained his theory in less technical terms in a 1982 interview in the journal ReVision, where he considered the possibility of a deeper ground underlying both the explicate and the implicate order. When asked if this ground is self-aware, he replied “Yes … since it contains both matter and mind, it would have in some sense to be aware.” (1982: 37) Repeating again his view that “thought and matter have a great similarity of order,” he stated that “in a way, nature is alive, as Whitehead would say, all the way to the depths. And intelligent. Thus it is both mental and material, as we are.” (39)

In March of 1985, Bohm gave an important speech at a meeting of the American Society for Psychical Research. Published under the title “A New Theory of the Relationship of Mind and Matter,”^13 it combined a direct endorsement of panpsychism with Bohm’s first explicit use of the concept of participation as related to a new worldview. Beginning with the panpsychist aspect, there are several passages in which he clearly asserts that mind is found in all systems that contain “information content”—that is, in all dynamically coherent particles or subsystems. This new emphasis on information recalled the work of Bateson, though Bohm did not specifically cite him.

Recognizing that the term ‘information’ implies both a meaning and a consciousness able to perceive that meaning, Bohm notes first of all that, on his interpretation of quantum theory, all physical systems embody information. On his view, “the notion of information [is] something that need not belong only to human consciousness, but that may indeed be present, in some sense, even in inanimate systems of atoms and electrons” (1986: 124–125). Because of the “basic similarity between the quantum behavior of a system … and the behavior of mind” (130), Bohm argues that mind and matter are intimately connected at all levels of being:

[T]he mental and the material are two sides of one overall process. … There is one energy that is the basis of all reality. … There is never any real division between mental and material sides at any stage of the overall process. (129)

The conclusion is a pluralistic panpsychism that reaches up and down the ontological hierarchy:

I would suggest that both [mind and body] are essentially the same. … That which we experience as mind … will in a natural way ultimately reach the level of the wavefunction and of the “dance” of the particles. There is no unbridgeable gap or barrier between any of these levels. … It is implied that, in some sense, a rudimentary consciousness is present even at the level of particle physics. It would also be reasonable to suppose an indefinitely greater kind of consciousness that is universal and that pervades the entire process [of the universe]. (131)

For Bohm, this panpsychism fits together with a world described as fundamentally participatory in nature: “the basic notion is participation rather than interaction” (113). As he sees it, matter is participatory because of the quantum nature of atomic particles. These particles, even if one assumes them (as Bohm did) to be point-like entities, are seen to exist probabilistically: An electron in an atom has a high chance of existing in its so-called proper orbit, but it also has a non-zero chance of existing outside that orbit, across the room, or even across the universe. Each particle exists, in a very real sense, everywhere in the universe at once. Because of this, every particle is in contact with every other particle.^14 All particles thus “dance” together, to a greater or lesser degree. We can clearly see this phenomenon in superconductivity—wherein “electrons are thus participating in a common action based on a common pool of information” (122)—or in non-local experiments. But even where it is not apparent, this interconnection is always present. Echoing a view as old as Anaxagoras, Bohm says “the whole of the universe is in some way enfolded in everything and … each thing is enfolded in the whole” (114).

On this view of reality, the objectivist stance of an observer dispassionately making observations is fundamentally inadequate. Interaction becomes participation:

[S]uch a complex process of participation evidently goes far beyond what is meant by a merely mechanical interaction. It is therefore not really correct to call what happens a measurement. … Rather, it is a mutual transformation of both systems … . (124)

Each system changes the other—an idea reaching back to Hartshorne, Schiller, and even Campanella. Bohm concludes, like Wheeler, that

the mechanical notion of an interactive universe is seen to be inadequate. It is in need of replacement by the notion of an objectively participative universe that includes our own participation as a special case. (126)

In 1990 Bohm reissued the 1986 article with substantial changes—confusingly, under the same title. In the new version he clarifies his philosophical terminology without abandoning his central view. He states, for example, that “quantum theory … implies that the particles of physics have certain primitive mind-like qualities … (though of course, they do not have consciousness)” (1990: 272). He is clearly refining his ideas, no longer being satisfied to attribute “rudimentary consciousness” to elementary particles.

For Bohm, then, participation occurs both within the material realm, down to the quantum level, and also between the processes of mind that occur at all levels of being. He describes “the essential mode of relationship of all these [levels of mind] as participation” (284), a fact that applies equally to the human scale and to the atomic scale: “For the human being, all of this implies a thoroughgoing wholeness, in which mental and physical sides participate very closely in each other.” Such an ontological outlook may be best described as a form of participatory panpsychism.

Bohm’s last significant philosophical work, co-written with Basil Hiley, was Undivided Universe (1993). Though primarily a technical work in quantum physics, it included a well-developed philosophical analysis that elaborated on earlier themes. The philosophical conclusions at the end of the book were taken largely verbatim from Bohm (1990) and so did not add anything substantially new.

Notes

1. It should be noted, though, that all of these, especially functionalism, can be interpreted as forms of panpsychism.

2. There is evidence that the Greeks also experimented with rubbed amber and the attractive force of static electricity. If so, that would have added further evidence of psyche in inorganic objects.

3. It also anticipates the soon-to-follow work of Russell and his quasi-panpsychist neutral monism. That concept—the basis for what is today called “Russellian monism”—is discussed in chapter 9 of the present volume.

4. Interestingly, scientists have discovered that the sun does in fact have an internal “resonance phenomena” that is surprisingly complex. The sun exhibits at least two modes of resonance: a 16-month cycle of increasing and decreasing rotation near the solar equator (see Howe et al. 2000) and a series of up-and-down surface vibrations, about 2,000 kilometers in magnitude, centered on a period of 5 minutes (see Friedman 1986 or Lang 1995). These “solar heartbeats” point to an internal structure and complexity of a high order, and through the associated sun-spot activity they have a non-trivial effect on the Earth. The sun has a number of other fascinating mysteries about it, not the least is the sudden and dramatic rise in the temperature of its atmosphere, from around 6,000°K at the surface to around 1,000,000°K at a height of 100,000 km above the surface; this astonishing increase has no known cause, and in fact appears to violate the second law of thermodynamics. Such physical complexity indicates, if nothing else, that our understanding of a body as complex as the sun has significant gaps. We should thus not be too quick to dismiss the possibility of yet other unacknowledged aspects of its existence.

5. The idea that cells might be conscious continues to find adherents. See, for example, Edwards 2005.

6. Physics describes systems of mass-energy that evolve via specific natural laws that are expressible mathematically. Causality seems to exist entirely within the realm of matter and energy. There is neither room nor evidence for non-physical (i.e., mental or spiritual) causation. Hence the widely held belief that physics is “causally closed.”

7. See, for example, Bateson 1972: 403ff.

8. This aspect of Bateson’s philosophy seems to be rarely acknowledged, even as the concept of “information” is put to use in other panpsychist theories. Bohm (1986) spoke in similar terms, though without citing Bateson. Chalmers (1996: 293–301) developed his own information-theoretic form of panpsychism, but without discussing the related panpsychist views of either Bateson or Bohm.

9. The main problem with this view is that mind is no longer truly fundamental, but apparently must radically emerge as soon as a system with “parts” appears—perhaps the first hydrogen atom, or the first proton (with quarks as parts). But this is a philosophical problem that Bateson neither resolves nor even acknowledges.

10. “(1) All mind is an aggregate of interacting parts or components. (2) The interaction between parts of mind is triggered by difference. (3) Mental process requires collateral energy. (4) Mental process requires circular chains of determination. (5) In mental process, the effects of difference are to be regarded as transforms of the events which preceded them. (6) The description and classification of these processes of transformation disclose a hierarchy of logical types immanent in the phenomena.” (Bateson 1979: 102)

11. See Monod’s 1971 book Chance and Necessity.

12. The nematode worm C. elegans is hypothesized to experience at most two “moments” per second, the simpler paramecium one per minute (Hameroff and Penrose 1996: 51).

13. The talk was published as Bohm 1986.

14. Recall Leibniz’s view that all monads are in contact with all others. See Leibniz 1714b, section 61.

Bibliography

Abram, D. 1996. The Spell of the Sensuous. Vintage.
Agar, W. 1943. A Contribution to the Theory of the Living Organism. Melbourne University Press.
Alexander, S. 1914. The basis of realism. In Realism and the Background of Phenomenology, ed. R. Chisolm (Free Press, 1960).
Alexander, S. 1920. Space, Time, and Deity. Macmillan.
Allison, H. 1987. Benedict de Spinoza. Yale University Press.
Alter, T., and Howell, R. 2015. The short slide from a posteriori physicalism to Russellian monism. In Consciousness in the Physical World, ed. T. Alter and Y. Nagasawa. Oxford University Press.
Alter, T., and Nagasawa, Y. 2012. What is Russellian monism? Journal of Consciousness Studies 19 (9–10): 67–95.
Alter, T., and Nagasawa, Y., eds. 2015. Consciousness in the Physical World. Oxford University Press.
Andrews, J. 1998. Weak panpsychism and environmental ethics. Environmental Values 7: 381–396.
Aristotle. 1995. The Complete Works of Aristotle, ed. J. Barnes. Princeton University Press.
Armstrong, D. 1968. A Materialist Theory of the Mind. Routledge.
Armstrong, E. 1973. Saint Francis: Nature Mystic. University of California Press.
Armstrong-Buck, S. 1986. Whitehead’s metaphysical system as a foundation for environmental ethics. Environmental Ethics 8: 241–259.
Augustine. ca. 410. The City of God. Reprint: Catholic Way, 2015.
Bacon, F. ca. 1620. Natural History (Silva silvarum sive historia naturalis).
Bahcall, N., Ostriker, J. P., Perlmutter, S., and Steinhardt, P. J. 1999. The cosmic triangle. Science 284 (5419): 1481–1489.
Bak, P., and Chen, K. 1991. Self-organized critically. Scientific American 264 (1): 46–53.
Bakewell, C. 1904a. Review of Why the Mind Has a Body. Philosophical Review 13 (2): 220–229.
Bakewell, C. 1904b. A rejoinder. Philosophical Review 13 (3): 342–346.
Barnes, J. 1987. Early Greek Philosophy. Penguin.
Basile, P. 2007. The compounding of consciousness. In Consciousness, Reality, and Value, ed. P. Basile and L. McHenry. Ontos.
Basile, P. 2008. Mind-body problem and panpsychism. In Handbook of Whiteheadian Process Philosophy, ed. W. Desmond Jr. and M. Weber. Ontos.
Basile, P. 2010a. It must be true, but how can it? Some remarks on panpsychism and mental composition. In The Metaphysics of Consciousness, ed. P. Basile. Cambridge University Press.
Basile, P. 2010b. Materialist versus panexperientialist physicalism. Process Studies 39 (2): 264–284.
Basile, P. 2015. Learning from Leibniz: Whitehead (and Russell) on mind, matter, and monads. British Journal for the History of Philosophy 23 (6): 1128–1149.
Bateson, G. 1968. Conscious purpose versus nature. In Dialectics of Liberation, ed. D. Cooper. Penguin. In Steps to an Ecology of Mind (Ballantine, 1972).
Bateson, G. 1970. Form, substance, and difference. General Semantics Bulletin 37: 5–13. Reprinted in Bateson, Steps to an Ecology of Mind (Ballantine, 1972).
Bateson, G. 1972. Steps to an Ecology of Mind. Ballantine.
Bateson, G. 1979. Mind and Nature. Ballantine.
Bawden, H. 1904. The meaning of the psychical from the point of view of the functional psychology. Philosophical Review 13 (3): 298–319.
Beeson, D. 1992. Maupertuis: An Intellectual Biography. Voltaire Foundation, Taylor Institution.
Beever, J., and Cisney, V. 2013. All things in mind: Panpsychist elements in Spinoza, Deleuze, and Peirce. Biosemiotics 6 (3): 351–365.
Bennett, C. 1922. Review of Volonte et Conscience. Philosophical Review 37: 86–90.
Bennett, J. 1984. A Study of Spinoza’s Ethics. Hackett.
Bergson, H. 1896/1911. Matter and Memory. Allen and Unwin.
Bergson, H. 1907/1911. Creative Evolution. Holt.
Bergson, H. 1911/1920. Mind Energy. Holt.
Bergson, H. 1922. Duration and Simultaneity. Reprint: Bobbs-Merrill, 1965.
Berman, M. 1981. The Reenchantment of the World. Cornell University Press.
Birch, C. 1971. Purpose in the universe. Zygon 6 (1): 4–27.
Birch, C. 1972. Participatory evolution. Journal of the American Academy of Religion 40: 147–163.
Birch, C. 1974. Chance, necessity, and purpose. In Studies in the Philosophy of Biology, ed. F. Ayala and T. Dobzhansky. Macmillan.
Birch, C. 1994. Why I became a panxperientialist. Presented at conference on Consciousness in Humans, Animals, and Machines, Claremont, California.
Birch, C. 1995. Feelings. University of New South Wales Press.
Bjelland, A. 1981. Capek, Bergson, and process proto-mentalism. Process Studies 11 (3): 180–189.
Bjelland, A. 1982. Popper’s critique of panpsychism and process protomentalism. Modern Schoolman 59 (4): 233–254.
Blamauer, M., ed. 2011. The Mental as Fundamental. Ontos.
Blamauer, M. 2012. Schelling’s “real materialism.” Minerva 16: 1–24.
Blamauer, M. 2012b. Does the fundamentality of consciousness entail its ubiquity? Filozofia 67 (3): 243–253.
Blamauer, M. 2013. The role of subjectivity and the continuity-argument for panpsychism. Polish Journal of Philosophy 7 (1): 7–18.
Bohm, D. 1957. Causality and Chance in Modern Physics. Routledge.
Bohm, D. 1980. Wholeness and the Implicate Order. Routledge.
Bohm, D. 1982. Nature as creativity. ReVision 5 (2): 35–40.
Bohm, D. 1986. A new theory of the relationship of mind and matter. Journal of the American Society for Psychical Research 80 (2): 113–135.
Bohm, D. 1990. A new theory of the relationship of mind and matter. Philosophical Psychology 3 (2): 271–286.
Bohm, D., and Hiley, B. 1993. Undivided Universe. Routledge.
Bonansea, B. 1969. Tommaso Campanella. Catholic University Press.
Bonifazi, C. 1978. The Soul of the World. University Press of America.
Bowie, A. 1998. Schelling. In Encyclopedia of Philosophy, ed. E. Craig. Routledge.
Bradley, F. 1893. Appearance and Reality. Reprint: Clarendon, 1930.
Brettschneider, B. 1964. The Philosophy of Samuel Alexander. Humanities Press.
Brickman, B. 1941. An Introduction to Francesco Patrizi’s Nova de Universis Philosophia.
Brown, N. 1959. Life Against Death. Wesleyan University Press.
Brown, S. 1990. Leibniz and More’s cabbalistic circle. In Henry More: Tercentary Studies, ed. S. Hutton. Kluwer.
Bruno, G. 1584a. Cause, Principle, and Unity (De la causa, principio, et uno). Reprint: Cambridge University Press, 1998.
Bruno, G. 1584b. On the Infinite Universe and Worlds (De l’infinito universo et mondi). In D. Singer, Giordano Bruno: His Life and Thought, with Annotated Translation of His Work—On the Infinite Universe and Worlds (Schuman, 1950).
Burks, A. 1996. Peirce’s evolutionary pragmatic idealism. Synthese 106: 323–372.
Burks, A. 1997. Logic, learning, and creativity in evolution. In Studies in the Logic of Charles Sanders Peirce, ed. N. Houser et al. Indiana University Press.
Bush, W. 1925. William James and panpsychism. In Studies in the History of Ideas, volume 2. Columbia University Press.
Butler, C. 1978. Panpsychism: A restatement of the genetic argument. Idealistic Studies 8: 33–39.
Butler, S. 1880. Unconscious Memory. Reprint: Longmans, Green, 1910.
Calcagno, A. 1998. Giordano Bruno and the Logic of Coincidence. P. Lang.
Callicott, J. B. 1982. Traditional American Indian and Western European attitudes toward nature: An overview. Environmental Ethics 4: 293–318.
Campanella, T. 1620. On the Sense and Feeling in All Things and on Magic (De sensu rerum et magia). In Tommaso Campanella, ed. B. Bonansea (Catholic University Press, 1969).
Campanella, T. 1638. Metaphysics (Metafisica). In Tommaso Campanella, ed. B. Bonansea (Catholic University Press, 1969).
Capek, M. 1961. The Philosophical Impact of Contemporary Physics. Van Nostrand.
Capek, M. 1971. Bergson and Modern Physics. Reidel.
Cardano, G. 1560. The De subtilitate of Girolamo Cardano. Reprint: Arizona Center for Medieval and Renaissance Studies, 2013.
Carus, P. 1892. Panpsychism and panbiotism. Monist 3: 234–257.
Cassirer, E. 1927. The Individual and the Cosmos in Renaissance Philosophy. Reprint: Barnes and Noble, 1963.
Cassirer, E. 1942. Giovanni Pico della Mirandola. Journal of the History of Ideas 3 (2): 123–344.
Cavendish, M. 1655. Philosophical and Physical Opinions. In Modern Women Philosophers: 1600–1900, ed. M. Waithe. Reprint: Kluwer, 1991.
Cavendish, M. 1664. Philosophical Letters. In Women Philosophers of the Early Modern Period, ed. M. Atherton (Hackett, 1994).
Chaisson, E. 2001. Cosmic Evolution. Harvard University Press.
Chalmers, D. 1995. Facing up to the problem of consciousness. Journal of Consciousness Studies 2 (3): 200–219.
Chalmers, D. 1996. The Conscious Mind. Oxford University Press.
Chalmers, D. 2002. Consciousness and its place in nature. In Philosophy of Mind, ed. D. Chalmers. Oxford University Press.
Chalmers, D. 2015. Panpsychism and panprotopsychism. In Consciousness in the Physical World, ed. T. Alter and Y. Nagasawa. Oxford University Press.
Churchland, P. M. 1986. Some reductive strategies in cognitive neurobiology. Mind 95: 279–309.
Churchland, P. M. 1997. To transform the phenomena. Philosophy of Science 64 supplement, S408–S420. In P. M. Churchland and P. S. Churchland, On the Contrary (MIT Press, 1998).
Clark, M. 1990. Nietzsche on Truth and Philosophy. Cambridge University Press.
Clark, M., and Dudrick, D. 2012. The Soul of Nietzsche’s Beyond Good and Evil. Cambridge University Press.
Clark, R. 1955. Herder: His Life and Thought. University of California Press.
Clarke, D. 2003. Panpsychism and the Religious Attitude. SUNY Press.
Clarke, D., ed. 2004. Panpsychism: Past and Recent Selected Readings. SUNY Press.
Cleve, F. 1969. The Giants of Pre-Sophistic Greek Philosophy. Martinus Nijhoff.
Clifford, W. 1874. Body and mind. In Lectures and Essays, volume 2 (Macmillan, 1903)
Clifford, W. 1878. On the nature of things in themselves. Mind, January. In Lectures and Essays (Macmillan, 1903).
Cochran, A. 1971. The relationship between quantum physics and biology. Foundations of Physics 1 (3): 235–250.
Cobb, J. B., Jr., and Griffin, D. R., eds. 1977. Mind in Nature. University Press of America.
Coleman, S. 2012. Mental chemistry: Combination for panpsychists. Dialectica 66 (1): 137–166.
Coleman, S. 2014. The real combination problem: Panpsychism, micro-subjects, and emergence. Erkenntnis 79 (1): 19–44.
Conway, J., and Kochen, S. 2006. The free will theorem. Foundations of Physics 36 (10): 1441–1473.
Conway, J., and Kochen, S. 2009. The strong free will theorem. Notices of the American Mathematical Society 56 (2): 226–232.
Cooper, W. 1990. William James’s theory of mind. Journal of the History of Philosophy 28: 571–593.
Coxon, A. 1986. The Fragments of Parmenides. Van Gorcum.
Craig, E., ed. 1998. Encyclopedia of Philosophy. Routledge.
Crombie, I. 1962. An Examination of Plato’s Doctrines, volume 1. Routledge.
Curley, E. 1969. Spinoza’s Metaphysics. Harvard University Press.
Curley, E. 1988. Behind the Geometrical Method. Princeton University Press.
DeGrood, D. 1965. Haeckel’s Theory of the Unity of Nature. Christopher.
Delahunty, R. 1985. Spinoza. Routledge.
De Quincey, C. 1994. Consciousness all the way down? Journal of Consciousness Studies 1 (2): 217–229.
De Quincey, C. 1999. Past matter, present mind. Journal of Consciousness Studies 6 (1): 91–106.
De Quincey, C. 2002. Radical Nature. Invisible Cities.
Dewey, J. 1925. Experience and Nature. Open Court.
Dewey, J. 1940. Time and individuality. In The Later Works, volume 14, ed. J. Boydston (Southern Illinois University Press, 1988).
Diderot, D. 1754. Thoughts on the Interpretation of Nature. In Selected Writings, ed. L. Crocker (Macmillan, 1966).
Diderot, D. 1769. D’Alembert’s Dream. In Diderot: Interpreter of Nature (Lawrence and Wishart, 1937).
Diderot, D. 1774–1780. Elements of Physiology. In Diderot: Interpreter of Nature (Lawrence and Wishart, 1937).
Donagan, A. 1989. Spinoza. University of Chicago Press.
Dooley, B. 1995. Italy in the Baroque. Garland.
Drake, D. 1925. Mind and Its Place in Nature. Reprint: Kraus, 1970.
Dulles, A. 1941. Princeps Concordiae. Harvard University Press.
Dyson, F. 1979. Disturbing the Universe. Harper & Row.
Eddington, A. 1920. Space, Time, and Gravitation. Cambridge University Press.
Eddington, A. 1928. The Nature of the Physical World. Cambridge University Press.
Eddington, A. 1939. The Philosophy of Physical Science. Cambridge University Press.
Edelman, G. 1992. Bright Air, Brilliant Fire. Basic Books.
Edwards, J. 2005. Is consciousness only a property of individual cells? Journal of Consciousness Studies 12 (4–5): 60–76.
Edwards, P. 1967. Panpsychism. In Encyclopedia of Philosophy, ed. P. Edwards. Macmillan.
Edwards, P. 1972. Panpsychism. In Encyclopedia of Philosophy, ed. P. Edwards. Macmillan.
Ells, P. 2011. Panpsychism: The Philosophy of the Sensuous Cosmos. O-Books.
Endres, M., and Pichler, A. 2013. Ways of reading Nietzsche in the light of KGW IX. Journal of Nietzsche Studies 44 (1): 90–109.
Ernst, G. 2010. Tommaso Campanella: The revolution of knowledge from the prison. In Philosophers of the Renaissance, ed. R. Blum. Catholic University of America Press.
Fechner, G. 1848. Nanna, or on the Soul-Life of Plants. In Religion of a Scientist, ed. R. Lowrie (Pantheon, 1946).
Fechner, G. 1861. On the Soul-Question. In Religion of a Scientist, ed. R. Lowrie (Pantheon, 1946).
Feigl, H. 1958. The “mental” and the “physical.” In Concepts, Theories, and the Mind-Body Problem, ed. H. Feigl et al. University of Minnesota Press.
Feigl, H. 1960. Mind-body, not a pseudo-problem. In Dimensions of Mind, ed. S. Hook. New York University Press.
Ferenczi, S. 1926. Further Contributions to the Theory and Technique of Psycho-Analysis. Reprint: Hogarth, 1950.
Fierz, M. 1983. Girolamo Cardano. Birkhauser.
Ford, L. 1984. The Emergence of Whitehead’s Metaphysics. SUNY Press.
Ford, L. 1987. From pre-panpsychism to pansubjectivity. In Faith and Creativity, ed. G. Nordgulen. CBP.
Ford, L. 1995. Panpsychism and the early history of prehension. Process Studies 24: 15–33.
Ford, M. 1981. William James: Panpsychist and metaphysical realist. Trans Peirce Society 17: 158–170.
Ford, M. 1982. William James’ Philosophy. University of Massachusetts Press.
Foster, J. 1982. The Case for Idealism. Routledge and Kegan Paul.
Francoeur, R. 1961. The World of Teilhard. Helicon.
Freeman, K. 1948. Ancilla to the Pre-Socratic Philosophers. Blackwell.
Freudenthal, G. 1995. Aristotle’s Theory of Material Substance. Clarendon.
Friedman, H. 1986. Sun and Earth. Scientific American Library.
Frisina, W. 1997. Minds, bodies, experience, nature: Is panpsychism really dead? In Pragmatism, Neo-Pragmatism, and Religion, ed. C. Hardwick. Lang.
Fuller, B. 1945. A History of Philosophy. Holt.
Gaskin, J., ed. 1994. The Elements of Law, Natural and Politic. Oxford University Press.
Giglioni, G. 1995. Panpsychism versus hylozoism: An interpretation of some seventeenth-century doctrines of universal animation. Acta Comeniana 11: 25–44.
Giglioni, G. 2002. Francis Glisson’s notion of confoederatio naturae in the context of hylozoistic corpuscularism. Revue d’Histoire des Sciences 55 (2): 239–262.
Giglioni, G. 2010. The first of the moderns or the last of the ancients? Bernardino Telesio on nature and sentience. Bruniana e Campanelliana 16 (1): 69–87.
Gilbert, W. 1600. On the Magnet (De magnete). Reprint: Dover, 1958.
Gill, M., and Lennox, J., eds. 1994. Self-Motion: From Aristotle to Newton. Princeton University Press.
Globus, G. 1972. Biological foundations of the psychoneural identify hypothesis. Philosophy of Science 39: 291–301.
Globus, G. 1973. Unexpected symmetries in the “world knot.” Science 108 (4091): 1129–1136.
Globus, G. 1976. Mind, structure, and contradiction. In Consciousness and the Brain, ed. G. Globus et al. Plenum.
Globus, G. 2009. Halting the descent into panpsychism: A quantum thermofield theoretical perspective. In Mind That Abides: Panpsychism in the New Millennium, ed. D. Skrbina. John Benjamins.
Goff, P. 2009. Why panpsychism doesn’t help us explain consciousness. Dialectica 63 (3): 289–311.
Goff, P. 2014. Orthodox property dualism + linguistic theory of vagueness = panpsychism. In Consciousness Inside and Out, ed. R. Brown. Springer.
Goff, P. 2015. Against constitutive forms of Russellian monism. In Consciousness in the Physical World, ed. T. Alter and Y. Nagasawa. Oxford University Press.
Goethe, W. 1828. Commentary on the aphoristic essay “Nature. In Scientific Studies: Johann Wolfgang von Goethe, ed. D. Miller (Suhrkamp, 1988).
Greene, R. 1962. Henry More and Robert Boyle on the spirit of nature. Journal of the History of Ideas 23: 451–474.
Griffin, D. R. 1977. Whitehead’s philosophy and some general notions of physics and biology. In Mind in Nature, ed. J. Cobb and D. Griffin. University Press of America.
Griffin, D. R. 1988a. Introduction: The reenchantment of science. In The Reenchantment of Science, ed. D. Griffin. SUNY Press.
Griffin, D. R. 1988b. Of minds and molecules. In The Reenchantment of Science, ed. D. Griffin. SUNY Press.
Griffin, D. R. 1997. Panexperientialist physicalism and the mind-body problem. Journal of Consciousness Studies 4 (3): 248–268.
Griffin, D. R. 1998. Unsnarling the World Knot. University of California Press.
Guthrie, W. 1962–1981. History of Greek Philosophy, volumes 1–6. Cambridge University Press.
Guthrie, K. 1988. The Pythagorean Sourcebook and Library. Phanes.
Haeckel, E. 1868/1876. The History of Creation. Routledge.
Haeckel, E. 1892. Our monism. Monist 2 (4): 481–486.
Haeckel, E. 1895. Monism as Connecting Religion and Science. A. and C. Black.
Haeckel, E. 1899. The Riddle of the Universe. Reprint: Watts, 1929.
Haeckel, E. 1904. The Wonders of Life. Watts.
Haldane, J. B. S. 1932. The Inequality of Man. Chatto & Windus.
Haldane, J. B. S. 1934. Quantum mechanics as a basis for philosophy. Philosophy of Science 1: 78–98.
Halton, E. 2005. Peircean animism and the end of civilization. Contemporary Pragmatism 2 (1): 136–166.
Hameroff, S. 1994. Quantum coherence in microtubules. Journal of Consciousness Studies 1: 91–118.
Hameroff, S. 1998a. Funda-mentality: Is the conscious mind subtly linked to a basic level of the universe? Trends in Cognitive Sciences 2 (4): 119–127.
Hameroff, S. 1998b. More neural than thou. In Toward a Science of Consciousness II, ed. S. Hameroff et al. MIT Press.
Hameroff, S. 2009. The conscious connection: A psycho-physical bridge between brain and pan-experiential quantum geometry. In Mind That Abides: Panpsychism in the New Millennium, ed. D. Skrbina. John Benjamins.
Hameroff, S., and Penrose, R. 1996. Conscious events as orchestrated space-time selections. Journal of Consciousness Studies 3 (1): 36–53.
Hamilton, A. 1990. Ernst Mach and the elimination of subjectivity. Ratio 3 (2): 117–133.
Hamlyn, D. 1980. Schopenhauer: The Arguments of the Philosophers. Routledge.
Hampshire, S. 1951. Spinoza. Penguin.
Hampshire, S. 2002. The Spinoza solution. New York Review of Books, October 24: 55–56.
Harman, G. 2002. Tool-Being: Heidegger and the Metaphysics of Objects. Open Court.
Harris, E. 1973. Body-mind relation in Spinoza’s philosophy. In Spinoza’s Metaphysics, ed. J. Wilbur. Van Gorcum.
von Hartmann, E. 1869. Philosophy of the Unconscious. Reprint: Routledge, 1950.
Hartshorne, C. 1936. The compound individual. In Whitehead’s Philosophy: Selected Essays (University of Nebraska Press, 1972)
Hartshorne, C. 1937. Beyond Humanism. Willett, Clark.
Hartshorne, C. 1949. Chance, love, incompatibility. Philosophical Review 58 (5): 429–450.
Hartshorne, C. 1950. Panpsychism. In A History of Philosophical Systems, ed. V. Ferm. Philosophical Library.
Hartshorne, C. 1977. Physics and psychics. In Mind in Nature, ed. J. Cobb Jr. and D. Griffin. University Press of America.
Hartshorne, C. 1979. The rights of the subhuman world. Environmental Ethics 1: 49–60.
Hartshorne, C. 1990. The Darkness and the Light. SUNY Press.
Harvey, G. 2005. Animism: Respecting the Living World. Columbia University Press.
Harvey, G. 2015. The Handbook of Contemporary Animism. Routledge.
Heidegger, M. 1927. Being and Time. Reprint: SUNY Press, 1996.
Heidelberger, M. 2004. Nature from Within: Gustav Theodor Fechner and his Psychophysical Worldview. University of Pittsburgh Press.
Henry, J. 1987. Medicine and pneumatology: Henry More, Richard Baxter, and Francis Glisson’s Treatise on the Energetic Nature of Substance. Medical History 31: 15–40.
Henry, J. 2001. Animism and empiricism: Copernican physics and the origins of William Gilbert’s experimental method. Journal of the History of Ideas 62 (1): 99–119.
Henry, J. 2011. Omnipotence and thinking matter. In Materia: XIII Colloquio Internazionale, ed. D. Giovanozzi and M. Veneziana. Leo S. Olschiki Editore.
Herbert, G. 1989. Thomas Hobbes: The Unity of Scientific and Moral Wisdom. University of British Columbia Press.
Herder, J. 1778. On the Cognition and Sensation of the Human Soul. In Philosophical Writings: Johann Gottfried von Herder, ed. M. Forster (Cambridge University Press, 2002).
Hill, K. 2007. Nietzsche: A Guide for the Perplexed. Continuum.
Hobbes, T. 1655. On the Body (De corpore). In The English Works of Thomas Hobbes, ed. W. Molesworth (Bohn, 1839).
Hoeffding, H. 1908. A History of Modern Philosophy, volume 1. Macmillan.
Holman, E. 2008. Panpsychism, physicalism, neutral monism, and the Russellian theory of mind. Journal of Consciousness Studies 15 (5): 48–67.
Houser, N. 2014. The intelligible universe. Biosemiotics 11: 9–32.
Howe, R., et al. 2000. Dynamic variations at the base of the solar convection zone. Science 287 (5462): 2456–2460.
Humphrey, N. 1992. A History of the Mind. Chatto & Windus.
Hut, P., and Shepard, R. 1996. Turning the “hard problem” upside down and sideways. Journal of Consciousness Studies 3 (4): 313–329.
Hutto, D. 2000. Beyond Physicalism. Benjamins.
Huxley, J. 1942. The biologist looks at man. Fortune, December.
Ingegno, A. 1998. Introduction. In Cause, Principle, and Unity, ed. G. Bruno. Cambridge University Press.
Inwood, B., and Gerson, L. 1997. Hellenistic Philosophy. Hackett.
James, W. 1890. Principles of Psychology. Reprint: Dover, 1950.
James, W. 1902. Varieties of Religious Experience. Collier.
James, W. 1909. A Pluralistic Universe. Reprint: University of Nebraska Press, 1996.
James, W. 1911a. Some Problems of Philosophy. Reprint: Greenwood, 1968.
James, W. 1911b. Memories and Studies. Longmans, Green.
James, W. 1912. Essays in Radical Empiricism. Reprint: University of Nebraska Press, 1996.
James, W. 1920. Letters of William James. Atlantic Monthly Press.
Jammer, M. 1957. Concepts of Force. Harvard University Press.
Janaway, C. 2007. Beyond Selflessness. Oxford University Press.
Jeans, J. 1932. The Mysterious Universe. Macmillan.
Jeans, J. 1942. Physics and Philosophy. University of Michigan Press.
Joachim, H. 1901. A Study of the Ethics of Spinoza. Reprint: Russell & Russell, 1964.
Jung, C. G., and Pauli, W. 1955. The Interpretation of Nature and the Psyche. Routledge.
Kant, I. 1766. Dreams of a Spirit-Seer. Reprint: Macmillan, 1900.
Kant, I. 1781. Critique of Pure Reason. Reprint: St. Martin’s Press, 1965.
Kant, I. 1790. Critique of Judgment. Reprint: Hafner, 1951.
Kauffman, S. 2016a. Humanity in a Creative Universe. Oxford University Press.
Kauffman, S. 2016b. Cosmic mind? Theology and Science 14 (1): 36–47.
Kaufmann, W. 1950. Nietzsche: Philosopher, Psychologist, Antichrist. Princeton University Press.
Kaufmann, W. 1967/1972. Nietzsche. In The Encyclopedia of Philosophy, ed. P. Edwards. Macmillan.
Kepler, J. 1618. Harmonies of the World. Reprint: Prometheus Books, 1995.
Kerr-Lawson, A. 1984. Spirit’s primary nature is to be secondary. Bulletin of the Santayana Society 2: 9–14.
Kind, A. 2015. Pessimism about Russellian monism. In Consciousness in the Physical World, ed. T. Alter and Y. Nagasawa. Oxford University Press.
Kirk, G., et al. 1983. The Presocratic Philosophers. Cambridge University Press.
Klausner, N. 1967. Charles A. Strong, realist and panpsychist. Monist 51: 267–283.
Klemm, D., and Klink, W. 2008. Consciousness and quantum mechanics. Zygon 43 (2): 307–327.
Koch, C. 2012. Consciousness: Confessions of a Romantic Reductionist. MIT Press.
Koch, C. 2013. Ubiquitous minds. Scientific American Mind 25: 26–29.
Koestler, A. 1967. The Ghost in the Machine. Macmillan.
Koestler, A. 1978. Janus. Random House.
Kristeller, P. 1964. Eight Philosophers of the Italian Renaissance. Stanford University Press.
Kuelpe, O. 1913. Philosophy of the Present in Germany. Allen.
Kuklick, B. 1977. The Rise of American Philosophy. Yale University Press.
LaMettrie, J. 1745. Natural History of the Soul. In Machine Man and Other Writings, ed. A. Thomson. Reprint: Cambridge University Press, 1996.
LaMettrie, J. 1747. Man, a Machine. (L’Homme Machine). In Man a Machine: And, Man a Plant, ed. R. Watson and M. Rybalka (Hackett, 1994).
LaMettrie, J. 1748. Man, a Plant. (L’Homme Plante). In Man a Machine: And, Man a Plant, ed. R. Watson and M. Rybalka (Hackett, 1994).
Lang, K. 1995. Sun, Earth, and Sky. Springer.
Leibniz, G. 1686a. Primary Truths. In Philosophical Essays, ed. R. Ariew and D. Garber (Hackett, 1989).
Leibniz, G. 1686b. Letter to Arnauld. In Philosophical Essays, ed. R. Ariew and D. Garber (Hackett, 1989).
Leibniz, G. 1687. Letter to Arnauld. In Philosophical Essays, ed. R. Ariew and D. Garber (Hackett, 1989).
Leibniz, G. 1690. Notes on some comments by Michel Angelo Fardela. In Philosophical Essays, ed. R. Ariew and D. Garber (Hackett, 1989).
Leibniz, G. 1695. A New System of Nature. In Philosophical Essays, ed. R. Ariew and D. Garber (Hackett, 1989).
Leibniz, G. 1698. On Nature Itself. In Philosophical Papers and Letters, ed. L. Loemker (University of Chicago Press, 1956).
Leibniz, G. 1707. Comments on Spinoza’s philosophy. In Philosophical Essays, ed. R. Ariew and D. Garber (Hackett, 1989).
Leibniz, G. 1714a. Principles of Nature and of Grace. In Philosophical Essays, ed. R. Ariew and D. Garber (Hackett, 1989).
Leibniz, G. 1714b. The monadology. In Philosophical Essays, ed. R. Ariew and D. Garber (Hackett, 1989).
Leibniz, G. 1716. Letter to Des Bosses. In Philosophical Essays, ed. R. Ariew and D. Garber (Hackett, 1989).
Leibniz, G. 1989. Philosophical Essays, ed. R. Ariew and D. Garber. Hackett.
Leinkauf, T. 2010. Francesco Patrizi: New philosophies of history, poetry, and the world. In Philosophers of the Renaissance, ed. R. Blum. Catholic University of America Press.
Leiter, B. 2013. Nietzsche’s naturalism reconsidered. In The Oxford Handbook of Nietzsche, ed. K. Gemes and J. Richardson. Oxford University Press.
Leopold, A. 1979. Some fundamentals of conservation in the southwest. Environmental Ethics 1 (2): 131–141.
Lewis, D. 1966. An argument for the identity theory. Journal of Philosophy 63: 17–25.
Lewtas, P. 2015. Russellian panpsychism: Too good to be true? American Philosophical Quarterly 52 (1): 57–71.
Lloyd, A. C. 1959. Parmenides. In Encyclopædia Britannica. Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
Locke, J. 1689. An Essay Concerning Human Understanding. Reprint: Dutton, 1964.
Lockwood, M. 1989. Mind, Brain, and the Quantum. Blackwell.
Loeb, P. 2015. Will to power and panpsychism. In Nietzsche on Mind and Nature, ed. M. Dries and P. Kail. Oxford University Press.
Long, A. A. 1974. Hellenistic Philosophy. Duckworth.
Long, A. A. 1996. Parmenides on thinking being. Boston Proceedings on Ancient Philosophy 12: 125–151.
Lossky, N. 1901. Kozlov i Yevo panpsikhism. Voprosy filosofi i psikhologii 58: 198–202.
Lossky, N. 1906. The Intuitive Basis of Knowledge. In A History of Russian Philosophy, ed. V. Kuvakin (Prometheus Books, 1994).
Lossky, N. 1917/1928. The World as an Organic Whole. Oxford University Press.
Lossky, N. 1951. History of Russian Philosophy. International Universities Press.
Lotze, R. H. 1971. Microcosmos. T. & T. Clark.
Lucretius. 1977. The Nature of Things (De rerum natura). Norton.
Lycan, W. 2011. Recent naturalistic dualisms. In Light Against Darkness, ed. A. Lange et al. Vandenhoeck & Ruprecht.
Mach, E. 1883. The Science of Mechanics. Reprint: Open Court, 1942.
Madden, E., and Hare, P. 1971. The powers that be. Dialogue 10, 12–30.
Madell, G. 1988. Mind and Materialism. Edinburgh University Press.
Magee, B. 1983. The Philosophy of Schopenhauer. Oxford University Press.
Manjaly, J. 2009. Panpsychic presuppositions of Samkhya metaphysics. In Mind That Abides: Panpsychism in the New Millennium, ed. D. Skrbina. John Benjamins.
Martin, C., and Pfeifer, K. 1986. Intentionality and the non-psychological. Philosophy and Phenomenological Research 46: 531–556.
Marx, W. 1984. The Philosophy of F. W. J. Schelling. Indiana University Press.
Mathews, F. 1998. The real, the one and the many in ecological thought. In Spirit of the Environment, ed. J. Palmer and D. Cooper. Routledge.
Mathews, F. 2003. For Love of Matter. SUNY Press.
Maxwell, G. 1978. Rigid designators and mind-brain identity. Minnesota Studies in the Philosophy of Science 9: 365–403.
McCarthy, J. 1979. Ascribing mental qualities to machines. In Philosophical Perspectives in Artificial Intelligence, ed. M. Ringle. Humanities Press.
McDaniel, J. 1983. Physical matter as creative and sentient. Environmental Ethics 5: 291–317.
McDougall, W. 1920. Body and Mind: A History and a Defense of Animism. Macmillan.
McGinn, C. 1991. The Problem of Consciousness. Blackwell.
McGinn, C. 1997. Character of Mind. Oxford University Press.
McGinn, C. 1999. The Mysterious Flame. Basic Books.
McGinn, C. 2006. Hard questions. In Consciousness and its Place in Nature, ed. A. Freeman. Imprint Academic.
McGuire, J. 1968. Force, active principles, and Newton’s invisible realm. Ambix 15 (3): 154–208.
McGuire, J. 1994. Natural motion and its causes: Newton on the ‘Vis Insita’ of bodies. In Self-Motion, ed. M. Gill and J. Lennox. Princeton University Press.
McHenry, L. 1995. Whitehead’s panpsychism as the subjectivity of prehension. Process Studies 24: 1–14.
McHenry, L. 2010. Sprigge’s ontology of consciousness. In The Metaphysics of Consciousness, ed. P. Basile, J. Kiverstein, and P. Phemister. Cambridge University Press.
McRae, R. 1981. Life, vis inertiae, and the mechanical philosophy. In Pragmatism and Purpose, ed. L. Sumner et al. University of Toronto Press.
Merchant, C. 1979. The Death of Nature. Harper & Row.
Merleau-Ponty, M. 1945. Phenomenology of Perception. Reprint: Routledge, 1962
Monod, J. 1971. Chance and Necessity. Random House.
Montague, W. 1905. Panpsychism and monism. Journal of Philosophy 2 (23): 626–629.
Montague, W. 1912. A realistic theory of truth and error. In New Realism, ed. H. Holt. Macmillan.
Montague, W. 1945. Human soul and cosmic mind. Mind 54 (213): 50–65.
Moore, G. 2002. Nietzsche, Biology, and Metaphor. Cambridge University Press.
Naess, A. 1975. Freedom, Emotion, and Self-Subsistence. Universitetsforl.
Nagel, T. 1974. What is it like to be a bat? Philosophical Review 83 (4): 435–450.
Nagel, T. 1979. Mortal Questions. Cambridge University Press.
Nagel, T. 1986. The View from Nowhere. Oxford University Press.
Nagel, T. 2002. Concealment and Exposure. Oxford University Press.
Nagel, T. 2012. Mind and Cosmos. Oxford University Press.
Nash, R. 1975. The significance of the arrangement of the deck chairs on the Titanic (the extension of ethics and humanity). Not Man Apart 5, October: 7–9. Reprinted in Earthworks, ed. M. Van Deventer (Friends of the Earth, 1980).
Nash, R. 1977. Do rocks have rights? The Center Magazine 10 (November/December): 2–12.
Naydler, J. 1996. Goethe on Science. Floris Books.
Nehamas, A. 1985. Nietzsche: Life as Literature. Harvard University Press.
Newton, I. 1687. Principia (The Mathematical Principles of Natural Philosophy). Reprint: University of California Press, 1934.
Nietzsche, F. 1883. Thus Spoke Zarathustra. In The Portable Nietzsche, ed. W. Kaufmann (Penguin, 1954).
Nietzsche, F. 1886. Beyond Good and Evil. Reprint: Penguin, 1973.
Nietzsche, F. 1887. On the Genealogy of Morals. Reprint: Oxford University Press, 1996.
Nietzsche, F. 1906. The Will to Power. Reprint: Random House, 1967.
Nietzsche, F. 1954. Werke, ed. K. Schlechta. Carl Hanser Verlag.
Nietzsche, F. 1979. Philosophy and Truth, ed. D. Breazeale. Humanities Press.
Nietzsche, F. 2003. Writings from the Late Notebooks, ed. R. Bittner. Cambridge University Press.
Nisbet, H. 1970. Herder and the Philosophy and History of Science. Modern Humanities Research Association.
O’Brien, J. 1958. Gravity and love as unifying principles. Thomist 21: 184–193.
O’Brien, J. 1988. Teilhard’s view of nature and some implications for environmental ethics. Environmental Ethics 10: 329–346.
Orr, E. 2012. Wakeful World: Animism, Mind, and the Self in Nature. Moon Books.
Ouspensky, P. 1912. Tertium Organum. Reprint: Routledge, 1981.
Pagel, W. 1982. Paracelsus. Karger.
Paracelsus, P. 1894. Concerning the nature of things. In The Hermetic and Alchemical Writings of Aureolus Philippus Theophrastus Bombast. J. Elliot.
Parkes, G. 1994. Composing the Soul. University of Chicago Press.
Parkes, G. 2009. The awareness of rocks: East-Asian understandings and implications. In Mind That Abides: Panpsychism in the New Millennium, ed. D. Skrbina. John Benjamins.
Parkinson, G. 1953. Spinoza’s Theory of Knowledge. Clarendon.
Partridge, E. 1984. Nature as a moral resource. Environmental Ethics 6 (2): 101–130.
Paulsen, F. 1892/1895. Introduction to Philosophy. Holt.
Peck, A. 1943. Bibliographic footnotes. In Aristotle, Generation of Animals. Harvard University Press.
Peirce, C. S. 1891. The architecture of theories. Monist 1, no. 1: 161–176. In The Essential Peirce, volume 1, ed. N. House and C. Kloesel (Indiana University Press, 1992).
Peirce, C. S. 1892a. The doctrine of necessity examined. Monist 2, no. 1: 321–337. In The Essential Peirce, volume 1, ed. N. House and C. Kloesel (Indiana University Press, 1992).
Peirce, C. S. 1892b. The law of mind. Monist 2, no. 2: 533–559. In The Essential Peirce, volume 1, ed. N. House and C. Kloesel (Indiana University Press, 1992).
Peirce, C. S. 1892c. Man’s glassy essence. Monist 3, no. 1: 1–22. In The Essential Peirce, volume 1, ed. N. House and C. Kloesel (Indiana University Press, 1992).
Peirce, C. S. 1934. Collected Papers of Charles Sanders Peirce. Cambridge University Press.
Peirce, C. S. 1992a. The Essential Peirce, volume 1, ed. N. House and C. Kloesel. Indiana University Press.
Peirce, C. S. 1992b. The Essential Peirce, volume 2, ed. N. House and C. Kloesel. Indiana University Press.
Peirce, C. S. 1993. Reasoning and the Logic of Things. Harvard University Press.
Penrose, R. 1989. Emperor’s New Mind. Oxford University Press.
Penrose, R. 1994a. Mechanisms, microtubules, and the mind. Journal of Consciousness Studies 1 (2): 241–249.
Penrose, R. 1994b. Shadows of the Mind. Oxford University Press.
Perry, H. 1968. The First Duchess of Newcastle. Johnson Reprint.
Perry, R. 1935. Thought and Character of William James. Little, Brown.
Plato. 1997. Complete Works, ed. J. Cooper. Hackett.
Plato. 1953. Sophist. Clarendon.
Plumwood, V. 1993. Feminism and the Mastery of Nature. Routledge.
Plumwood, V. 1998. Intentional recognition and reductive rationality. Environmental Values 7: 397–421.
Plumwood, V. 2002. Environmental Culture. Routledge.
Poellner, P. 1995. Nietzsche and Metaphysics. Oxford University Press.
Popper, K., and Eccles, J. 1977. The Self and Its Brain. Springer.
Porter, J. 2006. Nietzsche’s theory of the will to power. In A Companion to Nietzsche, ed. K. Pearson. Blackwell.
Priestley, J. 1777. Disquisitions relating to matter and spirit. In The Theological and Miscellaneous Works of Joseph Priestly, ed. J. Rutt. Reprint: Kraus, 1972.
Prince, M. 1885. The Nature of Mind and the Human Automatism. In The Origins of Psychology, volume 1 (Alan R. Liss, 1975).
Prince, M. 1904. The identification of mind and matter. Philosophical Review 13 (4): 444–451.
Reeve, C., and Miller, P., eds. 2006. Introductory Readings in Ancient Greek and Roman Philosophy. Hackett.
Reginster, B. 2012. Replies to my critics. Journal of Nietzsche Studies 43 (1): 130–140.
Rensch, B. 1960. Evolution above the Species Level. Columbia University Press.
Rensch, B. 1971. Biophilosophy. Columbia University Press.
Rensch, B. 1972. Spinoza’s identify theory and modern biophilosophy. Philosophical Forum 3: 193–207.
Rensch, B. 1977. Arguments for panpsychistic identism. In Mind in Nature, ed. J. Cobb and D. Griffin. University Press of America.
Richardson, J. 2000. Clark on will to power. International Studies in Philosophy 32 (3): 107–117.
Rist, J. 1989. The Mind of Aristotle. Phoenix series, volume 25. University of Toronto Press.
Robinson, E. 1949. Animism as a world hypothesis. Philosophical Review 58: 53–63.
Rockwell, T. 2013. Mind or mechanism: Which came first? In Origins of Mind, ed. L. Swan. Springer.
Rorty, R. 1995. Dewey between Hegel and Darwin. In Rorty and Pragmatism, ed. H. Saatkamp. Vanderbilt University Press.
Rosenberg, G. 1996. Rethinking nature. Journal of Consciousness Studies 3 (1): 76–88.
Rosenberg, G. 2004. A Place for Consciousness. Oxford University Press.
Rosenberg, G. 2015. Causality and the combination problem. In Consciousness in the Physical World, ed. T. Alter and Y. Nagasawa. Oxford University Press.
Royce, J. 1892. Spirit of Modern Philosophy. Reprint: Houghton Miffin, 1955.
Royce, J. 1898. Studies of Good and Evil. Reprint: Appleton, 1915.
Royce, J. 1899–1901. The World and the Individual. Macmillan.
Russell, B. 1915. Ultimate constituents of matter. In Realism and the Background of Phenomenology, ed. R. Chisolm. Reprint: Free Press, 1960.
Russell, B. 1921. The Analysis of Mind. Routledge.
Russell, B. 1927a. The Analysis of Matter. Routledge.
Russell, B. 1927b. An Outline of Philosophy. Allen and Unwin.
Russell, B. 1940/1949. An Inquiry into Meaning and Truth. Norton.
Russell, B. 1956. Portraits from Memory. Allen and Unwin.
Salter, W. 1922. Panpsychism and freedom. Philosophical Review 31 (3): 285–287.
Sambursky, S. 1959. The Physics of the Stoics. Routledge.
Sandbach, F. 1975. The Stoics. Chatto & Windus.
Schelling, F. 1797. Ideas for a Philosophy of Nature. Reprint: Cambridge University Press, 1988.
Schelling, F. 1800. System of Transcendental Idealism. Reprint: University Press of Virginia, 1978.
Schiller, F. 1891. Riddles of the Sphinx. S. Sonnenschein.
Schiller, F. 1907. Studies in Humanism. Macmillan.
Schiller, F. 1929. Logic for Use. G. Bell.
Schilpp, P., ed. 1941. The Philosophy of Alfred North Whitehead. Northwestern University Press.
Schleicher, D. 2013. Interview with John Horton Conway. Notices of the American Mathematical Society 60 (5): 567–575.
Schnadelbach, H. 1984. Philosophy in Germany: 1831–1933. Cambridge University Press.
Schopenhauer, A. 1819. The World as Will and Idea. Reprint: J. M. Dent, 1995.
Schopenhauer, A. 1819. The World as Will and Representation, volume 1. Reprint: Dover, 1969
Schopenhauer, A. 1836. On the Will in Nature, ed. D. Cartwright (Berg, 1993).
Schopenhauer, A. 1851. Parerga and Paralipomena, ed. D. Cartwright (Clarendon, 1974).
Schweitzer, A. 1949. The Philosophy of Civilization. Macmillan.
Seager, W. 1991. Metaphysics of Consciousness. Routledge.
Seager, W. 1995. Consciousness, information, and panpsychism. Journal of Consciousness Studies 2 (3): 272–288.
Seager, W. 1999. Theories of Consciousness. Routledge.
Seager, W. 2001. Panpsychism. Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy (online), summer 2001 edition.
Seager, W. 2009. Panpsychism. In The Oxford Handbook of Philosophy of Mind, ed. A. Beckermann et al. Oxford University Press.
Seager, W. 2010. Panpsychism, aggregation, and combinatorial infusion. Mind and Matter 8 (2): 167–184.
Searle, J. 1997. Consciousness and the philosophers. New York Review of Books 44 (4): 43–50.
Searle, J. 2013. Can information theory explain consciousness? New York Review of Books 60 (1).
Sellars, R. 1960. Panpsychism or evolutionary materialism. Philosophy of Science 27: 329–350.
Shani, I. 2010. Mind stuffed with red herrings: Why William James’ critique of the mind-stuff theory does not substantiate a combination problem for panpsychism. Acta Analytica 25 (4): 413–434.
Sharpe, R. 1989. Dennett’s journey towards panpsychism. Inquiry 32 (2): 233–240.
Sheldrake, R. 1990. The Rebirth of Nature. Century.
Sherrington, C. 1941. Man on His Nature. Macmillan.
Sherrington, C. 1949. Goethe on Nature and on Science. Cambridge University Press.
Singer, D. 1950. Giordano Bruno. Schuman.
Skolimowski, H. 1990. The world as sanctuary. [summer]. Quest.
Skolimowski, H. 1992. Living Philosophy: Eco-Philosophy as a Tree of Life. Arkana/Penguin.
Skolimowski, H. 1993. A Sacred Place to Dwell. Element Books.
Skolimowski, H. 1994. The Participatory Mind. Arkana/Penguin.
Skrbina, D. 1994. Participatory chaos: An analytic model of consciousness. In Coherence and Chaos in our Uncommon Futures, ed. M. Mannermaa et al. Finland Future Research Centre.
Skrbina, D. 2003. Panpsychism as an underlying theme in western philosophy. Journal of Consciousness Studies 10 (3): 4–46.
Skrbina, D. 2006. Beyond Descartes: Panpsychism revisited. Axiomathes 16: 387–423.
Skrbina, D. 2008. On the problem of the aggregate. In Chromatikon IV. Presses Universitaires de Louvain.
Skrbina, D. 2009a. Panpsychism in history: An overview. In Mind That Abides: Panpsychism in the New Millennium, ed. D. Skrbina. John Benjamins.
Skrbina, D. 2009b. Minds, objects, and relations: Toward a dual-aspect ontology. In Mind That Abides: Panpsychism in the New Millennium, ed. D. Skrbina. John Benjamins.
Skrbina, D. 2009c. Transcending consciousness: Thoughts on a universal conception of mind. Journal of Consciousness Studies 16 (5): 79–87.
Skrbina, D. 2010. Whitehead and the ubiquity of mind. In Chromatikon VI. Presses Universitaires de Louvain.
Skrbina, D. 2011. Mind space: Toward a solution to the combination problem. In The Mental as Fundamental, ed. M. Blamauer. Ontos Verlag.
Skrbina, D. 2013. Ethics, eco-philosophy, and universal sympathy. Dialogue and Universalism 23 (4): 59–74.
Skrbina, D. 2014. Dualism, dual-aspectism, and the mind. In Contemporary Dualism, ed. A. Lavazza and H. Robinson. Routledge.
Skrbina, D. 2015. The Metaphysics of Technology. Routledge.
Smart, J. J. C. 1959. Sensations and brain processes. Philosophical Review 68: 141–156.
Smith, T. V. 1934. From Thales to Plato. Chicago University Press.
Spencer, H. 1855. Principles of Psychology, volume 1. Reprint: Appleton, 1897.
Spencer, H. 1884. Religion: A retrospect and prospect. Nineteenth Century 15 (83): 1–12.
Spinoza, B. 1674. Letter to Schuller (#58). In A Spinoza Reader, ed. E. Curley (Princeton University Press, 1994).
Spinoza, B. 1677. Ethics. In A Spinoza Reader, ed. E. Curley (Princeton University Press, 1994).
Sprigge, T. 1983. Vindication of Absolute Idealism. Edinburgh University Press.
Sprigge, T. 1984. Santayana and panpsychism. Bulletin of the Santayana Society 2: 1–18.
Sprigge, T. 1991a. Are there intrinsic values in nature? In Applied Philosophy, ed. B. Almond and D. Hill. Routledge.
Sprigge, T. 1991b. Some recent positions in environmental ethics examined. Inquiry 34: 107–128.
Sprigge, T. 1993. James and Bradley. Open Court.
Sprigge, T. 1998a. Panpsychism. In Encyclopedia of Philosophy, ed. E. Craig. Routledge.
Sprigge, T. 1998b. Idealism. In Encyclopedia of Philosophy, ed. E. Craig. Routledge.
Stack, G. 2005. Nietzsche’s Anthropic Circle. University of Rochester Press.
Starchenko, N. 1994. Nikolai Lossky. In A History of Russian Philosophy, ed. V. Kuvakin. Prometheus Books.
Stone, C. 1972. Should trees have standing? Towards legal rights for natural objects. Southern California Law Review 45: 450–501.
Stout, G. 1919a. Mind & Matter. Reprint: Cambridge University Press, 1931.
Stout, G. 1919b. God & Nature. Reprint: Cambridge University Press, 1952.
Strawson, G. 1994. Mental Reality. MIT Press.
Strawson, G. 2003a. Real materialism. In Chomsky and His Critics, ed. L. Antony and N. Hornstein. Blackwell.
Strawson, G. 2003b. What is the relation between an experience, the subject of the experience, and the content of the experience? Philosophical Issues 13: 279–315.
Strawson, G. 2006a. Realistic monism: Why physicalism entails panpsychism. Journal of Consciousness Studies 13, no. 10–11: 3–31. Reprinted with same pagination in Consciousness and its Place in Nature, ed. A. Freeman. Imprint Academic.
Strawson, G. 2006b. Panpsychism? Reply to commentators with a celebration of Descartes. Journal of Consciousness Studies 13 (10–11): 184–280.
Strawson, G. 2009. Realistic monism: Why physicalism entails panpsychism. (Revision of Strawson 2006). In Mind That Abides, ed. D. Skrbina. John Benjamins.
Strawson, G. 2015a. Real materialism (with new postscript). In Consciousness in the Physical World, ed. T. Alter and Y. Nagasawa. Oxford University Press.
Strawson, G. 2015b. Nietzsche’s metaphysics? In Nietzsche on Mind and Nature, ed. M. Dries and P. Kail. Oxford University Press.
Strawson, G. 2015c. Letters to the editor. Times Literary Supplement 20 (March).
Strong, C. 1903. Why the Mind Has a Body. Macmillan.
Strong, C. 1904a. Dr. Morton Prince and panpsychism. Psychological Review 11: 67–69.
Strong, C. 1904b. Reply to Professor Bakewell. Philosophical Review 13 (3): 337–342.
Strong, C. 1918. Origin of Consciousness. Macmillan.
Strong, C. 1937. A Creed for Skeptics. Macmillan.
Stubenberg, L. 2015. Russell, Russellian monism, and panpsychism. In Consciousness in the Physical World, ed. T. Alter and Y. Nagasawa. Oxford University Press.
Tallmadge, K. 1944. Nous and naturalism. New Scholasticism 18 (2): 185–196.
Teale, E. 1976. The Wilderness World of John Muir. Houghton Mifflin.
Teilhard de Chardin, P. 1941. The atomism of spirit. In Teilhard, Activation of Energy (Collins, 1970).
Teilhard de Chardin, P. 1947. The place of technology. In Teilhard, Activation of Energy (Collins, 1970).
Teilhard de Chardin, P. 1950. The Heart of Matter. Reprint: Harcourt Brace Jovanovich, 1979.
Teilhard de Chardin, P. 1952. The reflection of energy. In Teilhard, Activation of Energy (Collins, 1970).
Teilhard de Chardin, P. 1959. The Phenomenon of Man. Harper and Row.
Teilhard de Chardin, P. 1970. Activation of Energy. Collins.
Telesio, B. 1586. On the Nature of Things (De rerum natura). In Renaissance Philosophy, volume 1, ed. A. Fallico and H. Shapiro (Random House, 1967).
Theise, N., and Kafatos, C. 2013. Sentience everywhere: Complexity theory, panpsychism, and the role of sentience in self-organization of the universe. Journal of Consciousness Exploration and Research 4 (4): 378–390.
Thiese, N., and Kafatos, C. 2016. Fundamental awareness. Communicative and Integrative Biology 9 (3): e1155010.
Thoreau, H. 1851. Journal, volume 4. Reprint: Princeton University Press, 1981.
Thoreau, H. 2000. Wild Fruits. Norton.
Tononi, G. 2012. Integrated information theory of consciousness: An updated account. Archives Italiennes de Biologie 150 (4): 293–329.
Tononi, G. 2012b. Phi: A Voyage from the Brain to the Soul. Pantheon.
Tononi, G., and Koch, C. 2015. Consciousness: Here, there, and everywhere? Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B 370, no. 1668.
Trepanier, S. 2004. Empedocles: An Interpretation. Taylor & Francis.
Troland, L. 1918. Paraphysical monism. Philosophical Review 27 (1): 39–62.
Troland, L. 1922. Psychophysics as the key to the mysteries of physics and of metaphysics. Journal of the Washington Academy of Sciences 12 (6): 141–162.
Tye, M. 2000. Consciousness, Color, and Content. MIT Press.
Uzgalis, W. 2011. The Correspondence of Samuel Clarke and Anthony Collins, 1707–08. Broadview.
Van Cleve, J. 1990. Mind-dust or magic? Panpsychism versus emergence. Philosophical Perspectives 4: 215–226.
Vartanian, A. 1960. Introduction. In J. LaMettrie, L’Homme Machine. Princeton University Press.
Velmans, M. 2007. The co-evolution of matter and consciousness. Synthesis Philosophica 44 (2): 273–282.
Vietor, K. 1950. Goethe the Thinker. Harvard University Press.
Waddington, C. 1961. The Nature of Life. Allen and Unwin.
Walker, E. 1970. The nature of consciousness. Mathematical Biosciences 7: 131–178.
Weber, M. 2009. Hypnosis: Panpsychism in action. In Handbook of Whiteheadian Process Thought, ed. M. Weber and W. Desmond. De Gruyter.
Wendt, A. 2015. Quantum Mind and Social Science. Cambridge University Press.
Wheeler, J. 1994. It from bit. In At Home in the Universe. American Institute of Physics.
Wheeler, J. 2002. John Wheeler responds. Discover 23 (8).
White, L., Jr. 1967. The historical roots of our ecologic crisis. Science 155 (3767): 1203–1207.
White, L., Jr. 1973. Continuing the conversation. In Western Man and Environmental Ethic, ed. I. Barbour. Addison-Wesley.
Whitehead, A. 1925. Science and the Modern World. Reprint: Free Press, 1967.
Whitehead, A. 1926a. Religion in the Making. Macmillan.
Whitehead, A. 1926b. Time. In L. Ford, The Emergence of Whitehead’s Metaphysic, 1925–1929 (SUNY Press, 1984).
Whitehead, A. 1929. Process and Reality. Reprint: Free Press, 1978.
Whitehead, A. 1933. Adventures of Ideas. Reprint: Free Press, 1967.
Whitehead, A. 1938. Modes of Thought. Macmillan.
Whitehead, A. 1941. Immortality. In The Philosophy of Alfred North Whitehead, ed. P. Schilpp. Northwestern University Press.
Wilber, K. 1995. Sex, Ecology, Spirituality. Shambhala.
Wilber, K. 2000. Integral Psychology. Shambhala.
Williams, L. 2001. Nietzsche’s Mirror. Rowman & Littlefield.
Wittgenstein, L. 1953. Philosophical Investigations. Macmillan.
Wolfson, H. 1937. Spinoza’s mechanism, attributes, and panpsychism. Philosophical Review 46 (3): 307–314.
Woodward, W. 1972. Fechner’s panpsychism. Journal of the History of the Behavioral Sciences 8: 367–386.
Wright, W. 1947. A History of Modern Philosophy. Macmillan.
Wright, S. 1953. Gene and organism. American Naturalist 87 (5): 5–18.
Wright, S. 1964. Biology and the philosophy of science. Monist 48: 265–290.
Wright, S. 1977. Panpsychism and science. In Mind in Nature, ed. J. Cobb and D. Griffin. University Press of America.
Wundt, W. 1892/1894. Lectures on Human and Animal Psychology. S. Sonnenschein.
Young, J. 2010. Friedrich Nietzsche: A Philosophical Biography. Cambridge University Press.
Zohar, D. 1990. The Quantum Self. Bloomsbury.